<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Sam Chisholm</title>
<link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>News updating friends and family on our journey</description>
<generator>quarto-1.2.335</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Results and returning for round 2</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-07_results-and-round2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Once again I am writing from Sam’s bedside here at BC Children’s Hospital – our second arrival. Compared with the first, this is so much easier. Sam’s health has dramatically improved and it is much easier to be in hospital when you plan to go there. We are also returning to people that know and care for Sam.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-june-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-june-7">Reflections on June 7</h2>
<p>Yesterday was a business day. Sam’s return to the hospital. We checked into the Oncology day-clinic, Sam had a few tests, we met with Dr.&nbsp;Cheng to discuss the progress made and the plans moving forward. In the afternoon Sam would receive his first chemical doses of chemo round 2<sup>1</sup>.</p>
<section id="results" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results">Results</h3>
<p>We had an opportunity to look at before and after imagery from Sam’s PET scans. I am glad I had not seen the first scans until now. The difference is dramatic.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The size and density to the cancerous mass is greatly reduced</li>
<li>The impacts on Sam’s other organs has been removed – or is minimal. The first scans showed high impacts on Sam’s lungs heart – mostly causing high levels of fluid build up and pressure. Now his lungs are now clear of fluid and only a residual amount of fluid remains around the heart – this is expected to resolve over time. 3. Currently Sam has two main masses of cancer. The main one in his chest and a smaller one in his neck. They are greatly reduced since our arrival seven weeks ago. I need to get a copy of the results again so I can quantify the amount of reduction.</li>
</ol>
<p>This is exciting – the cancer is responding to treatment.</p>
</section>
<section id="plans" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="plans">Plans</h3>
<p>It is exciting to see such progress. In moments of weakness it is also terrifying. The remains a lot of work to be done these cancerous masses are measurable in centimetres – there are billions of cancerous cells to be removed<sup>2</sup>.</p>
<p>Despite the challenges, for the first time we actually have a plan! Until now, none of us have known what the plan would be. Sam’s cancer is extremely rare, and how it would respond to treatment was not known. Now that we know the treatment is working. We will move forward with a treatment regime. The plan is to complete six rounds of chemotherapy with on-going evaluation to adapt the plan as needed.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are thankful for positive results and that Sam is doing so well.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for a plan, though we need to gear ourselves for a marathon. We have heard it said around here numerous times that this cancer journey is both a roller-coaster and a marathon.</p></li>
<li></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>This is the actual round 2. What I referred to previously as round to was actually round 1, and the very first week of chemo … well they don’t actually count that one.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p><em>cell densities in human tissues are on the order of 1 billion to 3 billion cells/ml</em>.<br>
McClelland, Randall E., Robert Dennis, Lola M. Reid, Jan P. Stegemann, Bernard Palsson, and Jeffrey M. Macdonald. “Chapter 6 - Tissue Engineering.” In Introduction to Biomedical Engineering (Third Edition), edited by John D. Enderle and Joseph D. Bronzino, 273–357. Boston: Academic Press, 2012. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-374979-6.00006-X.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-07_results-and-round2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Amazing family weekend</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-06_amazing-weekend-rmh.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/weekend-vacation.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">A family vacation weekend! Left our dinner out at Whitespot. Auntie Tina with nephew Chris and neice Jane (upper left). Right – time simply being outside.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Our break away from the hospital comes to an end today, yet we can bask in the joy that this weekend provided! We have had an incredible weekend as a family and with some of our extended family. It was amazing to see how well Sam is doing. I don’t know if the cancer i gone – but I do know that it has been dramatically reduced.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-this-past-weekend" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-this-past-weekend">Reflections on this past weekend</h2>
<section id="june-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="june-3">June 3</h3>
<p>Our first full day off. A day of rest and simply exploring the RMH (Ronald McDonald House). We also took care of all the medical items ourselves – medications and needles and NG tube feeding. We had it all down all the steps were going well – until we hit a glitch. We do not have a reason for it, and we have seen it happen a number of times while in the hospital: The NG tube clogged and this time we could not get it back. After working at it for about an hour we decided togive up for the night and pushed as much Coca-cola into it as we could (a hack that sometimes works to dissolve clogs).</p>
<p>Saturday afternoon<sup>1</sup>, we had a wonderful visit with Bob and Wendy H. Sam shocked me as he was also up for the visit. Wendy and Tina had a good catch-up, while Bob, Sam, and played on a digital game table. Sam and Bob broke the game after Sam discovered a glitch and they both exploited it.</p>
</section>
<section id="june-4" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="june-4">June 4</h3>
<p>Sunday morning the NG remained clogged. We were fairly quick to recognize that this was a blessing! Sam had a new job – to eat and ensure that he met or exceeded the calories that he would have received via the NG tube. He did not disappoint –our boy has his appetite back. About mid-afternoon, Tina pulled the tube.</p>
<p>Also in the afternoon we had some great visits. First with Uncle Kevin and then joined by cousins Chris and Jane (Cal’s children). We all chatted and hung out outside. That evening the cousins and the three of us got Sam off hospital property for the first time since this whole journey began! We got out for a meal – at the Kerrisdale White Spot where Sam had a milkshake and a double-double.</p>
</section>
<section id="june-5" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="june-5">June 5</h3>
<p>Another great day as a family starting with a full breakfast provided by volunteers at the RMH. Times talking together, imagining, drawing – including time outside (outside can be precious following weeks of being in hospital). In the afternoon we grabbed an ride-share down the Marine Gateway Cineplex and took in the new Guardians o the Galaxy movie – loved it!</p>
<p>These last few days have felt like a vacation!</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Celebrating how well Sam has been doing</p></li>
<li><p>A joyful family weekend – letting medical issues be in the background of our lives.</p></li>
<li><p>Bonus physiotherapy for Sam. The elevator at the RMH was under repair for most of the weekend. This initially forced Sam to take the stairs – two flights up to the room. By the end of the weekend he chose the stairs to keep restoring his strength.</p></li>
<li><p>Today we will learn the results of last Friday’s PET and CT scans – the current state of the cancer.<br>
We will discuss with the medical team what the next steps are. Once again we will be stepping into the unknown. For now we know what life looks like until mid-day.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>added on June 7<sup>th</sup>↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-06_amazing-weekend-rmh.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/weekend-vacation.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Freedom from hospital life</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-03_freedom-release-to-rmd.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Good morning!<br>
Here we are having a good morning as we are experience a good level of freedom. All three of us are currently at the Ronald McDonald House. This am, Sam and I have had breakfast together, and as I write this Tina is sleeping in.</p>
<p>Sam made it through, we made it through this last round of chemotherapy!</p>
<section id="reflections-on-june-1-and-2" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-june-1-and-2">Reflections on June 1 and 2</h2>
<p><em>June 1</em> Sam was still in hospital. In consultation with the medical team most all of Sam’s meds moved from a) being on a delivery schedule to list as take-as-needed, b) changed from IV delivery to oral. The purpose of this day was to prepare us to get out – to give us control of Sam’s care.</p>
<p><em>June 2</em>, yesterday, was very full with procedures and our transition out of the hospital. Forty-five days prior we made the emergency move from Prince George to the hospital. We have lived there full time and now we had the day to prepare to leave.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The day started with trip to the BC Cancer Clinic for a PET and CT scan. This was much easier than the last trip. Last time the Ambulance service transported Sam which was needed given the state of his health at that time. This time, the three of us went downstairs, got in a taxi, and walked into the clinic.</p></li>
<li><p>Next were the steps to leave including:</p></li>
<li><p>A trip to the pharmacy – to collect all of Sam’s medications. This was actually simple, as the pharmacy is just downstairs. I would realize hours later, well after closing that I bought the wrong needles for Sam’s blood thinner…</p></li>
<li><p>Trips to move our lives over to the RMH<sup>1</sup>. In our time here we have lived full-time at the hospital with minor respite at the RMD. During our time here we have only added materials to our lives as we bought or people brought us life-essentials, and gifts arrived. We are blessed to have all that we need and more. I did spend a couple hours moving our things – very glad that the RMD had utility wagon that we could borrow.</p></li>
<li><p>Trip to the Red Cross – to get some hardware for Sam. He has some strength to regain so in moments of weakness or fatigue he can fall back to the wheelchair or shower-transfer-bench.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>We were fully here by 7:00pm. We are loving it! The feelings this morning are almost reminiscent of family vacations that we have had in the past. We are not home but we are free to be ourselves!</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for this opportunity to get out for a few days.</p></li>
<li><p>Upcoming we have to return to the hospital on Tuesday, June 6 when we will hear the results of the PET and CT scans and likely be admitted to start the next round of chemotherapy.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful, for the amazing care Sam received at BC Children’s Also thankful that we have a break from it – that we can sleep through the night without the need to take vitals, take blood, deliver medications, or listen to alarms.</p></li>
<li><p>Challenges of side-effects have mostly resolved! I will need to go in search of a vacuum cleaner as Sam’s hair rains from his head.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern, a recent scan flagged a the potential for a problematic kidney stone.</p></li>
<li><p>As always, we will remain concerned about any cancer in his system.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Ronald McDonald House↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>procedures</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-03_freedom-release-to-rmd.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A weekend pass, friends, and a date!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-01_pass-and-concert.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/hugs-4kc-concert.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Unexpected hugs at just prior to the start of the For King and Country concert</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Today is day 44 in hospital. Aside from one afternoon weeks ago Sam has not left these halls – it is time to have a change of scenery. Expectations are that this will happen over this weekend! As I write this my family is sleeping and I am only listening to the sound of a single pump pushing supplemental food into Sam’s body. No other lines are attached to him and no alarms were ringing through the night!</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-31" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-31">Reflections on May 31</h2>
<p>Yesterday the medical team started preparing to have us leave for a few days! We will be out in the small gap of time between chemotherapy rounds. All of Sam’s medications were converted to oral and I was trained up on how to use the food pump which the team wants to keep going. We are excited to have a change of scenery, to get Sam out, and for all three of us to have comfortable beds (<em>we will be staying at the RMH – Ronald McDonald House</em>). Honestly, we also have a little anxiety to make this change and leave the safety of these four wall. But bring it on – let’s get out for a few days!</p>
<p>Aria and family were able to visit again. Aria and Tina hit up a local gluten free bakery. Sam was able to have a short visit with David and Lucas H. and a little longer with David. We are thankful for their friendship.</p>
<p>In the evening Tina and I attended a concert! For several years Tina was been dreaming of attending a <a href="https://open.spotify.com/artist/3sDbKMebVH2VYcRSl7u1VC?si=6FcIxJJtS6uwiBK8RLl0qA">For King and Country</a> concert and we were able to get tickets. Tina loved it! She also loved huge hugs from Carlene and Kendra S., and Kim P. who happened to be sitting fairly close by!</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for the upcoming opportunity to get out for a few days. Round 3 of chemo will likely start next Tuesday. There will be adjustments as we take on a new routine.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for the chance to visit with friends.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for date nights!</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful to see Sam’s blood counts returning to normal including the numbers indicating the strengthening of hi immune system.</p></li>
<li><p>Challenges of side-effects continue. Sam, although have a return of energy, is becoming physically exhausted. This whole regime, and being bed-bound for a full week, has led to parts of his system being bound – constipation is significant issue. It will pass but likely not without pain. GI sores from the chemotherapy also complicate this.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern, a recent scan flagged a the potential for a problematic kidney stone.</p></li>
<li><p>Upcoming, this Friday June 2, Sam is books for a PET scans. The purpose of this scan is to determine the current state of the cancer. We look forward to knowing the results. We are excited that previous scans suggest significant reductions in the cancer, and that this scan should confirm that. As always, we will remain concerned about any cancer in his system.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-01_pass-and-concert.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/hugs-4kc-concert.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Visits and a date</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-31_visits-date.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="reflections-on-may-29-and-30" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-29-and-30">Reflections on May 29 and 30</h2>
<p>Medically, the last couple days for Sam have been mostly positive as we see his numbers come back and see him gain energy back, be mostly over his cold/flu. The chemo-side-effects have presented themselves further as Sam has begun to lose his hair, I discuss additional challenges in the concerns below.</p>
<p>During this time, it has been great to have Nana here to visit with all of us but especially with Sam. Her time here also allowed Tina and I to get out together for a few hours away from the hospital. Vancouver has been good to us in that we have not struggled to find good food for Tina. However, most of this has been ordered in. On the 29<sup>th</sup> we were able go out for some good food – to have a date. We took the Skytrain into Yaletown, walked the neighbourhood and had a meal together. I know this is shocking to many – I don’t think we took one picture on our date… if we had I would have posted something.</p>
<p>The 30<sup>th</sup> is marked as being Nana’s last day visiting with us – we expect she will be back in a number of weeks. Uncle Cal, and cousins Amanda and Chris were also able to stop by for a quick visit. Nana and the family left in the evening. Sam also had a friend stop by, David H. spent the evening with him, while Aria and Tina visited. An additional visit earlier today, Tina and I had a great catch-up with Sam, Nick and Elara G.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for visits from Nana, local family, and friends.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful to see Sam’s blood counts returning to normal including the numbers indicating the strengthening of hi immune system.</p></li>
<li><p>Challenges of side-effects. Sam, although have a return of energy, is becoming physically exhausted. This whole regime, and being bed-bound for a full week has led to parts of his system being bound – constipation is significant issue. It will pass but likely not without pain. GI sores from the chemotherapy also complicate this.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern, a recent scan flagged a the potential for a problematic kidney stone.</p></li>
<li><p>Upcoming, this Friday June 2, Sam is books for a PET scans. The purpose of this scan is to determine to current state of the cancer. We look forward to knowing the results. We are excited that previous scans suggest significant reductions in the cancer and that this scan should confirm that. As always, we will remain concerned about any cancer in his system.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-31_visits-date.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Weekend Review</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-29_weekend.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I am writing this am simply to keep the updates coming. Perhaps it is a good thing that there is little of significance to communicate as this past weekend was much of the same – generally holding a pattern and continuing on with the chemotherapy – now day 17 of 21.</p>
<section id="weekend-highlights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="weekend-highlights">Weekend highlights</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Nana is here and has spent some good time with Sam. I am especially thankful that Tina has had some great visits with her mom.</p></li>
<li><p>I got out for a couples hours to ride around the city.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has struggled with secondary illness – basically he has a cold. He started a different antibiotic and was starting to feel better by Sunday afternoon.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Friends in PG did a major yard clean-up for us – thank-you!</p></li>
<li><p>We are starting to see Sam’s blood counts return to normal … though his immune system has not recovered yet.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that early indications are that the cancer is being removed from Sam’s body. Though we choose to hope and trust that he will see complete return to health, we will remain concerned that any cancer persists in his body.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-29_weekend.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>An update and a meditation: Psalm 91</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-27_psalm-91.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>The Psalms are a great place to read and be inspired. The writers pour out their hearts in song and prayer providing beautiful expressions from the heart that can cover a broad range of emotion from pain and frustration to hope and praise. Several people have given Psalm 91 to us to read, meditate on, and pray through. I encourage you to read this Psalm, and pray it for Sam!</p>
<section id="therapy-update" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="therapy-update">Therapy update</h2>
<p>Before you do just a few quick points to update you on how his journey is going and the next steps as we know them:</p>
<ul>
<li>We are currently just past the halfway mark in round 2 of chemotherapy. The heavy chemical part of the treatment is over and now Sam’s body has to work through the effects. Effects include (these are generally expected):
<ul>
<li><p>collapse of the immune system: Sam’s blood counts are monitored daily. Over the last number of days drops in the red and platelet cells have been managed with transfusions. We need to simply wait for the white cells to come back. It seems Sam may be through the worst of this part as cell counts are beginning to return on their own.</p></li>
<li><p>sores in the GI system. Sam had some sores in his mouth earlier in this process. They have healed but he has other much further on in the system that are painful. These will heal in time.</p></li>
<li><p>Most of Sam’s time is spent in bed … his body is doing a lot of work. The downside of being in bed this long is that he is stiff and sore; he has a lot of muscle tension and very little energy to stretch it out or move to loosen it up. We will get there but there is work to be done.</p></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>Next steps and current state of the cancer:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The truth is the next steps are very much unknown. The treatment plan will depend on how the cancer has responded to this latest round of therapy.</p></li>
<li><p>We are encouraged, Sam had an X-ray to rule out that the flu he had was not causing a pneumonia. This scan confirmed that he did not have pneumonia. What was unexpected, is that the scan also gave us a glimpse at the state of his cancer, and the doctors confirmed that the cancer-mass has shrunk.</p></li>
<li><p>Once this current therapy is complete on June 2<sup>nd</sup> Sam will be booked for a scan. Once the results of the scan are known a new plan will be made.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="meditation-psalm-91" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="meditation-psalm-91">Meditation <a href="https://www.bible.com/bible/111/PSA.91.NIV">Psalm 91</a></h2>
<p>Thank you for journeying with us. May this Psalm inspire your thoughts and prayers:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Whoever dwells in the shelter of the Most High</p>
<p>will rest in the shadow of the Almighty.</p>
<p>I will say of the <span class="smallcaps">Lord</span>, “He is my refuge and my fortress,</p>
<p>my God, in whom I trust.”</p>
<p><br>
Surely he will save you</p>
<p>from the fowler’s snare</p>
<p>and from the deadly pestilence.</p>
<p>He will cover you with his feathers,</p>
<p>and under his wings you will find refuge;</p>
<p>his faithfulness will be your shield and rampart.</p>
<p>You will not fear the terror of night,</p>
<p>nor the arrow that flies by day,</p>
<p>nor the pestilence that stalks in the darkness,</p>
<p>nor the plague that destroys at midday.</p>
<p>A thousand may fall at your side,</p>
<p>ten thousand at your right hand,</p>
<p>but it will not come near you.</p>
<p>You will only observe with your eyes</p>
<p>and see the punishment of the wicked.</p>
<p><br>
If you say, “The <span class="smallcaps">Lord</span> is my refuge,”</p>
<p>and you make the Most High your dwelling,</p>
<p>no harm will overtake you,</p>
<p>no disaster will come near your tent.</p>
<p>For he will command his angels concerning you</p>
<p>to guard you in all your ways;</p>
<p>they will lift you up in their hands,</p>
<p>so that you will not strike your foot against a stone.</p>
<p>You will tread on the lion and the cobra;</p>
<p>you will trample the great lion and the serpent.</p>
<p><br>
“Because he loves me,” says the <span class="smallcaps">Lord</span>, “I will rescue him;</p>
<p>I will protect him, for he acknowledges my name.</p>
<p>He will call on me, and I will answer him;</p>
<p>I will be with him in trouble,</p>
<p>I will deliver him and honor him.</p>
<p>With long life I will satisfy him</p>
<p>and show him my salvation.”</p>
</blockquote>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-27_psalm-91.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Preliminary findings (round 2)</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-25_preliminary-findings.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>The days have been blurring together in this time-warp experience here at BC Children’s hospital. This morning is the beginning of day 37 – now just over five weeks since our arrival. This current round of chemotherapy will come to an end in another ten days. In some ways it feels like we are on a long waiting period, yet everyday brings its own challenges or occasional bits of news. Each day we:</p>
<ul>
<li>get updates on Sam’s blood counts</li>
<li>manage pain related to the effects of chemo</li>
<li>try to stay active</li>
<li>try to play a game or read … but often the energy/concentration level is not there so there is a lot of TV. <em><br>
We would love some recommendations of shows or movies that you have enjoyed.</em></li>
</ul>
<section id="findings-from-an-x-ray" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="findings-from-an-x-ray">Findings from an X-ray</h2>
<p>Two days ago Tina and I had a good conversation with Dr.&nbsp;S. Cheng. We love how honest she is with us, that she shares what she knows and how she lets us know what she does not know. In our meeting, she told us about Sam’s latest chest X-ray – the purpose of which was to rule out the potential for pneumonia related to Sam’s cold. There was also enough information in the image that Dr.&nbsp;Cheng could provide a preliminary report: the tumour is smaller than shown in the previous CT scan (taken after round 1 of chemo). We are headed in the right direction – round 1 saw a reduction in the cancerous mass, and round 2 appears to be doing the same! We will know better in with the next scan in a couple weeks when a scan will be done to image the cancer itself.</p>
<p>As to what the next steps will be following this round of chemo – that is simply unknown.</p>
</section>
<section id="reflections-on-may-23-and-24" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-23-and-24">Reflections on May 23 and 24</h2>
<p>The 23<sup>rd</sup> was a day filled with the love from friends and family. The three of us had a good visit with Craig and Lisa R, followed by Tina and I having time with them. Nana spent much of the day sitting with Sam, and much of the evening with Tina. Yesterday, was quieter in Sam’s room. As per doctor’s recommendations we reduced his visitor hours. I spent most of the day with Sam, less a couple hours, when Nana sat with him. Outside the room, Tina and Mary (Nana) had a great visit with Tina’s nieces Amanda and Jayme, and Jane, and her brother Cal.</p>
<p>It has also been nice to seen the familar faces of Jarod and Erin S. as we either meet with them or simply bump into them in the halls here.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for friends and family supporting us.</p></li>
<li><p>The medical team here continues to be amazing.</p></li>
<li><p>Side effects of the chemo-therapy. No hair loss yet, but significant muscle pain, and pains related to sores in the GI track<sup>1</sup>.</p></li>
<li><p>The constant cancer concern. We will not know how the cancer has responded to this treatment for another week-and-a-half. Once the full therapy cycle is complete the team here will scan for changes.</p></li>
<li><p>Homesickness and boredom. Sam has been a champ making the best of his time here. Yesterday, Sam and I had a great conversation about home, that we miss it, and we imagined/ dreamed of what we love about home from simple things of regular life, to friends, to dreaming of what we would like to do when we return. Longing for home and feeling trapped in this hospital ward may become significant challenges in the days ahead.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Gastrointestinal track – from the mouth all the way through and out of the digestive system↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-25_preliminary-findings.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Nana is here!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-23_nana-arrives.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Although I am wiped out from a short night of sleep, I have joy. Sam is awake beside me acting himself. I do hope that he takes a nap later – but this is good to see. He has energy to play a game – something he simply has not had the concentration power to do. Last night had actually been a hard one. I am not sure it was the flu or other effects of the chemo but his sleep had been interupted and thereby mine was as well.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-22" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-22">Reflections on May 22</h2>
<p>Medically, yesterday was a day of discomfort. Sam had the flu, a result of the chemo taking out his immune system, and with this illness he had quite a bit of muscle pain. Blood tests also showed his counts were down again. In response, Sam received transfusions in the afternoon.</p>
<p>The highlight of the day was the happy reunion of Sam and Nana in the early afternoon! I had taken the skytrain out to the airport and we travelled straight back to the see Tina and Sam. Tina and her mom were also able to spend some good times catching up. Hopefully they are having a good sleep-in over at the RMH.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for Nana</p></li>
<li><p>The medical team here continues to be amazing.</p></li>
<li><p>The constant cancer concern. We will not know how the cancer has responded to this treatment for another week-and-a-half. Once the full therapy cycle is complete the team here will scan for changes.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-23_nana-arrives.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Of fevers and friends</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-22_friends-fever.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-05-21_chase-ben-sam.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Great visits with Chase and Ben. So good to see these young men together again!</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="reflections-on-the-may-20-21-weekend" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-the-may-20-21-weekend">Reflections on the May 20-21 weekend</h2>
<p>Saturday was generally a quiet day. We were excited to receive update pictures from Joel and Joanna C. as they travelled from Prince George with Sam’s good friends Chase and Ben C. Ben of course brought greetings from his family and Sam and I are now set up with our favourite cookies from Krista. We had an initial visit Saturday evening and despite a having to cancel a morning visit on Sunday the boys had great visits again in the afternoon.</p>
<p>An expected side effect from the chemotherapy was a drop in Sam’s blood counts. We saw this over the weekend with a full collapse of Sam’s white count on Sunday. This temporary loss of the body’s ability to fight was also paired with a fever and phlegm. The medical team was ready for this and had Sam on antibiotics right away. Visits were cancelled for most of the day as Tina and I watched our boy sleep most of the day away. By later afternoon, Sam was awake and was welcomed visits from Chase and Ben – though masks were needed for all. So good to see these boy / young men back together again – Good for the soul (ours and Sam’s)!</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for friends, and in particular in-person connections</p></li>
<li><p>The medical team here continues to be amazing. A special shout-out to Melissa for the her calm, cool, and constant work as she managed all of Sam’s regular needs in addition to all of the cold/fever related issues.</p></li>
<li><p>The constant cancer concern. We will not know how the cancer has responded to this treatment for another week-and-a-half. Once the full therapy cycle is complete the team here will scan for changes.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-22_friends-fever.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 22 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-05-21_chase-ben-sam.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Got some rest</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-20_rest.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-05-20_van-from-qep.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Vancouver in the morning. A view from from Queen Elizabeth Park during my morning ride.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This morning we are in the calm, my family is sleeping, and as usual I am up with the sun. I am actually back at my chair following a morning bikeride through Queen Elizabeth Park and the surrounding neighbourhood. It was great to get some fresh morning air… from waht I understand that is pretty hard to come by in much of BC and Alberta these days.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-19" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-19">Reflections on May 19</h2>
<p>Actually, a calm day. Sam had some mild nausea in the morning and with the assistance of some additional medication was able to get through it and sleep much of the morning. There were the usual visits by the medical team but these were not as frequent as the previous phases of this chemotherapy run. Tina had spent the night at the Ronald McDonald House and she was able to sleep in. I was not able to sleep in the morning but after Tina arrived I had a solid nap.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for rest, in the forms of sleep and activities that rejuvenate (e.g.&nbsp;bike ride for Colin)</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for the medical team here that are taking great care of our boy.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that it is easy for us to stay with him</p></li>
<li><p>We are looking forward to seeing some friends this weekend.</p></li>
<li><p>We are ever-concerned that the chemotherapy will be effective</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-20_rest.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-05-20_van-from-qep.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Well managed days</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-19_managed-days.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It is nice to provide a quick, low-intensity post. To all reading, thank you again for journeying with us.</p>
<p>I wonder if I ever read this again what my experience will be. I expect, that it will be an emotional roller coaster and perhaps this is your experience reading along. This last month has been the most intense of our lives, some days are just plain difficult and painful, others are quiet as we wait for next steps, new phases of experience. In all the days I think I live in a constant state of vigilance, my guard is always up, until something knocks me over. Yesterday, was a quiet day, a day of calm in this storm. My hope is that today will be as well.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-18" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-18">Reflections on May 18</h2>
<p>Learning lessons from the day before the current medication plan for Sam is working. He has not had anymore nausea, and when he has some pain (e.g.&nbsp;muscle ache, headaches) we are on it quickly and medicines are quickly made available. All-in-all, it was a quiet day. We played some video games, got down the hall for a walk, and played a board game.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Rest: we all need it. Last night was far better than the previous days as fluids are not being pushed on Sam. We still need to find more rest.</p></li>
<li><p>Side effects: we have have learned some lessons and are managing current side effects well-enough. Other side effects are expected. I expect that Sam’s mouth will be more sensitive as sores develop, these sores could extend all they way through his digestive track. Chemo-balding is also expected.</p></li>
<li><p>Potential for secondary infection: One of the effects of the chemotherapy is a reduction in Sam’s blood counts. The medical team can manage reductions in red cells and platelets, but they cannot manage reduced white cell counts. As such, Sam will be more susceptible to colds, flus, or whatever is floating around. We will likely move to a mask-up and wash-up protocol before entering the room.</p></li>
<li><p>Ultimately, that this intense treatment is effective at removing the cancer from Sam’s body.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-19_managed-days.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cytarabine aka Cyterrible</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-18_rough-days.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>This morning the sun is shining, my family is sleeping peacefully. It seems that we have Sam’s health management under control. My outlook today is one of hope. The previous two days were definitely more challenging.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-16-and-17" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-16-and-17">Reflections on May 16 and 17</h2>
<p>Yesterday morning, as I was considering what to convey, the day started with a challenge… I will get to that, but before I do I actually need to back up two days.</p>
<p>Two days ago we had a meeting with our medical team. It was a fairly standard check-in but one that shook Tina and I to the core. We were both, individually, in own personal funks for much of the day before we had an opportunity to discuss it together. During the meeting we were introduced to members of the medical team from Canuck Place. They let us know some of the services that they provide including potential future options respite from the hospital experience. What shook us to the core was the main purpose of <a href="https://www.canuckplace.org">Canuck Place</a> – palliative care. To be clear, we are not going down that road, but not knowing what the future holds, it is within the realm of possibility and I suspect that the medical team here had a ethical obligation to ensure this connection was made. We have known this, but the meeting forced us to confront the possibility more directly – again, re-opening this wound/fear.</p>
<p>Two days ago was also the fifth of five days of the heavy chemical delivery for this current round of chemotherapy. The remaining 16 days of this chemo round are in place for the chemicals to complete their work, and to allow Sam to recover from it. As of that evening we had not seen much for side effects. Yesterday morning, that would change.</p>
<p>Yesterday, as I was considering what to write, Sam’s day began with a strong wave of nausea and pain. The previous two nights one of the drugs that Sam was given was Cytarabine. I’ll blame that one, though it could been side effects from the whole set. It took several hours to get Sam comfortable, and by the afternoon he was feeling ok, tired but ok. And, though I am exhausted as well, Sam’s fatigue is beyond the lack of sleep we have been having as is a product of the treatment the chemo. In addition the chemotherapy medications will reduce Sam’s blood counts – reducing the capacity of his blood to: provide him energy/oxygen (hemoglobin/ red blood cells), protect him from injury (platelets), and protect him from disease (white blood cells).</p>
<p>Some positive highlights:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Tina and Erin S. were able to spend some time together (2 days ago)</p></li>
<li><p>A relaxed and enjoyable visit with Uncle Cal and cousin Jane (yesterday)</p></li>
<li><p>Coffee and treats sent to by friends.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>The heavy dosing of this round of chemotherapy drugs is now complete</p></li>
<li><p>From what we are told, we are entering the valley of chemo side effects. Sam, seems ok this am. My hope is that the side effects will be minimal for him.</p></li>
<li><p>Although a rough start to yesterday, Sam now has a medication regime that seems to be working to curb the feelings of side effects causing nausea and pain.</p></li>
<li><p>We remain concerned that this treatment is ultimately successful at removing the cancer from Sam’s body.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-18_rough-days.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The current pattern</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-16_typical-day.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Yesterday evening Kevin, my brother-in-law and soul-brother, checked in with me. With everything going on we kept it to a text-based conversation. He asked a simple question of how was today? I was going to write something simple, to say that it went well and I had to catch myself as I realized our normal here just is not normal. Generally, it was a good day, we are carrying on with the plan. Generally, it was a lower stress day. Below I refine and expand on my original text to give you a glimpse at how our days are:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The day started early, or perhaps there was not night. Given the amount of fluids being pumped into Sam we were up every 1.5 - 2 hours. So we start the day sleep deprived.</p></li>
<li><p>Every hour something was going on with Sam’s medications and or tube feed. This included numerous chemo drug deliveries.</p></li>
<li><p>Several blood and fluid tests – checking chemistries and how those may impact the delivery of chemo.</p></li>
<li><p>The IV team was in to change one of his dressings – the one on the PICC on his arm which he received last week. FYI Sam is down to two sets of blood connections. The PICC on his arm, which is not centrally located, and the Hickman which is being used to deliver the chemo.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam is on a tube feed. He is still eating regularly, but with all the potential impacts from chemo the desire is to supplement his nutrition, and give him every chance to regain or retain weight.</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Peggy W. came by for her usual check-in, clarified a few of our questions, but no concerns – all is going as planned</p></li>
<li><p>The nurses were training on a new protocol for hooking up the IV system. … they are moving to a quick connect/release system.</p></li>
<li><p>During much of the above Sam and I watched a movie, obviously with a good number of pauses – I think the 2-hour movie took closer to five.</p></li>
<li><p>I got out — took a nap and had a shower over at the Ronald McD House. When I got back Sam and Tina were also able to nap – so helpful is restoring our short nights.</p></li>
<li><p>We have a small fridge in the room, and with recent meals it was a left-over night. On the food front, we are very pleased that we have not struggled to keep Tina in food despite all her food sensitivities.</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for visits with friends and family</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Tina has had good food.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern for the current round of treatment. We are expecting side effects. To date, we have not seen very little. A little soreness in the mouth but this has been very manageable.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern for potential longer lasting and high impact side effects. These can include damage to bodily organ or secondary cancers.</p></li>
<li><p>Ultimately, we are concerned that the treatment is effective and that the cancer is removed entirely from Sam’s body.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-16_typical-day.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Chemo, friends, family, and mothers day</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-15_chemo-friends-mothers-day.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-05-13_sam-john.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Sam and John B. Long time friends reunited.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As I write this morning the morning sun lights the room sneaking past the edges of the blind. I need this light to wake me as it has been a weekend where sleep has been highly interrupted. My family is sleeping peacefully. We are now starting day 4 of Sam’s latest chemo treatment. Over this past weekend Sam has had a lot of intense ‘medicines’ pushed into him. I put this in quotes as if we weren’t tackling cancer these medicines would be considered poisons. Along with the medication has been a lot of fluid – resulting in the need to put a lot of fluid out. Sam and I have been awake through the nights every 1-3 hours… I am so glad to see him resting now.</p>
<section id="friends-and-family-visits" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friends-and-family-visits">Friends and family visits</h2>
<p>For a second weekend in a row were were able to visit with Friends from Prince George as the Bandstras made a special trip. Sam and John had a great time hanging out and playing games. Jess and Kate took Tina out for Saturday afternoon. John (Sr) and I did a few errands. We also had a family movie night, and managed to get in a couple rounds of <a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/131357/coup">Coup</a> before they had to make the return trip. So great to have some normal family fun.</p>
<p>My parents also had some good time, simply being with Sam, and giving Tina and I some time to get away. I was able to get away to have dinner with them the night before they left.</p>
</section>
<section id="mothers-day" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mothers-day">Mothers day</h2>
<p>I will try to sum this up for Tina but to be clear these are my thoughts not hers. This mothers day was challenging and yet beautiful. The challenge of course is where we are and why we are here. Some hours are just simply hard as we are forced to look into the abyss – to contemplate the mortality of our precious boy. The day was also beautiful. The charities supporting oncology families, and the Ronald McDonald House, have showered Tina with presents; practical and extravagant – who doesn’t like Purdy’s. Tina and I were also able to have a beautiful conversation where she heart-received the message that she is a wonderful mother and that we would, together, continue to love our boy through whatever challenges present themselves.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for visits with friends and family</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for a beautiful mothers day.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern for the current round of treatment. We are expecting side effects. Yesterday we started to see signs of them as Sam had his first mouth sore – it is expected that his entire digestive system from mouth, all the way through, and out will become sensitive if not raw and just generally cause him to feel gross. Hair loss is also expected. It cn be described as descending into a valley of pain and then climbing back out.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern for potential longer lasting and high impact side effects. These can include damage to bodily organ or secondary cancers.</p></li>
<li><p>Ultimately, we are concerned that the treatment is effective and that the cancer is removed entirely from Sam’s body.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-15_chemo-friends-mothers-day.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-05-13_sam-john.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Chemotherapy round 2 has begun</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-13_chemo-round2-began.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I am happy to report that everything went as planned yesterday. Sam cam through the surgery to establish the new central line without any difficulty – though a little tender where he opened up. The new central line working as expected, this line (aka Hickman device) was established travelling from Sam’s leg through to the major vessels just below his heart. The previous PICC lines were not able to reach the major vessels near the heart as there was too much clotting in Sam’s chest. With this new line established round two of chemotherapy has begun.</p>
<p>Chemotherapy medications were started promptly after Sam returned from surgery and a short period in recovery. All of these medications are entering his system through the central line system along with <em>a lot</em> of additional fluid. As I have noted in previous posts the drugs are intense and in order to protect his other organs additional fluid is needed. Practically speaking this means that life, and sleep are interrupted with many bathroom breaks.</p>
<p>Gram and Papa were here providing moral and practical support. We also had a visit from Lisa S. who brought a stack of cards from home with messages of encouragement from Sam’s friends at the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church’s</a> youth group, along with cards for Tina and I.</p>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Surgery went well. Finally, an effective central line has been established allowing treatment to begin.</p></li>
<li><p>Chemotherapy round 2 has begun. This is a much more powerful treatment then the first. There are risks and side effects. The risks include potential damage to Sam’s organs (e.g.&nbsp;liver and kidneys). Side effects are expected to start showing within a week, including hair loss, and generally feeling gross.</p></li>
<li><p>I expect we will not experience solid sleeps over these next number of days as there is a flurry of drugs, testing of fluids, and release of excess fluids … these interruptions are about every 2-3 hours.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all support of friends, family, rekindling old friendships, and care received from strangers</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for an amazing medical team here at BC Children’s hospital.</p></li>
<li><p>Tina and I are thankful for Sam. He continues to have an amazing attitude through everything!</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>procedures</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-13_chemo-round2-began.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Assembling at the chemotherapy starting line (round 2)</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-12_starting-line-round-2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Today our waiting period should be ending. We will have a few last hours of anticipation before Sam heads down to surgery for a third attempt to establish a central line. Assuming all goes as planned he will begin round two of chemotherapy. This next round is likely what we all think about when it comes to chemotherapy as the medicines used are so intense that Sam will likely lose his hair. The full therapy session is 21 days, with the first five being the medicinal treatment and the following 16 being for recovery. We are expecting by mid-next week Sam might be feeling pretty rough.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-10" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-10">Reflections on May 10</h2>
<p>Yesterday was fairly calm with the usual visits by doctors and nurses. Gram and Papa were here and their presence allowed Tina and I to get away. I even had a couple hours on my own. My brother-in-law has lent me his electric bike and I went exploring the great network of bike lanes through numerous neighbourhoods across Vancouver (17km ride). This trip included some stops to pick up essential supplies including a stop at a gluten-free bakery for Tina.</p>
<p>The level of care continues to be amazing. Sam had a headache in the afternoon and given that the he does have some blood clots the doctors have reason to monitor this as a concern and ordered an MRI which he received hours later. Sam definitely has his humor back stating to the doctor that <em>we will set your mind at ease by looking at my mind</em>.</p>
<p>As a family we had a relaxing evening. We walked out to the deck where Sam and I played a <a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/154597/hive-pocket">hive pocket</a>. Sam destroyed me the first time we played but I managed a win yesterday – though my brain hurt. A solid strategy game that does not take that long to play.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam goes into surgery in the late morning – scheduled for 11:30. This line will be inserted in the leg and travel up to the inferior vena cava – just below the heart. In addition, instead of having the lines dangling from his leg the surgeon wants to create an outlet in Sam’s abdomen, above the belt-line, which will allow him to remain mobile.</p></li>
<li><p>Chemotherapy should begin this afternoon. This brings with it a couple main concerns.</p>
<ul>
<li>That this treatment is effective a removing cancer from Sam’s body</li>
<li>There are common side effects such as hair loss, temporary impacts on Sam’s immune system, generally feeling gross, and the potential for others. We don’t expect anything symptoms of these in the next 24-48 hours but they will come.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all of the support we have received, your care and prayers, messages, visits, and gifts. We are blessed to have such a community around us.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="meditation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="meditation">Meditation</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>He gives strength to the weary<br>
and increases the power of the weak.<br>
Even youths grow tired and weary,<br>
and young men stumble and fall;<br>
but those who hope in the Lord<sup>1</sup><br>
will renew their strength.<br>
They will soar on wings like eagles;<br>
they will run and not grow weary,<br>
they will walk and not be faint.</p>
<p>Isaiah. 40 v. 29-31 NIV translation</p>
</blockquote>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>alternately: those who wait on the Lord (ESV)↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>procedures</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-12_starting-line-round-2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>In preparation for chemotherapy – waiting</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-11_brief-update.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>We are in a waiting period. The next round of chemo cannot begin until the new central line is established. Over the last couple days:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>We have had visits with various doctors to discuss the next steps (e.g.&nbsp;procedure for central line and chemotherapy treatments).</p></li>
<li><p>To ensure that Sam gets the nutrition that he needs in the weeks ahead he had a new NG tube installed – allowing for supplemental food to be pumped to his stomach via a tube going in his nose and down to the stomach.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has good energy these days and we have been walking around the hospital and Sam is looking at his schoolwork via google-classrooms – getting excited about finishing grade nine.</p></li>
<li><p>Yesterday evening my parents arrived. Sam and Papa enjoyed watching the hockey game together while Tina and I got away together for a good dinner a few blocks away on Main St.</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<p><em>repeated from yesterday</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>We are very thankful for the entire medical team here. The care-aid and nurses take on the day-to-day care, each with their own style of care but all doing a great job of addressing needs as they arise. The support teams including IV, nutrition, and physio. The cleaning staff who are so polite. Sam’s doctors who are excellent communicators and are gracious in allowing time for dialogue and answering our questions when they have answers, and are straight with us when they do not know.</p></li>
<li><p>There are a lot of unknowns going forward. Sam’s form of cancer is mostly unknown. As such, the treatment plan / chemotherapy will be to hit it with the largest hammer available. This will be hard on Sam’s body and we hope much harder on the cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation, another attempt to establish a central-line will be made. As the clotting in the chest blocking access via the arms towards the heart a line will be attempted through the vessels in one of Sams’s legs, to approach the heart from below. Once this line is established chemotherapy will begin. Timing will be based on the next available time… this may be as late as Friday.</p></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-11_brief-update.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>In preparation for chemotherapy</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-10_brief-update.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I’ll keep it brief this morning. We are now in preparation mode for the next round of chemotherapy. It will hit hard, but I will describe that within the next couple days. There are a number of steps that need to occur before we begin – I have included these below</p>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>We are very thankful for the entire medical team here. The care-aid and nurses take on the day-to-day care, each with their own style of care but all doing a great job of addressing needs as they arise. The support teams including IV, nutrition, and physio. The cleaning staff who are so polite. Sam’s doctors who are excellent communicators and are gracious in allowing time for dialogue and answering our questions when they have answers, and are straight with us when they do not know.</p></li>
<li><p>There are a lot of unknowns going forward. Sam’s form of cancer is mostly unknown. As such, the treatment plan / chemotherapy will be to hit it with the largest hammer available. This will be hard on Sam’s body and we hope much harder on the cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation, another attempt to establish a central-line will be made. As the clotting in the chest blocking access via the arms towards the heart a line will be attempted through the vessels in one of Sams’s legs, to approach the heart from below. Once this line is established chemotherapy will begin. Timing will be based on the next available time… this may be as late as Friday.</p></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-10_brief-update.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PICCs and other procedures</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-09_PICCs-procedures.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Sam and I are both up. Sam is in good spirits having had a sound sleep last night. It must have been a quality sleep because it certainly was not a long one … we should both take naps today. Last night we watched a very disappointing hockey game and then had a gaming session. I confess it got later than it should and Tina was not here to put a stop to it. She went to have a full night sleep at the <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">RMDH</a> and I hope that she is able to sleep well into the morning. As I write this Sam is reading a classic – if you know that the answer is <code>42</code> then you know the series he just started.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-8" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-8">Reflections on May 8</h2>
<p>To start the day we thought it would be rather simple and that the afternoon would be relaxed… It wasn’t all bad though there are some concerning elements, it just did not all go as planned. The bulk of the day</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>To start Sam did go under general anesthetic to adjust his <a href="http://www.cw.bc.ca/library/pdf/pamphlets/BCCH1552_PICC.pdf">PICC-line</a> and complete a lumbar puncture. The PICC procedure did not go the way the medical team had hoped. The plan was simply to adjust the position of the existing line, but they were not able to do this so they pulled that line and attempted a new line on the other arm. This new line also did not go as planned, as they were not able to centrally locate the outlet. This is where there is some concern, attempts to (re)position the previous or locate the current line failed due to blood clots in Sam’s system. No one is very clear as to why he has clots so frequently in his blood vessels (to be clear this is not because they are keeping anything from us … it is just they do not know). We know that some of the clots are an effect of the cancer – as the body tried to fight it; alternately, this clotting could be somehow related to the previous chemotherapy. The fact is there is clotting in Sam’s blood vessels, and there is more clotting than a couple weeks ago despite taking blood thinners twice a day.</p></li>
<li><p>The lumbar puncture went as planned.</p></li>
<li><p>The quiet afternoon turned into an additional procedure. The previous scans had focused on the upper chest and neck. This ultrasound was done to evaluate the potential of clotting in the abdomen and legs. Results are pending.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>We were finally back to the room by about 4pm. Time for dinner. I had left overs. A friend had brought poke bowls yesterday and the left over one as almost as good as the first. Sam had a hospital dinner supplemented with snacks from Safeway. Tina was off on her own adventure.</p>
<p>I am so happy for Tina as she was able to get away yesterday afternoon. Senga was here and she took her out to a local park and then out for a Tina-friendly meal.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam has a new PICC, despite not being placed idealy it should work.</p></li>
<li><p>Concerns around clotting in Sam’s blood vessels. He is on blood thinners but there appear be more clots than a couple weeks ago.</p></li>
<li><p>We are expecting to meet with the Dr.&nbsp;Cheng this afternoon to discuss recent results and plans for Sam’s next round of chemotherapy – which may start tomorrow.</p></li>
<li><p>Joyful for connections with friends – in person and through communication.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-09_PICCs-procedures.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
