<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Sam Chisholm</title>
<link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>News updating friends and family on our journey</description>
<generator>quarto-1.2.335</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Got some rest</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-20_rest.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-05-20_van-from-qep.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Vancouver in the morning. A view from from Queen Elizabeth Park during my morning ride.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This morning we are in the calm, my family is sleeping, and as usual I am up with the sun. I am actually back at my chair following a morning bikeride through Queen Elizabeth Park and the surrounding neighbourhood. It was great to get some fresh morning air… from waht I understand that is pretty hard to come by in much of BC and Alberta these days.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-19" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-19">Reflections on May 19</h2>
<p>Actually, a calm day. Sam had some mild nausea in the morning and with the assistance of some additional medication was able to get through it and sleep much of the morning. There were the usual visits by the medical team but these were not as frequent as the previous phases of this chemotherapy run. Tina had spent the night at the Ronald McDonald House and she was able to sleep in. I was not able to sleep in the morning but after Tina arrived I had a solid nap.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for rest, in the forms of sleep and activities that rejuvenate (e.g.&nbsp;bike ride for Colin)</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for the medical team here that are taking great care of our boy.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that it is easy for us to stay with him</p></li>
<li><p>We are looking forward to seeing some friends this weekend.</p></li>
<li><p>We are ever-concerned that the chemotherapy will be effective</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-20_rest.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-05-20_van-from-qep.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Well managed days</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-19_managed-days.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It is nice to provide a quick, low-intensity post. To all reading, thank you again for journeying with us.</p>
<p>I wonder if I ever read this again what my experience will be. I expect, that it will be an emotional roller coaster and perhaps this is your experience reading along. This last month has been the most intense of our lives, some days are just plain difficult and painful, others are quiet as we wait for next steps, new phases of experience. In all the days I think I live in a constant state of vigilance, my guard is always up, until something knocks me over. Yesterday, was a quiet day, a day of calm in this storm. My hope is that today will be as well.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-18" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-18">Reflections on May 18</h2>
<p>Learning lessons from the day before the current medication plan for Sam is working. He has not had anymore nausea, and when he has some pain (e.g.&nbsp;muscle ache, headaches) we are on it quickly and medicines are quickly made available. All-in-all, it was a quiet day. We played some video games, got down the hall for a walk, and played a board game.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Rest: we all need it. Last night was far better than the previous days as fluids are not being pushed on Sam. We still need to find more rest.</p></li>
<li><p>Side effects: we have have learned some lessons and are managing current side effects well-enough. Other side effects are expected. I expect that Sam’s mouth will be more sensitive as sores develop, these sores could extend all they way through his digestive track. Chemo-balding is also expected.</p></li>
<li><p>Potential for secondary infection: One of the effects of the chemotherapy is a reduction in Sam’s blood counts. The medical team can manage reductions in red cells and platelets, but they cannot manage reduced white cell counts. As such, Sam will be more susceptible to colds, flus, or whatever is floating around. We will likely move to a mask-up and wash-up protocol before entering the room.</p></li>
<li><p>Ultimately, that this intense treatment is effective at removing the cancer from Sam’s body.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-19_managed-days.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cytarabine aka Cyterrible</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-18_rough-days.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>This morning the sun is shining, my family is sleeping peacefully. It seems that we have Sam’s health management under control. My outlook today is one of hope. The previous two days were definitely more challenging.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-16-and-17" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-16-and-17">Reflections on May 16 and 17</h2>
<p>Yesterday morning, as I was considering what to convey, the day started with a challenge… I will get to that, but before I do I actually need to back up two days.</p>
<p>Two days ago we had a meeting with our medical team. It was a fairly standard check-in but one that shook Tina and I to the core. We were both, individually, in own personal funks for much of the day before we had an opportunity to discuss it together. During the meeting we were introduced to members of the medical team from Canuck Place. They let us know some of the services that they provide including potential future options respite from the hospital experience. What shook us to the core was the main purpose of <a href="https://www.canuckplace.org">Canuck Place</a> – palliative care. To be clear, we are not going down that road, but not knowing what the future holds, it is within the realm of possibility and I suspect that the medical team here had a ethical obligation to ensure this connection was made. We have known this, but the meeting forced us to confront the possibility more directly – again, re-opening this wound/fear.</p>
<p>Two days ago was also the fifth of five days of the heavy chemical delivery for this current round of chemotherapy. The remaining 16 days of this chemo round are in place for the chemicals to complete their work, and to allow Sam to recover from it. As of that evening we had not seen much for side effects. Yesterday morning, that would change.</p>
<p>Yesterday, as I was considering what to write, Sam’s day began with a strong wave of nausea and pain. The previous two nights one of the drugs that Sam was given was Cytarabine. I’ll blame that one, though it could been side effects from the whole set. It took several hours to get Sam comfortable, and by the afternoon he was feeling ok, tired but ok. And, though I am exhausted as well, Sam’s fatigue is beyond the lack of sleep we have been having as is a product of the treatment the chemo. In addition the chemotherapy medications will reduce Sam’s blood counts – reducing the capacity of his blood to: provide him energy/oxygen (hemoglobin/ red blood cells), protect him from injury (platelets), and protect him from disease (white blood cells).</p>
<p>Some positive highlights:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Tina and Erin S. were able to spend some time together (2 days ago)</p></li>
<li><p>A relaxed and enjoyable visit with Uncle Cal and cousin Jane (yesterday)</p></li>
<li><p>Coffee and treats sent to by friends.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>The heavy dosing of this round of chemotherapy drugs is now complete</p></li>
<li><p>From what we are told, we are entering the valley of chemo side effects. Sam, seems ok this am. My hope is that the side effects will be minimal for him.</p></li>
<li><p>Although a rough start to yesterday, Sam now has a medication regime that seems to be working to curb the feelings of side effects causing nausea and pain.</p></li>
<li><p>We remain concerned that this treatment is ultimately successful at removing the cancer from Sam’s body.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-18_rough-days.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The current pattern</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-16_typical-day.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Yesterday evening Kevin, my brother-in-law and soul-brother, checked in with me. With everything going on we kept it to a text-based conversation. He asked a simple question of how was today? I was going to write something simple, to say that it went well and I had to catch myself as I realized our normal here just is not normal. Generally, it was a good day, we are carrying on with the plan. Generally, it was a lower stress day. Below I refine and expand on my original text to give you a glimpse at how our days are:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The day started early, or perhaps there was not night. Given the amount of fluids being pumped into Sam we were up every 1.5 - 2 hours. So we start the day sleep deprived.</p></li>
<li><p>Every hour something was going on with Sam’s medications and or tube feed. This included numerous chemo drug deliveries.</p></li>
<li><p>Several blood and fluid tests – checking chemistries and how those may impact the delivery of chemo.</p></li>
<li><p>The IV team was in to change one of his dressings – the one on the PICC on his arm which he received last week. FYI Sam is down to two sets of blood connections. The PICC on his arm, which is not centrally located, and the Hickman which is being used to deliver the chemo.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam is on a tube feed. He is still eating regularly, but with all the potential impacts from chemo the desire is to supplement his nutrition, and give him every chance to regain or retain weight.</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Peggy W. came by for her usual check-in, clarified a few of our questions, but no concerns – all is going as planned</p></li>
<li><p>The nurses were training on a new protocol for hooking up the IV system. … they are moving to a quick connect/release system.</p></li>
<li><p>During much of the above Sam and I watched a movie, obviously with a good number of pauses – I think the 2-hour movie took closer to five.</p></li>
<li><p>I got out — took a nap and had a shower over at the Ronald McD House. When I got back Sam and Tina were also able to nap – so helpful is restoring our short nights.</p></li>
<li><p>We have a small fridge in the room, and with recent meals it was a left-over night. On the food front, we are very pleased that we have not struggled to keep Tina in food despite all her food sensitivities.</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for visits with friends and family</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Tina has had good food.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern for the current round of treatment. We are expecting side effects. To date, we have not seen very little. A little soreness in the mouth but this has been very manageable.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern for potential longer lasting and high impact side effects. These can include damage to bodily organ or secondary cancers.</p></li>
<li><p>Ultimately, we are concerned that the treatment is effective and that the cancer is removed entirely from Sam’s body.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-16_typical-day.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Chemo, friends, family, and mothers day</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-15_chemo-friends-mothers-day.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-05-13_sam-john.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Sam and John B. Long time friends reunited.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As I write this morning the morning sun lights the room sneaking past the edges of the blind. I need this light to wake me as it has been a weekend where sleep has been highly interrupted. My family is sleeping peacefully. We are now starting day 4 of Sam’s latest chemo treatment. Over this past weekend Sam has had a lot of intense ‘medicines’ pushed into him. I put this in quotes as if we weren’t tackling cancer these medicines would be considered poisons. Along with the medication has been a lot of fluid – resulting in the need to put a lot of fluid out. Sam and I have been awake through the nights every 1-3 hours… I am so glad to see him resting now.</p>
<section id="friends-and-family-visits" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friends-and-family-visits">Friends and family visits</h2>
<p>For a second weekend in a row were were able to visit with Friends from Prince George as the Bandstras made a special trip. Sam and John had a great time hanging out and playing games. Jess and Kate took Tina out for Saturday afternoon. John (Sr) and I did a few errands. We also had a family movie night, and managed to get in a couple rounds of <a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/131357/coup">Coup</a> before they had to make the return trip. So great to have some normal family fun.</p>
<p>My parents also had some good time, simply being with Sam, and giving Tina and I some time to get away. I was able to get away to have dinner with them the night before they left.</p>
</section>
<section id="mothers-day" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mothers-day">Mothers day</h2>
<p>I will try to sum this up for Tina but to be clear these are my thoughts not hers. This mothers day was challenging and yet beautiful. The challenge of course is where we are and why we are here. Some hours are just simply hard as we are forced to look into the abyss – to contemplate the mortality of our precious boy. The day was also beautiful. The charities supporting oncology families, and the Ronald McDonald House, have showered Tina with presents; practical and extravagant – who doesn’t like Purdy’s. Tina and I were also able to have a beautiful conversation where she heart-received the message that she is a wonderful mother and that we would, together, continue to love our boy through whatever challenges present themselves.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for visits with friends and family</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for a beautiful mothers day.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern for the current round of treatment. We are expecting side effects. Yesterday we started to see signs of them as Sam had his first mouth sore – it is expected that his entire digestive system from mouth, all the way through, and out will become sensitive if not raw and just generally cause him to feel gross. Hair loss is also expected. It cn be described as descending into a valley of pain and then climbing back out.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern for potential longer lasting and high impact side effects. These can include damage to bodily organ or secondary cancers.</p></li>
<li><p>Ultimately, we are concerned that the treatment is effective and that the cancer is removed entirely from Sam’s body.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-15_chemo-friends-mothers-day.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-05-13_sam-john.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Chemotherapy round 2 has begun</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-13_chemo-round2-began.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I am happy to report that everything went as planned yesterday. Sam cam through the surgery to establish the new central line without any difficulty – though a little tender where he opened up. The new central line working as expected, this line (aka Hickman device) was established travelling from Sam’s leg through to the major vessels just below his heart. The previous PICC lines were not able to reach the major vessels near the heart as there was too much clotting in Sam’s chest. With this new line established round two of chemotherapy has begun.</p>
<p>Chemotherapy medications were started promptly after Sam returned from surgery and a short period in recovery. All of these medications are entering his system through the central line system along with <em>a lot</em> of additional fluid. As I have noted in previous posts the drugs are intense and in order to protect his other organs additional fluid is needed. Practically speaking this means that life, and sleep are interrupted with many bathroom breaks.</p>
<p>Gram and Papa were here providing moral and practical support. We also had a visit from Lisa S. who brought a stack of cards from home with messages of encouragement from Sam’s friends at the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church’s</a> youth group, along with cards for Tina and I.</p>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Surgery went well. Finally, an effective central line has been established allowing treatment to begin.</p></li>
<li><p>Chemotherapy round 2 has begun. This is a much more powerful treatment then the first. There are risks and side effects. The risks include potential damage to Sam’s organs (e.g.&nbsp;liver and kidneys). Side effects are expected to start showing within a week, including hair loss, and generally feeling gross.</p></li>
<li><p>I expect we will not experience solid sleeps over these next number of days as there is a flurry of drugs, testing of fluids, and release of excess fluids … these interruptions are about every 2-3 hours.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all support of friends, family, rekindling old friendships, and care received from strangers</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for an amazing medical team here at BC Children’s hospital.</p></li>
<li><p>Tina and I are thankful for Sam. He continues to have an amazing attitude through everything!</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>procedures</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-13_chemo-round2-began.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Assembling at the chemotherapy starting line (round 2)</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-12_starting-line-round-2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Today our waiting period should be ending. We will have a few last hours of anticipation before Sam heads down to surgery for a third attempt to establish a central line. Assuming all goes as planned he will begin round two of chemotherapy. This next round is likely what we all think about when it comes to chemotherapy as the medicines used are so intense that Sam will likely lose his hair. The full therapy session is 21 days, with the first five being the medicinal treatment and the following 16 being for recovery. We are expecting by mid-next week Sam might be feeling pretty rough.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-10" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-10">Reflections on May 10</h2>
<p>Yesterday was fairly calm with the usual visits by doctors and nurses. Gram and Papa were here and their presence allowed Tina and I to get away. I even had a couple hours on my own. My brother-in-law has lent me his electric bike and I went exploring the great network of bike lanes through numerous neighbourhoods across Vancouver (17km ride). This trip included some stops to pick up essential supplies including a stop at a gluten-free bakery for Tina.</p>
<p>The level of care continues to be amazing. Sam had a headache in the afternoon and given that the he does have some blood clots the doctors have reason to monitor this as a concern and ordered an MRI which he received hours later. Sam definitely has his humor back stating to the doctor that <em>we will set your mind at ease by looking at my mind</em>.</p>
<p>As a family we had a relaxing evening. We walked out to the deck where Sam and I played a <a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/154597/hive-pocket">hive pocket</a>. Sam destroyed me the first time we played but I managed a win yesterday – though my brain hurt. A solid strategy game that does not take that long to play.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam goes into surgery in the late morning – scheduled for 11:30. This line will be inserted in the leg and travel up to the inferior vena cava – just below the heart. In addition, instead of having the lines dangling from his leg the surgeon wants to create an outlet in Sam’s abdomen, above the belt-line, which will allow him to remain mobile.</p></li>
<li><p>Chemotherapy should begin this afternoon. This brings with it a couple main concerns.</p>
<ul>
<li>That this treatment is effective a removing cancer from Sam’s body</li>
<li>There are common side effects such as hair loss, temporary impacts on Sam’s immune system, generally feeling gross, and the potential for others. We don’t expect anything symptoms of these in the next 24-48 hours but they will come.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all of the support we have received, your care and prayers, messages, visits, and gifts. We are blessed to have such a community around us.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="meditation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="meditation">Meditation</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>He gives strength to the weary<br>
and increases the power of the weak.<br>
Even youths grow tired and weary,<br>
and young men stumble and fall;<br>
but those who hope in the Lord<sup>1</sup><br>
will renew their strength.<br>
They will soar on wings like eagles;<br>
they will run and not grow weary,<br>
they will walk and not be faint.</p>
<p>Isaiah. 40 v. 29-31 NIV translation</p>
</blockquote>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>alternately: those who wait on the Lord (ESV)↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>procedures</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-12_starting-line-round-2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>In preparation for chemotherapy – waiting</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-11_brief-update.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>We are in a waiting period. The next round of chemo cannot begin until the new central line is established. Over the last couple days:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>We have had visits with various doctors to discuss the next steps (e.g.&nbsp;procedure for central line and chemotherapy treatments).</p></li>
<li><p>To ensure that Sam gets the nutrition that he needs in the weeks ahead he had a new NG tube installed – allowing for supplemental food to be pumped to his stomach via a tube going in his nose and down to the stomach.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has good energy these days and we have been walking around the hospital and Sam is looking at his schoolwork via google-classrooms – getting excited about finishing grade nine.</p></li>
<li><p>Yesterday evening my parents arrived. Sam and Papa enjoyed watching the hockey game together while Tina and I got away together for a good dinner a few blocks away on Main St.</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<p><em>repeated from yesterday</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>We are very thankful for the entire medical team here. The care-aid and nurses take on the day-to-day care, each with their own style of care but all doing a great job of addressing needs as they arise. The support teams including IV, nutrition, and physio. The cleaning staff who are so polite. Sam’s doctors who are excellent communicators and are gracious in allowing time for dialogue and answering our questions when they have answers, and are straight with us when they do not know.</p></li>
<li><p>There are a lot of unknowns going forward. Sam’s form of cancer is mostly unknown. As such, the treatment plan / chemotherapy will be to hit it with the largest hammer available. This will be hard on Sam’s body and we hope much harder on the cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation, another attempt to establish a central-line will be made. As the clotting in the chest blocking access via the arms towards the heart a line will be attempted through the vessels in one of Sams’s legs, to approach the heart from below. Once this line is established chemotherapy will begin. Timing will be based on the next available time… this may be as late as Friday.</p></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-11_brief-update.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>In preparation for chemotherapy</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-10_brief-update.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I’ll keep it brief this morning. We are now in preparation mode for the next round of chemotherapy. It will hit hard, but I will describe that within the next couple days. There are a number of steps that need to occur before we begin – I have included these below</p>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>We are very thankful for the entire medical team here. The care-aid and nurses take on the day-to-day care, each with their own style of care but all doing a great job of addressing needs as they arise. The support teams including IV, nutrition, and physio. The cleaning staff who are so polite. Sam’s doctors who are excellent communicators and are gracious in allowing time for dialogue and answering our questions when they have answers, and are straight with us when they do not know.</p></li>
<li><p>There are a lot of unknowns going forward. Sam’s form of cancer is mostly unknown. As such, the treatment plan / chemotherapy will be to hit it with the largest hammer available. This will be hard on Sam’s body and we hope much harder on the cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation, another attempt to establish a central-line will be made. As the clotting in the chest blocking access via the arms towards the heart a line will be attempted through the vessels in one of Sams’s legs, to approach the heart from below. Once this line is established chemotherapy will begin. Timing will be based on the next available time… this may be as late as Friday.</p></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-10_brief-update.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PICCs and other procedures</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-09_PICCs-procedures.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Sam and I are both up. Sam is in good spirits having had a sound sleep last night. It must have been a quality sleep because it certainly was not a long one … we should both take naps today. Last night we watched a very disappointing hockey game and then had a gaming session. I confess it got later than it should and Tina was not here to put a stop to it. She went to have a full night sleep at the <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">RMDH</a> and I hope that she is able to sleep well into the morning. As I write this Sam is reading a classic – if you know that the answer is <code>42</code> then you know the series he just started.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-8" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-8">Reflections on May 8</h2>
<p>To start the day we thought it would be rather simple and that the afternoon would be relaxed… It wasn’t all bad though there are some concerning elements, it just did not all go as planned. The bulk of the day</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>To start Sam did go under general anesthetic to adjust his <a href="http://www.cw.bc.ca/library/pdf/pamphlets/BCCH1552_PICC.pdf">PICC-line</a> and complete a lumbar puncture. The PICC procedure did not go the way the medical team had hoped. The plan was simply to adjust the position of the existing line, but they were not able to do this so they pulled that line and attempted a new line on the other arm. This new line also did not go as planned, as they were not able to centrally locate the outlet. This is where there is some concern, attempts to (re)position the previous or locate the current line failed due to blood clots in Sam’s system. No one is very clear as to why he has clots so frequently in his blood vessels (to be clear this is not because they are keeping anything from us … it is just they do not know). We know that some of the clots are an effect of the cancer – as the body tried to fight it; alternately, this clotting could be somehow related to the previous chemotherapy. The fact is there is clotting in Sam’s blood vessels, and there is more clotting than a couple weeks ago despite taking blood thinners twice a day.</p></li>
<li><p>The lumbar puncture went as planned.</p></li>
<li><p>The quiet afternoon turned into an additional procedure. The previous scans had focused on the upper chest and neck. This ultrasound was done to evaluate the potential of clotting in the abdomen and legs. Results are pending.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>We were finally back to the room by about 4pm. Time for dinner. I had left overs. A friend had brought poke bowls yesterday and the left over one as almost as good as the first. Sam had a hospital dinner supplemented with snacks from Safeway. Tina was off on her own adventure.</p>
<p>I am so happy for Tina as she was able to get away yesterday afternoon. Senga was here and she took her out to a local park and then out for a Tina-friendly meal.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam has a new PICC, despite not being placed idealy it should work.</p></li>
<li><p>Concerns around clotting in Sam’s blood vessels. He is on blood thinners but there appear be more clots than a couple weeks ago.</p></li>
<li><p>We are expecting to meet with the Dr.&nbsp;Cheng this afternoon to discuss recent results and plans for Sam’s next round of chemotherapy – which may start tomorrow.</p></li>
<li><p>Joyful for connections with friends – in person and through communication.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-09_PICCs-procedures.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ambassadors from Prince George</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-08_PG-ambassadors.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/20230506_sam-hunter-cedars.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Great visits with Hunter this past weekend. Hunter also brought gifts from friends in Prince George. Sam is looking forward to cashing in a gift card for some chicken nuggets.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This morning as I write, I am also chatting with my boy. He is in great spirits. He is also hungry: <em>This smile will be a lot bigger when I get food</em>. In a couple hours Sam will have a procedure to adjust the internal position of his PICC (so no food allowed until after the procedure). The medical team is also hoping while he is under general anesthetic he will also get a lumbar puncture to continue monitoring Sam’s health there.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-the-weekend" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-the-weekend">Reflections on the weekend</h2>
<p>This past weekend we had some great visits with friends from Prince George. Hunter and Sam have been great friends since grade 1. It was great to have him visit, and to see these friends reconnect, talk and laugh. Hunter, also acted as an ambassador delivering gifts to Sam from his class, and another bag of gifts for Tina and I – friends sent us some cozy clothes.</p>
<p>Yesterday our good friends Beth H. was also able to visit bringing gifts from her family. I also love how she was able to bring refreshment to Tina’s soul.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam goes under general anesthetic this am (~9:30) to adjust his PICC and possibly a lumbar puncture.</p></li>
<li><p>We are encouraged that the results from last Friday were so positive – with a 40% reduction in the size of the tumor. We also remain hopeful that the cancer will continue to be responsive to treatment.</p></li>
<li><p>We continue to feel loved an supported. Friends want to be here with us, and send there love when they cannot. Friends, family, and a broader community of support continue to send their love.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-08_PG-ambassadors.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/20230506_sam-hunter-cedars.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Response to the first round of chemotherapy</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-06_results-1st-chemotherapy.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Yesterday, Sam finished his first round of chemotherapy his final round of drugs. Mid-morning he had a CT scan. In the afternoon we had a visit with Dr.&nbsp;Cheng to discuss the results and the next steps. Being that Sam’s cancer is very rare we did not know if it would respond to the chemotherapy. I am so glad to say that it has.</p>
<ul>
<li>The size of the main tumor in Sam’s chest has seen an estimated 40% reduction in size.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is excellent news – though there is much work to be done. It has been amazing to see Sam’s body respond so well this past week and to know that the cancer was reduced in size. With these results in, the beginnings of a plan can be made, and we have an idea of what the next couple weeks will look like.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>This coming Monday Sam will have two procedures.</p>
<ul>
<li>Adjustments to his PICC line. Initial problems with the PICC resolved – how or why remain unclear, but the result was that regular blood tests (on average about every 8 hours) were taken easily via the PICC line. Going forward, the PICC need some re-positioning to allow for the safe delivery of the next round of chemotherapy.</li>
<li>A lumbar puncture to confirm that the caner continues to not be in the central nervous system (there is some concern that this form of cancer could migrate there). Dr.&nbsp;will also inject chemotherapy medications into the spinal fluid as a preventative measure.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Tuesday, Dr.&nbsp;Cheng will be presenting Sam’s case and consulting with other experts in the field. That afternoon, the we should know the plan for the next round of chemotherapy.</p></li>
<li><p>Wednesday, the next week of chemotherapy should begin.</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Excellent results from the first week of chemotherapy.</p></li>
<li><p>On the flip-side, there is much work to be done to further reduce and ultimately remove the cancer. There is always a possibility that the disease adapts and stops responding</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for an amazing community of people around us. We have been encouraged and gifted beyond what we could have ever expected.</p></li>
<li><p>Yesterday we spent time as a family simply listing things that we are thankful for. It was a beautiful time.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-06_results-1st-chemotherapy.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2023 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Anticipation of next steps</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-05_anticipation.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>This morning’s run of pills will mark the end of Sam’s first round of chemotherapy. At 9:30 Sam is scheduled for a CT scan and we will wait in anticipation for the results, as the scan will help inform our next steps including: 1) the need (or not) of a new central line for drug delivery, and 2) response of the cancer so far and a strategy moving forward.</p>
<section id="reflection-on-may-4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflection-on-may-4">Reflection on May 4</h2>
<p>Sam was full of energy and he was determined to show the physiotherapist all that he could do. We went for a couple of walks including getting off the floor and getting outside. Sam was also able to be disconnected from his IV and we are all loving the freedom that comes with that.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>CT scan today, the information will be used to determine next steps.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam is mobile and regaining strength. So great to have a break from IV line.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern that the cancer responds well to the treatment and wisdom for the next steps.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-05_anticipation.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Clarifying… from what I understand</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-04_current-understanding.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/img/230504_sunrise.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Sunrise from BC Children’s Hospital... Finally providing the ‘room with a view’ picture.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It looks like another beautiful sunny day here in Vancouver. The sun is just coming up over the mountains and is beaming into Sam’s room. These early morning hours are usually my as my family sleeps, and I take time to think, to pray, and to write. Not really no changes from yesterday we continue to slide into this pattern of routine. Nurses will be by to check-in, other members of the medical team will be what feels like randomly, as they move around the hospital checking on all their patients. Life as a patient definitely requires just that patience as you are either waiting for news, waiting for next steps, or generally having life interrupted. Don’t get me wrong, the care Sam is receiving is incredible. Being a patient is just a minor challenge in this process.</p>
<section id="clarifying-from-what-i-understand" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="clarifying-from-what-i-understand">Clarifying, from what I understand</h2>
<p>It really has been encouraging to see Sam come back, the return of his humor, his appetite, desires to do things. This morning, I want to explain my understanding of what has been happening with him. Before arriving, Sam was very sick, having extreme lethargy, and barely able to get out of bed. His body’s immune system was on overdrive in effort to battle what we now know is the cancer. The effect of this was that his whole body inflamed – think of a time that you had a small cut or burn and your skin was red and a little puffy around the injury… now take that idea and apply it to inside Sam’s body, and the majority of the lymphatic system. So why is he so much better now? Why does the treatment seem to be working so well? Is Sam healing?</p>
<p>Treatment started this past Friday, six days ago, and by the end of Saturday Sam was already feeling much better. This is actually an expected response. I am unclear if how dramatic the response is was expected, but the medical team did expect a fairly rapid response. One of the drugs that is part of Sam chemotherapy <em>prednisone</em>, which can be used to change the way the body ’s immune system reacts – effectively taking the immune system out of overdrive and reducing all that internal swelling.</p>
<p>So is Sam getting better? Sam is definitely feeling better and has a much improved quality of life, and I hope and pray that he is getting better in the long term. However, I need to be clear, when it comes to the cancer in his body, we just do not know.</p>
<p>Sam is now scheduled for a scan tomorrow morning. We will know more once those results are in.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are stunned, blessed, blown-away by the generosity of so many through the <a href="https://www.gofundme.com/f/help-the-chisholm-family-while-sam-battles-cancer">GoFundMe</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam’s has had the return of mobility and an appetite. Walking around a little yesterday was encouraging but I also recognize that Sam has lost alot of strength, which we will need to see him build back.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern that the cancer responds well to the treatment.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-04_current-understanding.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://samc-news.netlify.app/img/230504_sunrise.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Current plans</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-03_current-plans.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It is Wednesday morning, day 15, I just arrived at the hospital having had a full night sleep. My family is sleeping, and it appears that I was not missed overnight – so good.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-2" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-2">Reflections on May 2</h2>
<p>Breakfast this am was a beautiful surprise, as friends from Prince George ordered us an amazing breakfast from Juliet’s Cafe including a Tina friendly version. The remainder of the morning was a parade of various members of the medical team. This included a visit with Dr.&nbsp;Cheng, Sam’s oncologist – we reviewed the plan going forward with her (below).</p>
<p>The afternoon and evening was similar with various visits. I got out for a couple hours to do some shopping to gear us up to live here. A carry-on bag of cloths was just not enough and we all needed some new socks. Tomorrow I will get out to stock up on snacks – as our boy’s appetite continues to strengthen. In the evening, the three of us got out onto a deck and watched the sunset.</p>
</section>
<section id="plans" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="plans">Plans</h2>
<p>Sam’s treatment plan does not extend very far. Here is what I currently know… though plans change based on numerous factors.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Currently, Sam is mid-way through his first round of chemotherapy.</li>
<li>On Friday, he will go for a scan. The purpose of this will be two-fold
<ol type="a">
<li>To evaluate the response of the cancer to the current treatment</li>
<li>To evaluate if PICC to determine if it will work for delivering future treatment.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>On Monday, Sam may have to have place a new central line.</li>
</ol>
<p>That’s it! We have an idea of what the next five days may hold. The medical team does not know what the steps are beyond as they do not have the data. Although it would be nice to know what Sam is in for, what challenges he may have to face, I appreciate that decisions are being made based on the information available. When more is known, informed decisions can be made.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Umm, Wow! We are stunned, blessed, blown-away by the generosity of so many as evidenced by the <a href="https://www.gofundme.com/f/help-the-chisholm-family-while-sam-battles-cancer">GoFundMe</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Needles: Sam is doing really well with them. Though the potential of installing a new central line (PICC) is a challenging thought.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam’s has had the return of mobility and an appetite.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern that the cancer responds well to the treatment.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-03_current-plans.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Humbled by generosity</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-02_humbled-assistance.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="gofundme-insert" style="float: right; width: 50%; padding: 0 0pt 3pt 6pt; min-width: 320px;">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/img/family_2022.jpg" style="width: 100%; border: solid 1px #c8c8c8"></p>
<div class="gfm-embed" data-url="https://www.gofundme.com/f/help-the-chisholm-family-while-sam-battles-cancer/widget/medium">
<script defer="" src="https://www.gofundme.com/static/js/embed.js"></script>
</div>
</div>
<p>Today marks two weeks here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Children’s hospital</a>. We continue to receive amazing care from the medical team, and we continue to be carried/surrounded by the love and prayers of all of you our friends and family, and we are humbled by your help!</p>
<p>Thank you all for your words of encouragement, gifts, and prayers. It seems you are unstoppable in finding ways to pour out your love and generosity. A number of days ago some friends convinced us that this <a href="https://www.gofundme.com/manage/help-the-chisholm-family-while-sam-battles-cancer">GoFundMe</a> page would be a good idea to support us in the expense of this current journey and to give people a means of providing tangible support. Please do not feel any obligation to give.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-1">Reflections on May 1</h2>
<p>Yesterday, was a great day! The issue of Sam’s feeding tube resolved by having to remove the tube. This turned out for the best as Sam got his appetite back. I can’t remember the last time Sam ate so well! Sam also noted that it is much easier to eat without the tube in. The medical team is also happy about this latest development.</p>
<p>Activity levels are also coming up. Sam is able to walk around some more. He was able to walk the hall here and he spent an hour sitting up and talking with his Uncle Cal.</p>
<p>These recent changes certainly give us hope for the future and definitely joy in the here-and-now. We are grateful for all of this. We have been cautioned that these improvements can be expected, but that the only way to evaluate if the cancer is responding is to complete new scans to see what has happened to the tumors. We will continue to choose hope and take joy in each victory.</p>
<p>Going forward, the next days ahead should be routine with medicines, bloodwork, checking vitals, and a new addition of prescribed physiotherapy. In about a week Sam will go for imaging and then the next steps will be determined.</p>
</section>
<section id="needs-concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="needs-concerns-and-victories">Needs, concerns, and victories</h2>
<p>Mostly victories today!</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Tina had a a full night sleep in our room at the [Ronald McDonald House] (night of April 30).</p></li>
<li><p>We all slept well last night (the family still is). Sam commented how cozy he felt after his nurse re-tucked him in following bloodwork and a bathroom break.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has his appetite back.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam’s activity level is improving.</p></li>
<li><p>I am thankful for messages and outpourings of love that we have received.</p></li>
<li><p>The cancer, and that it responds treatment, remains our largest concern.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-02_humbled-assistance.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A good day, but a rough night…</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-01_NG-tube-mishap.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It is currently just after 7:00am here. Sam is currently sleeping soundly, and I hope that Tina is having a good and lengthy sleep. Tina took a turn to sleep at our room at the Ronald McDonald House – her first night away from Sam since coming to Vancouver. Honestly it was a good night to miss… nothing major, just problems with the little things.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-april-30" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-april-30">Reflections on April 30</h2>
<p>Yesterday, was mostly quiet. Almost like we are entering into a routine. Sam was full of energy to start the day, feeling better than he had for months. We got out of the room, taking a tour of the ward, and checking out the youth room where we discovered options for art, music, a library of games (digital and board), movies, and video games. We made plans to start a Harry Potter movie marathon.</p>
<p>Sam was hungry again and I biked down to Broadway to grab a pizza (a great outing for me). It is weird, but life felt … normal. Our normal, now includes regular check-ins with nurses and doctors who are doing their routines of checking vitals, taking blood, loading Sam’s supplemental feeding, adjusting oxygen… <em>this is normal? this is routine?</em> Yes, it seems to be… and it was all going well until it wasn’t.</p>
<p>It is amazing how one tiny little thing can mess up your routine Something jammed up Sam’s NG-tube<sup>1</sup>. Attempts to clear it resulted in spillage and literally hours of frustration and extra work by the nurses. Sam has been patient through most all of it, and lost some significant time for sleeping… it is still not cleared.</p>
<!-- What I did not talk about was all of the extra alarms: obstructed lines, -->
<!-- sensors alarming regarding heart rates, or O~2~ -->
</section>
<section id="needs-concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="needs-concerns-and-victories">Needs, concerns, and victories</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>We are thankful to see Sam feeling so much better. We hope that this means he is getting better, but we will not know until Sam has his next scan which is not for about a week.</p></li>
<li><p>The little things matter in life – for all of us. Even though the little things may be issues in a larger storm they have a strong influence on life. I am thankful for the little-graces. I am learning to not take them for granted. I also hope for little graces in this journey ahead.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the medical team for all their hard work and care.</p></li>
<li><p>We also cannot forget the larger issue. We are in a major storm of life. Sam has cancer. His prognosis is unknown. We choose hope, but that does not mean waves of fear to not threaten to swamp us. We hope and pray for his healing. That the cancer would respond to treatment. That we would be able to go home together.</p></li>
</ol>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Nasogasteric feeding tube (i.e.&nbsp;through the nose to the gut)↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-01_NG-tube-mishap.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Joy in all the small victories</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-30_All-the-small-victories.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/img/tina-colin-BCCH-deck.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Sam is not a fan of getting his picture taken – so you get the two of us. Love to you all.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It is a beautiful Sunday morning, my family is sleeping. It is true the last days have been challenging, our lives have taken a huge turn. There have been tears, and fears. Today as I write, I have to reflect on the grace given us. There is no denying it. We have been blanketed in the love of friends and family. Thank you all for your notes of encouragement, your prayers, your solidarity in our circumstance. Today, I can share joys!</p>
<section id="reflections-on-april-29" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-april-29">Reflections on April 29</h2>
<section id="thankful-for-victories" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thankful-for-victories">Thankful for victories</h3>
<p>Yesterday was a day of grace, joy, and fun! As I reflect on the day, I am shocked at the contrast to the shock and challenges of the days prior. Yesterday was filled with many victories.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>We haven’t seen Sam have energy like this in over well over a month.</li>
<li>Times sitting up.<br>
</li>
<li>Concentrations levels to
<ul>
<li>Great visits and conversations with guests including: Shalom, a friend from PG; and his cousins Amanda, Chris and Mary-Joy.</li>
<li>Conquer Mario Kart tracks</li>
<li>Take in NHL playoffs</li>
<li>Read comic books</li>
</ul></li>
<li>He was hungry, and the cousins brought Wendy’s</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="health-and-healing-victories" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-and-healing-victories">Health and healing victories</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Sam’s PICC continues to function. This is a big deal. Blood chemistry is every four hours, and without the PICC it would mean needles for every sample. Today, needles to draw blood were not necessary.</p></li>
<li><p>On needles. Sam gets a small injection every 12 hours. Our nursing team might be in competition to see who can deliver with the least pain. Of the last three needles Sam felt one, a bit; didn’t feel one at all; and was tickled by a third. Wow, if we can keep this pattern going that would be amazing. Happy for what we have now.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam was able to complete the intake of his intense chemotherapy chemicals. If you have ever been in the health care system for more than a couple days you likely know the importance of … movements. Alex, Sam’s nurse, literally danced for joy as this health moment. The timing of this was critical to allow for the taking of the drugs. Also, if it had taken any longer Sam might have needed a yet another new IV.</p></li>
</ol>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-30_All-the-small-victories.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://samc-news.netlify.app/img/tina-colin-BCCH-deck.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Diagnosis and the initiation of treatment</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-29_diagnosis-and-treatment.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>My morning has started with an encouraging time with my boy. I managed to get some sleep over at the Ronald McDonald House and came back to Sam’s room for 5:00 (these days that is sleeping in for me). Shortly after I got here Sam woke up. Despite the intensity of the previous day, despite the pains in his body, he was full of faith and joy. He celebrated that his PICC worked for the latest blood-work (currently running at every four hours). We chatted for a bit, I rubbed his back, wrapped him in a warm blanket, and then tucked him back in. Currently he is sleeping soundly.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-april-28" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-april-28">Reflections on April 28</h2>
<p>This date will be significant to use for the rest of our lives – that day we received a diagnosis and the initiation of treatment.</p>
<section id="diagnosis-and-treatment" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="diagnosis-and-treatment">Diagnosis and Treatment</h3>
<p>In the morning the lead care team (Oncologist, Clinical Care Nurse, and Social Worker) met with us – the three of us to start, and then Tina and I for the details. Finally we have a diagnosis, Sam’s cancer has been identified. We have been looking forward to this as a diagnosis leads to a plan … if you know what it is, you can know how to treat it. We all wish it was that simple.</p>
<p>Sam has an extremely rare form of cancer. It is a blood-based cancer mostly located in the lymphatic system. The name of the disease is almost as long as the first two sentences in this paragraph. We know what to call it, we know where it is, the team will treat it. However, the treatment plan will be week-to-week, and as treatment phases are completed, additional steps will be taken to evaluate the response/impact on the disease.</p>
<p>Phase 1 of treatment has started, a round of chemotherapy, and we know the plan for this week.</p>
<p>I have to add that Sam is a champ! Today’s needle count tallied to 4 including the addition a new IV line.</p>
</section>
<section id="surrounded-by-love" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="surrounded-by-love">Surrounded by love</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>My Mom and Dad were here and were have to have a good time talking with Sam while Tina and I met with the medical team. I am glad they were here. It was good to share tears with them.</p></li>
<li><p>Rhoda and Dave, had a great conversation with Sam, and gifted him with comics and games</p></li>
<li><p>Tina had a great call with sister.</p></li>
<li><p>Many thanks to all of you for your notes of support, well-wishes, and prayers! Your words, stories, encouragement, and solidarity with us are amazing.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="needs-concerns-and-victories" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="needs-concerns-and-victories">Needs, concerns and victories</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>We are all walking in the dark. Our family and the Drs. Pray for wisdom to simply see the next step.</p></li>
<li><p>We need to see the cancer respond to the treatment. It is unknown, how this cancer will respond, or how it may adapt/ resist.</p></li>
<li><p>Chemotherapy, is intense, and some of the chemicals are literally poison. We have entered a world of trade-offs. The disease must die, but the treatment has dangers and significant potential side-effects.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>We will count the small victories and joys</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam took on numerous pokes/needles like a champ.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam’s PICC worked … most of the time.</p></li>
<li><p>Out of bed. Sam’ has been sick and mostly bed-ridden. He enjoyed some time out of bed sitting up in a chair.</p></li>
<li><p>It was a puppy therapy day today. If you know Sam you know he loves dogs.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="meditation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="meditation">Meditation</h3>
<p>There are two passages of scripture that are constantly in my mind. Two passages that reflect in-part where I am at.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>He guides me along the right paths for his name’s sake. Even though I walk through the darkest valley, I will fear no evil, for you are with me; <a href="https://www.bible.com/bible/111/PSA.23.NIV">Psalm 23</a></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>if you can do anything, take pity on us and help us.” “ ‘If you can’?”said Jesus. “Everything is possible for one who believes.” Immediately the boy’s father exclaimed, “I do believe; help me overcome my unbelief!” <a href="https://www.bible.com/bible/111/MRK.9.NIV">Mark 9:14f</a></p>
</blockquote>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-29_diagnosis-and-treatment.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pending decisions</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-28_confirming-cancer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Thank-you! We have received so many notes of solidarity, encouragement, and prayer. The community of support around us, all of you, is amazing!</p>
<section id="reflections-on-april-27th." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-april-27th.">Reflections on April 27<sup>th</sup>.</h2>
<p>I’m going to keep this one quick … we are in a state of hyper-vigilance for Sam, staying in the room with him. This is something that is essential for now, though not sustainable… we are stressed and exhausted.</p>
<ul>
<li>My parents, Earle and Dorothy, are here with us. Great to have their support. Thanks to the many who are also supporting them.</li>
<li>Recent scans confirm where the cancer is. No new surprises, though the impact of the cancer on Sam is stronger than previously known.</li>
<li>Cancer diagnosis is still pending. It is expected that BC Cancer Clinic will be able to identify the disease.</li>
<li>However, we may not be able to wait. Initial treatment steps may need to be taken before the diagnosis is in. From the medical perspective this is about managing risk. Starting treatment without diagnosis may impact longer term effectiveness of the treatments; not starting could allow the cancer to impact Sam in the now.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-28_confirming-cancer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
