<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Sam Chisholm</title>
<link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>News updating friends and family on our journey</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.361</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Holding Pattern – Waiting</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2405/2024-05-05_waiting.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<!-- 
::: {.callout-note icon="false"}
## TL;DR [Too long didn't read (i.e. the short version)]{.small}
::: -->
<p>It has been ten days since we returned to Vancouver. Life has been fairly routine, even slow. We have we been checking in with the hospital clinic. So far the metrics associated with Sam’s liver numbers are going the right direction. This suggests that the liver is healing/ becoming less inflamed.</p>
<p>This week we have a few items on the agenda: a) Clinic check-ins, b) Ultrasound of the liver to verify that the non-cancerous mass there is either stable or improving, and c) PET scan (possibly). The PET scan is the big item as it will show us the status of the cancer in Sam’s body. Results of the PET will also strongly inform Sam’s next treatment(s).</p>
<p>This journey has been long and we are tired. This past weekend family facilitated me having a break. Tina and Sam stayed with Mary and the Fricker family (Tina’s sister’s family) giving me almost 24 hours off. It was great to have that time without responsibilities.</p>
<p>Sam remains positive and is growing stronger. Tina and I are glad to see this. However, we cannot escape feelings of needing to be vigilant and anxious about what could be happening undetected – the results of the PET scan this week will be very helpful.</p>
<!-- 
::: {#photo}
![Sam was a great copilot in our journeys north and then south](https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-04-21_road-trip.jpg)
::: -->
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We celebrate that we were able to have a trip home. So good to connect with friends and family!</p></li>
<li><p>We celebrate that a year following the start of treatment, Sam is feeling the best he has ever felt.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the original central mass is stable. Thankful that three disease centers, treated using targeted radiation, have been removed.</p></li>
<li><p>Ongoing immune therapy has de-regulated Sam’s immune system. Side effects are becoming dangerous as Sam’s liver is inflamed. In order to continue with the immune therapy drugs, Sam’s immune system needs to be brought back to a regulated state. Recent bloodwork suggests that things are returning to normal function.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>new-sites</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2405/2024-05-05_waiting.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Break at Home!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-25_first-break-home.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<!-- 
::: {.callout-note icon="false"}
## TL;DR [Too long didn't read (i.e. the short version)]{.small}
::: -->
<div id="photo">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-04-21_road-trip.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Sam was a great copilot in our journeys north and then south</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>It has been a whirlwind trip back home. We connected with more people than we expected and yet missed too many of you. I hope you can forgive us if you were missed – we really have more love than we had time. Three days in the city was not enough but we were glad for it! It was also incredible to re-connect, even if just in-part, with the community that has been supporting us.</p>
<section id="travel-log" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="travel-log">Travel log</h2>
<p>The initial idea to travel was presented last Wednesday, April 17. However, actual travel plans were dependent on metrics on Sam’s bloodwork that would allow the medical team to decide if it would be safe for Sam to travel. Specifically, if Sam’s numbers were not good on the Friday, we check again on the Monday, and if they were not good then the trip would be cancelled. So to keep things flexible we chose to drive. As a family we have always done road trips and Sam was looking forward to this pilgrimage drive home.</p>
<section id="day-1-travel" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-1-travel">Day 1 – Travel</h3>
<p><em>Sunday, April 21</em></p>
<p>We got away from Vancouver at a good time. It was a cool cloudy day with some showers heading into the Fraser Canyon. We had a great early lunch at Horsting’s Farm near Cache Creek. In the afternoon we stopped to see Renee near Williams Lake. Refreshed and fed we travelled on arriving at my parents as the sun was setting.</p>
<p>We received a loving welcome from Mom and Dad and all of us loved seeing Sam reconnect with Buddy – his dog was crazy excited to see him! We were also able to catch the last two periods of the first Vancouver vs. Nashville playoff game.</p>
</section>
<section id="day-2-family" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-2-family">Day 2 – Family</h3>
<p><em>Monday</em></p>
<p>This was really the only day that we had any sort of plan which was to make family our priority. The earlier part of the day was spent with my parents and the evening with Tom, Margaret, Daniel and Alex. Good times connecting, talking, and playing games together.</p>
</section>
<section id="day-3-school" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-3-school">Day 3 – School</h3>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div id="photo2" class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-04-23_school-friends_x.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Sam loved reconnecting with his friends at school and later at youth group!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div id="Tuesday" class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><em>Tuesday</em></p>
<p>We let this day be driven by Sam and how he was feeling – he was feeling good. Mid-morning Sam had a great idea of visiting his friends at school over the lunch break. It was so good to see him simply slip into life at the school. We ended up spending the entire afternoon there as Sam joined in to classes. Tina and I connected with staff and a number of friends as parents rolled in for afterschool pickup.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- The evening was spent at Mom and Dads -- Dave and Ben joined to watch hockey. -->
</section>
<section id="day-4-whirlwind" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-4-whirlwind">Day 4 – Whirlwind</h3>
<p><em>Wednesday</em></p>
<p>Wednesday was more of a whirlwind. Sam had an appointment at the hospital pediatric clinic. This was our first connection with the Prince George team. Although they do not specialize in cancer treatment it was good to see how much ca be taken care of at the hospital back home. In the afternoon we squeezed in some visits with friends and dinner with the grandparents. In the evening Sam was able to attend youth group at the church!</p>
<!-- - Breakfast with Brian -->
<!-- - Medical team visit (I)
- Sam visited with Chase and Ben, while Tina had a quick visit with Joanna I ran out and got food for Sam (prednisone / 15-year-old Sam is always hungry)
- Tina had coffee with Jesse and Aria 
- Sam and I returned to the hospital clinic (II) to review labwork -- which was looking good
- Sam and I ran a couple errands and then returned to Mom and Dad's for dinner
- I ran out to get Edo Japan for Sam, Mom, and I. 
- Ran Sam to youth group
- Ran Tina to visit Sengas
- An hour at our house 
- Picked up Sam from youth group -->
</section>
<section id="day-5-return-to-vancouver" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-5-return-to-vancouver">Day 5 – Return to Vancouver</h3>
<p><em>Thursday</em></p>
<p>We had to head back to Vancouver. It was a great road trip. Sam is looking forward to the day when he can be the driver. In the meantime he watched the road and acted as a good copilot.</p>
<p>It was a great first trip home and hopefully our next one will be in the near future and with more days at home.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="next-steps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next Steps</h2>
<p>In the weeks ahead we are hoping to restart Sam’s immune therapy. This has been delayed as we wait for his immune system to come under control – bloodwork in Prince George suggested that Sam is headed in the right direction. Additionally, he will likely have another PET scan which will hopefully reveal good progress in this ongoing cancer battle.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We celebrate that we were able to have a trip home. So good to connect with friends and family!</p></li>
<li><p>We celebrate that a year following the start of treatment, Sam is feeling the best he has ever felt. We are incredibly grateful.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the original central mass is stable. Thankful that three disease centers, treated using targeted radiation, have been removed.</p></li>
<li><p>Ongoing immune therapy has de-regulated Sam’s immune system. Side effects are becoming dangerous as Sam’s liver is inflamed. In order to continue with the immune therapy drugs, Sam’s immune system needs to be brought back to a regulated state. Recent bloodwork suggests that things are returning to normal function.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>new-sites</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-25_first-break-home.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Happy Anniversary –Celebration!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-18_one-year.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>One year at BCCH</li>
<li>Gratitude for all of the support and care</li>
<li>Celebrating that the cancer is stable and more so that Sam is feeling good</li>
<li>A year in review – milestones of this journey</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div id="photo">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-04_chisholms-spring.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Enjoying a spring walk together. This photo was taken on Easter Monday and was Sam’s biggest walk in over a year.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>It has taken me <del>three</del> four days to write this post. Sam has had such great energy lately. He has been waking up at the same time as me and we have spent our days together – talking, playing, reading, and even sharing the chores.</p>
<p>In the early morning just over a year ago, on April 18, 2023, Sam arrived at BC Children’s hospital. Oh, how far he as come along this incredible journey of seeing him return to health. He is by no means out-of-the-woods yet, but now he can “walk-in-the-woods” with us. Sam is joyful, he has increasing energy and stamina, and his courageous attitude seems to have no limits.</p>
<p>One year ago Tina and Sam had been sent down by air ambulance and were admitted directly to the Pediatric Intensive Care Unit (PICU). I arrived about twelve hours later. Sam remained in PICU for the next number of days while the medical team stabilized him, and initial imaging and biopsies were completed. It would be 10 days later that the biopsy reports were completed and Sam’s cancer was identified. Once identified, we knew we would be travelling a challenging road – one that was not mapped by any procedures or protocols that the medical team could follow.</p>
<section id="gratitude" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gratitude">Gratitude</h2>
<p>We have so much to be grateful for throughout this journey (in no way is this quick list complete).</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam has received incredible medical care at the BC Childrens’ Hospital and BC Cancer Centre</p>
<ul>
<li>The doctors have pooled their collective expertise having to make untold numbers of decisions based on their professional judgement and not just established protocols.</li>
<li>The nurses on the oncology ward and later in clinic have shown Sam (and his parents) incredible care. We will forever treasure the compassion and personal connections that we have had all of you.</li>
<li>Access to incredible tools used to diagnose and accurately locate the disease in Sam, and all of the diligent technicians and radiologists.</li>
<li>All of the support staff, seen and unseen, that have made Sam’s care possible</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>A stranger who provided Sam a new immune system.</p></li>
<li><p>Incredible charities that have supported us</p>
<ul>
<li>The Ronald McDonald House has provided us a home away from home.</li>
<li>Canuck Place has advised on Sam’s care and provided great counsel for Tina and I.</li>
<li>Friends of Children provides assistance to families from northern BC</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>The love of friends and family supporting us. We treasure your visits and communications.</p></li>
<li><p>The hundreds of people praying and caring for Sam – thank you.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="celebration-despite-ambiguity" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="celebration-despite-ambiguity">Celebration despite ambiguity</h2>
<p>There is so much unknown. We know that Sam’s cancer remains. It is unknown if the treatments he has ongoing will be wholly effective.</p>
<p>Despite this ambiguity we celebrate! Currently, Sam is doing well. The last PET scan on April 5<sup>th</sup> suggests that Sam’s cancer has been stable! The central mass remains but has not grown and the immune system has been actively working there. The three disease centres found earlier have been neutralized.</p>
<p>More than the state of the cancer, we celebrate that Sam is feeling good! He is gaining strength. He is active and enjoying life!</p>
<p>There is much work to be done but for the time being it seems we are winning – I pray that this is true and continues to be true.</p>
</section>
<section id="major-milestones" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="major-milestones">Major Milestones</h2>
<p>What a journey this has been. Sam has been through three eras of cancer treatment: 1) chemotherapy, 2) BMT, and now 3) immune therapy. Radiation was given both before the BMT and also concurrent with immunotherapy. Below is provided a quick review of the major milestones.</p>
<section id="chemotherapy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="chemotherapy">Chemotherapy</h3>
<table class="table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 20%">
<col style="width: 41%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Date</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>2023</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>April 17</td>
<td>An alarming x-ray in Prince George provided evidence that Sam needed urgent care at BCCH.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>April 18</td>
<td>Air Ambulance in the early morning and admission to BCCH’s PICU.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>April 22</td>
<td>Transfer to BCCH Oncology Ward (T8).</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>April 28</td>
<td>Diagnosis of a extremely rare form of lymphoma.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>April 29</td>
<td>Chemotherapy is initiated. Sam will receive an additional 6 full rounds of chemotherapy taking him into October.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>June 2</td>
<td>Following his second round of chemotherapy Sam was discharged from the hospital for the first time. This marks the beginning of our family life at RMH. The next months we would visit the oncology clinic regularly. When it was time for each round of chemotherapy we would check into the ward for about 5 days.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>July 14</td>
<td>Plans for a bone marrow transplant were initiated. By mid-summer it became apparent that the chemotherapy would not remove all of the cancer. The remaining rounds of chemotherapy would reduce the cancer as much as possible, and keep it from spreading to new locations, while the BMT was being organized.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Sept.&nbsp;26</td>
<td>Preparations for BMT, baseline testing of Sam was initiated to evaluate impacts of the BMT (i.e.&nbsp;eye, ear, skin, and lung capacity testing).</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Oct.&nbsp;15</td>
<td>Sam completed his final round of chemotherapy.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Oct.&nbsp;23</td>
<td>Targeted radiation therapy over three days to destroy the central mass in Sam’s chest is initiated. This was completed at the BC Cancer Centre over 10 days.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Nov.&nbsp;8</td>
<td>Total body radiation is used to completely remove Sam’s existing immune system – to kill the blood producing cells in his bone marrow. This was done to make way for the bone marrow transplant.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="bone-marrow-transplant" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bone-marrow-transplant">Bone Marrow Transplant</h3>
<table class="table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 20%">
<col style="width: 37%">
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Nov.&nbsp;14</td>
<td>Bone marrow transplant is received. Sam had been admitted to the oncology ward a few days prior in preparation and would remain on ward in isolation for the next number of weeks. This was a particularly intense time as the medical team had to provide so many supports to his body</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Nov.&nbsp;25</td>
<td>First indications that the BMT was establishing – engraftment. Official engraftment would be established on Dec.&nbsp;1 based on metrics from Sam’s blood.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Dec.&nbsp;13</td>
<td>Sam is discharged from the hospital with plans to continue regular check-ins at the oncology clinic.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>2024</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Jan.&nbsp;11</td>
<td>Stepping down from all of the various medications had its challenges. Sam was admitted to the ward for eight days to determine what was causing his extreme lethargy. It was a complicated picture as we all had a flu in the days prior but what Sam was experiencing was more. In the end the main issue seemed to be adrenal insufficiency.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="immune-therapy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="immune-therapy">Immune therapy</h3>
<table class="table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 22%">
<col style="width: 40%">
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Feb.&nbsp;14</td>
<td>PET scan, that we were all hoping to be Sam’s last before having to go home, revealed a horror – the cancer had spread to three new locations. New battle strategies are brought into play. Plans to return home are canceled.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Feb.&nbsp;29</td>
<td>Sam receives his first dose of Nivomulab used to intentionally de-regulate Sam’s immune system and to turn off specific protein markers on the cancer cells that allow them to hide from the immune system.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>March 11</td>
<td>Targeted radiation starts against the three new sites. The shin and hip sites would see higher doses over four days. The T3-vertebrae would see lower daily radiation doses over ten days.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>April 5</td>
<td>PET scan demonstrated that: a) The three new disease sites had been effectively killed using radiation, b) the central mass was stable c) However, a new site in Sam’s liver raised new alarm bells.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>April 11</td>
<td>Biopsy of the liver revealed that this mass is not Sam’s original cancer but an indistinct mass that will be monitored.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We celebrate that a year following the start of treatment, Sam is feeling the best he has ever felt. We are incredibly grateful.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the original central mass is stable. Thankful that three disease centers, treated using targeted radiation, have been removed.</p></li>
<li><p>The newest growth in Sam’s liver is not the original cancer though it will be monitored.</p></li>
<li><p>Ongoing immune therapy has de-regulated Sam’s immune system. Side effects are becoming dangerous as Sam’s liver is inflamed. In order to continue with the immune therapy drugs, Sam’s immune system needs to be brought back to a regulated state.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>new-sites</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-18_one-year.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Catch-22, Biopsy Results</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-16_catch22.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-caution callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
April 18 – Strike out inaccuracies
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>In clinic yesterday, April 17, some of the medical strategies and understandings of Sam’s ongoing treatments were changed.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Primarily, a lower priority is being placed on the mass in Sam’s liver. This tissue is thought to be benign and <em>not</em> the source of stress to his liver.</li>
<li>The source of stress to Sam’s liver is now believed to related to his immune system continuing to run out of control. The use of steroids to bring the immune system in-check has not wholly been effective. New drug therapies have been initiated.</li>
</ol>
<p>I have edited the post below – striking out what is no longer believed to be accurate. <em>New additions are italicized</em>.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Initial biopsy results are complicated.<br>
</li>
<li>The new growth/tumour in Sam’s liver is not the original cancer – what it is, is still being determined.</li>
<li><del>This new spot does need to be treated.</del> The new spot will be monitored but is now thought to be benign.</li>
<li>The main method of treatment for <del>this new growth</del> <em>the immune system running at de-regulated/higher levels</em> is in conflict with ongoing cancer treatment.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<p>Sam and I are up early this morning in anticipation of an ultrasound appointment to image Sam’s liver. It is so nice to chat with my boy in the mornings. His energy has continued to improve over the last 10 days. He does not need to sleep as much and he is able to walk most places now and we are rarely using the wheelchair to transport him around.</p>
<section id="cancer-war" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cancer-war">Cancer war</h2>
<p>Below I attempt to convey the latest biopsy results and what this means for Sam’s cancer treatment. I suggest taking it slow. The picture is complicated as we now how two issues to resolve – the liver, and the cancer.</p>
<section id="initial-biopsy-results" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="initial-biopsy-results">Initial biopsy results</h3>
<p>Last Wednesday, Sam had a biopsy of his a growth in his liver, and yesterday we received some preliminary results. The good news is that this new growth is not Sam’s original cancer! However, we do not yet know definitively what it is – that will need to wait for the full report. <del>What we do know is that this growth is likely a source of dangerous agitation of Sam’s liver, and that it needs to be treated</del>. <em>It is now believed that the source of ongoing agitation to the liver is the on-going de-regulation of Sam’s immune system … effectively GVHD though it can be debated if this is the right term.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="treatment" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="treatment">Treatment</h3>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<dl>
<dt>Catch-22</dt>
<dd>
<p>… a dilemma or difficult circumstance from which there is no escape because of mutually conflicting or dependent conditions (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catch-22_(logic)">Wikipedia</a>)</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</blockquote>
</div>
</div>
<p>We are in ‘catch-22’ situation. The <del>new site in Sam’s liver</del> <em>immune system needs to be brought under control</em> as it is likely the major source of ongoing agitation to Sam’s liver. This is indicated in Sam’s regular bloodwork where various chemicals indicative of liver health and function are dangerously high. <del>The best chemical method for treating growths like this involve using steroids (i.e.&nbsp;Prednisone) – Sam is currently on these</del>. <em>Initial efforts to bring the immune system in-check used steroid (i.e.&nbsp;Prednisone). However, the steroids have shown themselves to only be partially effective and an alternate drug therapy has been initiated.</em></p>
<p>However, this steroidal treatment suppresses the immune system.</p>
<p>In the treatment of Sam’s cancer we have been using drugs to cause Sam’s immune system to be hyperactive (i.e.&nbsp;the opposite of suppressed). As such we are in a catch-22 situation. To treat the liver we must suppress the immune system, to treat the cancer we must make the immune system hyperactive<sup>1</sup>.</p>
<p><em>…Ughhh…</em></p>
<p>The imaging from this morning’s ultrasound, <em>April 16, suggested that the mass in the liver is stable and likely benign – it will be monitored but no further action is currently needed. Medical actions will focus on bringing the immune system under control.</em><del>should provide the medical team enough new information to determine how the current treatment is working and what alternate treatment options may exist.</del></p>
<p>I think what much of this comes down to may simply be timing.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Treat the liver quickly.</li>
<li>With the liver treated we can return to the immune therapy of the cancer.</li>
</ol>
<p>Once the liver agitation is resolved (or mostly resolved). We can return to managing Sam’s cancer.</p>
</section>
<section id="hope-and-anxiety" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hope-and-anxiety">Hope and anxiety</h3>
<dl>
<dt>Hope</dt>
<dd>
<p>If there is anything exciting from all of this it is that the new site is not Sam’s original cancer. This means that Sam’s cancer has been stable since the treatments following the PET scan back in February. This also means that the BMT-immune therapy treatment combination seems to be working.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Anxiety</dt>
<dd>
<p>In waiting for the liver <em>agitation</em> issue to be resolved we are delaying immune therapy treatments for the cancer. During this period it is possible that Sam’s original cancer could get going again.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
</section>
<section id="living-life" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="living-life">Living Life</h2>
<section id="friends-and-family" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friends-and-family">Friends and Family</h3>
<p>We had a good weekend. It has been great to see Sam with more energy and able to engage with people more. An upside of the current steroid treatment is that it has released Sam to have increased energy and we have seen more of chatty-Sam. We were also able to have some great visits. Brian and Hunter were here from Prince George. We were able to visit family and watch the Edmonton-Vancouver hockey game together. Nana Mary arrived yesterday and will stay with us for a few days.</p>
<!-- In the hours and days between clinic and family/friend visits Sam is devouring his latest novel, we haved enjoyed playing board games with other families here at the RMH, and playing some video games.  -->
<p>Sam remains courageous, hopeful, and generally joyful.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that the original central mass is stable. Thankful that three disease centers, treated using targeted radiation, have been removed.</p></li>
<li><p>The newest growth in Sam’s liver is not the original cancer! However, it needs to be treated in order to continue on with Sam’s cancer treatment.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam’s energy has increased!</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam’s pain levels have been stable and generally easy to manage.</p></li>
<li><p>The new immunotherapy drugs seems to have released Sam’s immune system to hit harder. As the immune system was starting to get out of control brakes have been able to slow the immune system back down. It is good to know that the chemical brakes work, at the same time we do not want to suppress the immune system too long as it is the main method of battling the cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>We mourn the loss of Dani – grieving in solidarity with her family.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>The cancer remains and has spread to new areas in Sam’s body. The sites are a mass in the center of his chest (the original), <del>and newer sites in his back (T3 vertebrae), his hip (right ilium), and left shin (tibia just below the knee).</del> Latest scan revealed a potential new site on Sam’s liver.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>It is not quite as simple as this… as the treatments are a not a 1:1 exchange, but alternate treatments do strongly impact each other.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>new-sites</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-16_catch22.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Victories and challenges – we battle on</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-07_battles-won.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
April 11
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Sam came through the biopsy without any issues.</p>
<p>Now we have to wait for the pathology report to let us know what we are dealing with. Initial findings may be available before the weekend, but a full report may take 10 days.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>PET Scan with results this past Friday</li>
<li>Victories at several sites</li>
<li>Stability at the initial site</li>
<li>One new site under investigation</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<section id="cancer-war" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cancer-war">Cancer war</h2>
<p>Sam has summarized this the past two PET scans in the following way (parap hrased):</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The PET scan in February was like someone dumped a load of bricks on me.<br>
This last PET scan was like someone removed all the bricks but then threw a single one at me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sam is great spirits. As the impacts of radiation therapy are behind him, and the effects of GVHD<sup>1</sup> are lessening he is seeing his energy return. Today he wants to go grocery shopping with me.</p>
<section id="review" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="review">Review</h3>
<p>The previous PET, back on Feb 14, provided really hard news. Following months of seeing a new immune system be established in Sam (Nov.&nbsp;- Feb) that imaging showed three new disease sites – it seemed that all of the previous efforts were for naught and that we were losing the cancer war. Despite all of the efforts of the BMT to establishing a new immune system, it did not seem to be effective at beating back the cancer.</p>
<p>Since the discovery of the new sites Sam has received immunotherapy (via the drug Nivomulab) as well as targeted radiation treatment to the new disease centers. The radiation therapy was straight forward and ended a couple weeks ago. With the immune therapy Sam was only able to have a single dose of the Nivomulab which triggered more GVHD<sup>2</sup> than he had seen during his BMT<sup>3</sup>. Although this GVHD was not physically comfortable (e.g.&nbsp;hot rashes, GI<sup>4</sup> effects) it was mentally comforting – if the immune system was attacking healthy tissue it meant that it was most likely also attacking the cancer. Most recently, the immune system started getting dangerously out of control by stressing Sam’s liver. In response, he was started on some steroids to put the brakes on his immune system and bring it back in-check.</p>
<p>This sets the stage for the PET scan this past Friday (April 5).</p>
</section>
<section id="pet-scan-results" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pet-scan-results">PET scan results</h3>
<p><em>April 5<sup>th</sup> scan</em></p>
<section id="radiated-sites" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="radiated-sites">Radiated sites</h4>
<p>We have clear wins! No cancer was detectable in the three sites discovered back in Feb.&nbsp;The cancer in his T3 vertebrae, hip, and shin has been wiped out by the radiation therapy.</p>
</section>
<section id="central-mass" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="central-mass">Central mass</h4>
<p>The mass in the center of Sam’s chest, the one that brought us down here to start with, is stable. There is increased metabolic activity in the area but it remains the same size as previous – and potentially a little smaller. What is exciting about this is that the only thing keeping this site in-check would have been Sam’s immune system. The fact that this site is stable suggests that the immune system is able to battle whatever cancer is still in this area.</p>
</section>
<section id="challenges" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="challenges">Challenges</h4>
<p>A single new site has been located. The new site is located in Sam’s liver. For now we have to assume that this is new disease site (i.e.&nbsp;the same type of cancer in a new location). However, it is possible that is something else. The liver is a big organ, one that is hard to do surgery on, but this new site is superficial (near the surface) just below Sam’s lower rib on the right side. Given where this site is we are hoping that a biopsy can be completed this coming week.</p>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="living-life" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="living-life">Living Life</h2>
<section id="friends-and-family" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friends-and-family">Friends and Family</h3>
<p>Although not planned this way it was great to have my parents visit this weekend. Initial scheduling of the PET scan was not until next week. I am glad they were here to be with us – PET scans are often stressful. Nana Mary, Uncles Kevin and Cal were also able to come in the afternoon that we received the PET scan results.</p>
<p>Yesterday, Tina and I were able to visit with Brian, Beth, David, and Luke. A definitely highlight from that visit was seeing Sam have energy to talk with his friend!</p>
</section>
<section id="tragedy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tragedy">Tragedy</h3>
<p>Yesterday’s visits were filled with joy. But the day was also filled with sorrow. Our hearts break for R, and her whole family, as her daughter Dani passed away in the early morning. Dani had fought hard.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that three disease centers have been removed. Thankful that the original central mass is stable. We battle on to determine what the latest site is and how best to attack it.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam’s energy has increased!</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam’s pain levels have been stable and generally easy to manage.</p></li>
<li><p>The new immunotherapy drugs seems to have released Sam’s immune system to hit harder. As the immune system was starting to get out of control brakes have been able to slow the immune system back down. It is good to know that the chemical brakes work, at the same time we do not want to suppress the immune system too long as it is the main method of battling the cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>We mourn the loss of Dani – grieving in solidarity with her family.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>The cancer remains and has spread to new areas in Sam’s body. The sites are a mass in the center of his chest (the original), <del>and newer sites in his back (T3 vertebrae), his hip (right ilium), and left shin (tibia just below the knee).</del> Latest scan revealed a potential new site on Sam’s liver.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Graft versus host disease↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Graft versus host disease↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Bone marrow transplant↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>gastrointestinal↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>new-sites</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-07_battles-won.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Spring break(?)</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-02_spring-break.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Friends visit</li>
<li>Hockey games</li>
<li>Waiting for treatment</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div id="canucks" class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-03-28_us-canucks.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">We had a great time at the Canucks versus Stars game. Sam is loving his new jersey.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div id="friends" class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-03-26_sam-ben-chase.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">It was spring break and some of Sam’s friends were able to come and visit. Chase, Sam, and Ben have been friends since they were all four.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="recap" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recap">Recap</h2>
<section id="cancer-war" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cancer-war">Cancer war</h3>
<p>Generally, we are in a holding pattern. Radiation therapy wrapped up a week-and-a-half ago and seems to have gone well. No further immune therapy treatments have happened as we are waiting for Sam’s immune system to return to normal/safe levels. The initial treatment ramped-up Sam’s immune system, ideally to fight the cancer, but a side effect has been that the immune system is running on the edge of out-of-control causing graft versus host disease and agitating his liver. So we wait. At clinic yesterday, we changed meds to slow the immune system down/ bring it under control.</p>
<p>During this waiting period he have seen Sam generally been lethargic with some itchiness related to graft versus host disease. It is unclear what causes the lethargy in Sam, it could be effects of the radiation or immune therapy, it could be the disease, all of the above or something else … We do get glimpses of the real Sam full of energy and life. These times are encouraging though it is hard to watch him drop back to lethargy.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
April 4 addition
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>In the last 3-4 days Sam has had much better energy… I hope it continues.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Generally, we are in a very ambiguous situation – not knowing what is happening with the cancer or if the treatments are having the desired effects. Sam will have a PET scan tomorrow (Friday, April 5) which should give us a picture of where things are at.</p>
</section>
<section id="living-life-and-special-memories" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="living-life-and-special-memories">Living life and special memories</h3>
<p>The previous two weeks have been busy. In adddition to medical appointments we had good visits with friends, family, and we attended a couple hockey games.</p>
<section id="friends-and-family" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friends-and-family">Friends and family</h4>
<p>We have been encouraged by visits with friends. Most importantly – Sam’s friends. It was spring break for the schools and a few friends were able to visit during this time.</p>
<p>Chase came and stayed with us/Sam for a number of days. Ben, along with the rest of his family, was able to visit a couple different times. I am thankful that these boys were able see Sam when he was up and when he was down and simply accept him where he was at.</p>
<p>We also love the times we can connect with family, here at the RMH, at their homes, and at a hockey game.</p>
</section>
<section id="hockey" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hockey">Hockey</h4>
<p>Sam has really been enjoying hockey during this difficult period. He looks forward to watching games. Since I last wrote we were able to attend two.</p>
<p>First, we attended the WHL’s Vancouver Giants versus Kelowna Rockets. This was a special family time as we were gifted box seats to the game. Family including Cal, Tricia, Jane, and Nana Mary were able to meet the three of us plus Chase there.</p>
<p>This past Friday (Feb.&nbsp;29), The three of us were able to attend the Vancouver Canucks versus Dallas Stars game. We had a great time together! Sam enjoyed it so much and this will be a core memory for each of us. Although Vancouver lost it was a great hard-fought game and with a party atmosphere at the arena!</p>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>We will be at clinic 2-3 times this week. Sam will have a PET scan tomorrow (Friday, April 5).</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam’s energy and capacity for simple living have swung up and down over the last month. The majority of the time his energy is low but we do get glimpses of our real Sam full of energy and life.</p></li>
<li><p>The ambiguity of not knowing if treatments are working and delays in treatment are challenging – to the point of terrifying. We have managed the not-knowing well, but our reserves/defenses are drained/weakened.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam’s pain levels have been stable and generally easy to manage. The main challenges are related to the GVHD, specifically with rashes, which are not painful but are at times very itchy and hot.</p></li>
<li><p>The new immunotherapy drugs seems to have released Sam’s immune system to hit harder. Though we look forward to this pushing the cancer back, side effects of the new immune system attacking healthy tissues are also big concern (i.e.&nbsp;GVHD). Sam has had some adverse effects and we need to allow these to resolve before proceeding with new treatments.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>The cancer remains and has spread to new areas in Sam’s body. The sites are a mass in the center of his chest (the original), and newer sites in his back (T3 vertebrae), his hip (right ilium), and left shin (tibia just below the knee).</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>new-sites</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-02_spring-break.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Graft versus host</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2403/2024-03-19_gvhd.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Immune therapy treatment was initiated on Feb 29<sup>th</sup>. It took about 10 days before symptoms of Graft versus host disease started to present themselves. It is our hope that the Graft versus disease processes (i.e.&nbsp;destruction of cancer cells) is even stronger.</li>
<li>Targeted radiation therapy for the new disease sites, discovered on the Feb.&nbsp;14<sup>th</sup> PET scan, is ongoing and will be complete by the end of this week.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<section id="recap-of-the-last-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recap-of-the-last-week">Recap of the last week</h2>
<section id="cancer-war" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cancer-war">Cancer war</h3>
<p>It has been over a week since I last wrote and we have been continuing along two lines of attack against the cancer in Sam’s body.</p>
<dl>
<dt>Radiation Therapy</dt>
<dd>
<p>Each weekday we have made a trip down to the BC Cancer Centre, about a 10 minute drive away. Sam is/has undergone targeted radiation for the three new disease sites discovered last month. These visits are fairly quick with about 15 minutes needed per site and most of that time is simply setting up/positioning Sam to target the sites the same way each time. Last week treatment of the sites below his knee and on his hip were completed – as these were not near critical organs they received higher doses of radiation per treatment. Treatment of the disease on Sam’s back will be completed at the end of this week. Evaluation of how well the treatments worked will not be for a minimum of 2-3 weeks.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Immune therapy</dt>
<dd>
<p>Last Thursday, Sam was due to have another dose of <a href="http://www.bccancer.bc.ca/drug-database-site/Drug%20Index/Nivolumab_handout.pdf">Nivolumab</a> two weeks following his initial dose. However, this second dose was delayed as his bloodwork suggested that his liver was inflamed and as such it could be dangerous to give another dose. It was a good decision! Over this past weekend Sam has much stronger symptoms of Graft Versus Host Disease (GVHD) than we have seen the entire time since receiving his bone marrow transplant (BMT).</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>As a reminder, the intent of the BMT was to give Sam a new immune system that would recognize the cancer and destroy it. The weeks following the transplant Sam was on a medication to keep the new immune system in-check and reduce symptoms of GVHD. Now that we know that there is more cancer, steps are being taken to release the new immune system to be more aggressive. Essentially, using different drugs, we went from applying the brakes to the immune system to adding fuel to it. The goal: activate/jump-start the immune system to attack the cancer. Of course doing this has the potential to unleash the immune system to also attack Sam’s healthy tissues.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>This past weekend Sam had intense rashes and evidence that the GVHD was not only active on the outside of his body but also the inside (e.g.&nbsp;loss of taste, increased liver enzymes). The GVHD seemed to reach a peak on the weekend. Recent bloodwork seems to align with the symptoms we have been observing. If Sam’s immune system continues to settle back down we will likely continue with this line of treatment.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="general-living" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="general-living">General living</h3>
<p>Sam’s life is pretty simple: watching too much YouTube, and when he has more energy, he reads, plays video games (only rarely able to sit up to play on his PC), and occasionally reviews some studies. Lately, his activity has been limited to short walks, mostly around the RMH. He also enjoys visiting with people, though his capacity can often be low causing visits to be short (e.g.&nbsp;30 minutes). Despite the length of this journey and current challenges Sam still maintains a positive attitude with statements like: <em>“I love my life.”, “I am so happy”</em>, <em>“We have a great family”.</em></p>
<p>Our parental pride swelled earlier this week. A boy here at the RMH, I’ll call him B., is about five years old and has looked up to Sam. B. was having a hard week and mad at the world – Sam decided to brighten his day. Sam chose a lego set which I purchased when I was out. Sam was able to give it to him the next day and also spent some time helping him assemble it. B. was thrilled! So great that Sam took the opportunity to care for this young man!</p>
<p>We continue to enjoy visits with family. Tina’s family members, who live in the region, try to make a point of being here each week. We look forward to seeing them on their usual days.</p>
<p>We also love to see friends as they are able to come through. This past week it was great to see Jess and John with Kate and John (Jr.).</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam’s energy and capacity for simple living have swung up and down over the last two weeks. Currently, his energy levels are low – mostly likely related to the ongoing treatments.</p></li>
<li><p>This is a long journey and all of our energy levels are tapped (physically and emotionally). Part of the challenge is the ambiguity. We are now in a third period (we call it “era”) of treatment (i.e.&nbsp;1: chemotherapy, 2: BMT, 3:immune-therapy). The previous therapies had protocols to follow and expected end dates. The current therapy is day-by-day, becoming week-by-week… there is no clear timeline …</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam’s pain levels have been stable and generally easy to manage. The main challenges are related to the GVHD, specifically with rashes, which are not painful but are at times very itchy and hot.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has a cold. It has now been identified as common cold that he would have had as a young child. The upside is he has a new immune system to battle it. The downside, his new immune system is like that of a newborn – needing to create antibodies for all of the diseases that Sam has already seen through life.</p></li>
<li><p>New battle strategies against the cancer have been developed but carry some higher risks.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The new immunotherapy drugs seems to have released Sam’s immune system to hit harder. Though we look forward to this pushing the cancer back, side effects of the new immune system attacking healthy tissues are also big concern (i.e.&nbsp;GVHD).<br>
<br>
Sam has had some adverse effects and we need to allow these to resolve before proceeding with new treatments.</p></li>
<li><p>Targeted radiation therapy began last week and will complete this week. We are thankful this tool can be used to reduce the burden of disease on Sam. However, radiation also comes with risks.</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation We cannot thank you enough.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>The cancer remains and has spread to new areas in Sam’s body. The sites are a mass in the center of his chest (the original), and newer sites in his back (T3 vertebrae), his hip (right ilium), and left shin (tibia just below the knee).</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>new-sites</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2403/2024-03-19_gvhd.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Again we wait</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2403/2024-03-08_again-we-wait.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Immune therapy treatment was started with no adverse reactions.</li>
<li>Radiation planning was completed with treatments to start next week.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
March 11
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>A few quick notes as we head into this week</p>
<ul>
<li>Today Sam starts his radiation therapy. Radiation therapy will be Monday - Friday for this week and next.</li>
<li>A couple victories:
<ul>
<li>We have had good control of Sam’s pain over the last week.</li>
<li>Sam has had more energy over the weekend than we have seen since before the BMT.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>With the ongoing immune therapy Sam has had more minor Graft-Versus-Host-Disease symptoms (GVHD, itchy rashes). We are hopeful that this means there is active Graft-Versus-Disease.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<p>The past week has come and gone and in general it has been a good week for Sam (all things considered). The next wave of treatments and treatment planning has begun. Though we will need to wait several weeks before we know how well or if the treatments are working.</p>
<section id="this-past-weeks-medical-journey" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="this-past-weeks-medical-journey">This past week’s medical journey</h2>
<p>Just over a week ago, on Thursday, Sam was started on <a href="http://www.bccancer.bc.ca/drug-database-site/Drug%20Index/Nivolumab_handout.pdf">Nivolumab</a> with the intention of ramping up his immune system to battle the cancer. We had expected to spend 3-4 nights in the hospital to monitor for potential adverse reactions to the drug. He did not have any adverse reactions! Sam was thrilled when the medical team offered to discharge him to leave hospital after one night.</p>
<p>On Friday morning, we made the quick trip down to BC Cancer where we met with the radiation oncologist. Initial discussions had suggested that radiation would only be used on the disease site in Sam’s back (T3 vertebrae). However, following a quick discussion the team at BC Cancer agreed to use radiation on all three of the new sites. To plan for this treatment, the radiation therapy team made some molds of Sam - his back and the front of his upper body - and then took him for a CT scan (this is a planning CT). These molds and measurements will ensure that Sam is in the exact same position during treatment – ensuring that the upcoming treatment is very precise.</p>
<p>Compared with my previous post, Sam’s health and pain levels have been quite stable with no significant pain spikes.</p>
<!-- We were leaving from the hospital and there had been some confusion around how we would get to BC Cancer.  An ambulance had been planned but their team was obviously not going to get to us to make our appointment on time at VGH.  Instead we chose to take our personal van.  This allowed us to arrive on time.   Arriving on time allowed us the opportunity to discuss options further with Dr. Goddard.  In addition, the team had the time they needed to do proper planning -->
</section>
<section id="next-steps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next steps</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Nivolumab immune therapy</dt>
<dd>
<p>This therapy is provided by IV once every two weeks. This coming Thursday (March 14) Sam will receive a second dose. This next dose will be double that of the first.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Radiation therapy</dt>
<dd>
<p>Targeted radiation of the three new disease sites will begin this coming Monday. Sam will receive a dose of radiation to each site every day for two weeks (10 business days). Assuming all goes well this will simply mean a short drive to BC Cancer clinic for the treatment and then a return to RMH.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Results and effectiveness</dt>
<dd>
<p>We are not going to know how any of these treatments are working for some time. It is too soon to tell if the immune therapy is working. Following radiation, we will need to wait a couple weeks for that treatment to take effect. … So we wait.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>For now the best indicator of how things are going is with Sam. How he is feeling. Where is pain levels are. How his body reacts to the treatments.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="life-together" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="life-together">Life together</h2>
<p><em>So how are we doing?</em></p>
<p>Last week, I felt beyond exhausted, physically and emotionally, this has been a long journey. Sam reminded me that we have been here five months longer than expected. He is right. The initial plan if everything had gone as expected/hoped would have seen us go home this past October. Next, the BMT process, should have seen us go home last week. Now, when are we going to get home? Simply, we just do not know.</p>
<p>In the meantime, we are enjoying life together. It is a simple life that includes medical care, meals, and time together. When Sam has the energy we get out of the building. Lately, he has enjoyed a trip to a local bookstore. In our room, Tina and I are thrilled when Sam has the energy to connect with friends and play some online games (which he has been able to do a couple times this week). Programs here at the Ronald McDonald House have been helpful. Sam has taken to playing the drums – I don’t know where he gets his rhythm from but he is a natural. I have enjoyed playing and learning a few new things on guitar. Tina has made it to a couple painting classes. We have also been able to connect with a number of other families including playing some board games together.</p>
<p>We are encouraged by visitors, Grace and Darren from Prince George, Tina’s Uncle Dave and Aunt Ruth originally from England but now in Abbotsford, and Tina’s family: siblings, Nana Mary, and Sam’s cousins are all in the Lower Mainland and we see some of them weekly.</p>
<p>One highlight from this past week was that we have moved to a larger room. This will allow us to enjoy our space more including providing some space for some anticipated guests.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam has had a good week. Pain levels have been stable and generally easy to manage.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has a chest cold. The upside is he has a new immune system to battle it. The downside, well it is a cold that is taking energy from him – energy we want him to have to battle the cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>The cancer remains and has spread to new areas in Sam’s body.</p></li>
<li><p>New battle strategies have been developed but carry some higher risks.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The new immunotherapy drugs will release Sam’s immune system to hit harder. Though we look forward to this pushing the cancer back, side effects of the new immune system attacking healthy tissues are also big concern.<br>
<br>
We are thankful that Sam has not had any adverse reactions to this drug. The next dose will be double the first so concerns remain.</p></li>
<li><p>Targeted radiation therapy begins next week. We are thankful this tool can be used to reduce the burden of disease on Sam. However, radiation also comes with risks.</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>We cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>new-sites</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2403/2024-03-08_again-we-wait.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cancer war – new battle strategies</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2402/2024-02-28_next-steps.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>The cancer remains and has spread to three new areas in Sam’s body (now four centers of disease)</li>
<li>A combination of radiation and drug therapy will be used to combat the cancer</li>
<li>Today Sam will start a new drug treatment and radiation planning will begin tomorrow</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<section id="this-past-weeks-medical-journey" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="this-past-weeks-medical-journey">This past week’s medical journey</h2>
<p>It has been a whirlwind of a week filled with anxious waiting, clinic visits most days, pain management, prayers, and the love of family.</p>
<p>It was one week ago today that Sam had a biopsy of one of the new disease sites. That procedure went exactly as planned and the tissue was sent to the BC Cancer lab for analysis – though we would not hear about the results until after the weekend.</p>
<p>Friday we were in clinic for a regular blood levels check and a quick exam. At the time, I was asked if Sam’s symptoms had changed and all I could say was ‘No, he seems to be doing well’. However, that would change over the following days as new pains mounted. I think of these as pain-spikes as they would come on quickly and cause changes in his pain management regime (i.e.&nbsp;drug doses were increased). We are thankful that we have such access to medical advice – though Sam and Tina deserve direct credit for sorting out the latest pain-spike.</p>
<section id="the-finding-and-the-plan" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-finding-and-the-plan">The Finding and The Plan</h3>
<!-- Monday Tina and I met with Jacob, Julianna, and Nicole to review the options. -->
<p>During Tuesday’s visit Dr.&nbsp;Jacob let us all know about the results of the biopsy. The new disease sites are the same cancer (primarily characterized by its <code>INI1</code> protein deletion). This information was critical to know in order to determine what treatments would be available for Sam. To be honest, the medical toolkit is getting low in options, but at least we still do have options:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Further chemotherapy is <em>not</em> an option. This cancer has become resistant and that line of therapy would put Sam’s new immune system at risk.<br>
</p></li>
<li><p>Radiation can be applied but is not a long term solution. We will use it to reduce the burden-of-disease on Sam. In particular it will be used on his T3-vertebrae to prevent potential growth at that site from impinging on Sam’s nerves.</p></li>
<li><p>A drug therapy for Sam has been approved. <a href="http://www.bccancer.bc.ca/drug-database-site/Drug%20Index/Nivolumab_handout.pdf">Nivolumab</a> is used for immunotherapy, though special approval was needed to use it on a BMT recipient. In general terms, this drug will take-the-brakes off Sam’s immune system. Specifically, and as I understand it, this drug disables proteins on the cancer cells that allow them to remain invisible to the immune system. This is a very similar philosophy of treatment as the BMT – to enable the immune system, and in Sam’s case to support his new immune system, to identify and destroy the cancer.<br>
The challenge is, until recently we have done the opposite, keeping the immune system brakes on so that the new immune system will not harm Sam’s healthy tissues. The medical team will be watching him closely. The goal: release the immune system to attack while watching for signs that the immune system does not harm Sam – it will be a fine balance.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>There are risks but we are excited to move forward with this option/opportunity to destroy this disease. Sam is excited and these options and expected hospital times, depending on how he tolerates the treatment, could be less difficult than he had imagined.</p>
<p>Today Sam will start this new immunotherapy treatment. He will be in-hospital for several days to ensure there are no complications. Assuming there are none we will be back at the RMH early next week.</p>
<p>Tomorrow Sam will also make a trip to the BC Cancer Clinic at VGH to have a CT scan which will provide the radiation oncology team the data that they need to complete the planning of their treatments.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="faith-hope-and-love" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="faith-hope-and-love">Faith, Hope and Love</h2>
<p>I am so proud of my son. He is a young man full of courage and faith. He continues to face his own mortality choosing courage over fear. My favourite quotes come from him on a near daily basis: “I have an amazing life” or “I am so happy”. His challenges are beyond my wildest nightmares but he remains strong, and full of hope. He is surrounded by the love of his family. He knows you are out there supporting him and we regularly share notes of encouragements as a family.</p>
<p>This past week we have received incredible support, following the news of more cancer when we had thought there would be less. Tina’s family has been close by and have been able to visit. My parents travelled down and were able to be here, support us, and spend some great time with Sam over several days.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>The cancer remains and has spread to new areas in Sam’s body.</p></li>
<li><p>New battle strategies have been developed but carry some higher risks. The new immunotherapy drugs will release Sam’s immune system to hit harder. Though we look forward to this pushing the cancer back, side effects of the new immune system attacking healthy tissues are also big concern.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that we have access to such incredible tools to show where the disease is in Sam’s body.</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>new-sites</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2402/2024-02-28_next-steps.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PET Scan Results – Cancer War</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2402/2024-02-15_cancer-war.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Feb 22 early morning update
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li><p>This morning Sam will have a minor surgery to complete a biopsy of the newly cancerous site on his T3 vertebrae. Results of the biopsy are expected following this coming weekend.</p></li>
<li><p>This afternoon we will meet with the radiation oncologist to discuss treatment options using radiation. I expect this will cover at least two scenarios: First, an emergency scenario should the cancer starts in Sam’s back begin to impact nerve function. Second, a scenario that could be more therapeutic assuming the cancer is slow enough growing that it does not require emergency action. … the second scenario should be less dangerous.</p></li>
<li><p>Friday we will be back in clinic to debrief and complete standard health checks.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam remains courageous. He understands everything that is going on. He knows his life is at risk. Yet he remains courageous, hopeful, trusting, and faithful.</p></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2402/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/240215_vancouver-aquarium-family.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Despite challenging news we had a great family day. Here we are pictured with the sea otters of the Vancouver aquarium – they are definitely a favorite.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The afternoon of the 14<sup>th</sup> Tina and I met with Sam’s doctor to discuss the results Sam’s PET scan – completed earlier in the day. The results were not what we hoped for – the cancer remains and has spread. Though we were initially shocked, disappointed, and honestly scared, the three of us have rallied and are preparing to take on this next fight.</p>
<section id="feb-15-recap" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="feb-15-recap">Feb 15 – recap</h2>
<p>Yesterday morning started with a good friend sending us this beautiful prayer:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Gracious God, when we cry to you and feel as if you do not hear us,<br>
grant us a tangible reminder of your promise to never leave us alone.</p>
<p>When we feel ground to dust, unable to sing your praises or whisper a prayer,<br>
surround us with others who will sit with us, pray for us, and be the hands and feet and face of Christ to us.</p>
<p>When the night has past and we see the coming dawn,<br>
help us to bear the light of Christ to those who still sit in deep darkness<br>
&nbsp; until we all shout alleluia on Easter morning.</p>
<p>Amen.</p>
<p><em>from Jill Duffield’s “Lent in Plain Sight: A Devotion through Ten Objects” (<a href="https://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0664265464/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o00_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;psc=1">Amazon</a>)</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The previous night and into that morning I felt it. I felt <em>ground-to-dust</em>. And yet notes of support and care started to roll in. When you reach out and express your care, your solidarity, and your prayers, you are the <em>hands and feet and face of Christ to us</em>.</p>
<p>Please continue to reach out to us – we need you. Please ask your children to reach out to Sam so that he knows he is not alone. Let him know that he is missed and that they are praying/ caring for him despite the physical distance. Many thanks to those who have reached out already and especially to Sam’s friends for reaching out to him.</p>
<p>The initial feeling of having our world rocked have shifted. As a family we have spent time encouraging each other and praying together. We have rallied – we are ready to take on this next cancer battle.</p>
</section>
<section id="pet-scan-results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pet-scan-results">PET scan results</h2>
<p>Although busy with regular clinic check-ins, we have had to bide our time since Sam received his bone marrow transplant – 93 days ago. Imaging has had to wait as there was so much going on in Sam’s body it was not possible to get a new image of the state of the cancer. Our assumptions and our hopes were that the prior treatments would have set the cancer back and that the new immune system would then attack anything that remains. However, the PET scan revealed a more complex picture.</p>
<section id="original-cancerous-mass" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="original-cancerous-mass">Original cancerous mass</h3>
<p>Imagery of the original mass suggested that the radiation therapy destroyed much of the cancer and likely that there is an on-going war between Sam’s new immune system and the remaining disease. The imagery of this site looks like a solar eclipse – with no activity in the middle, where the radiation focused, but with high activity/avidity around the edges.</p>
</section>
<section id="new-sites" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-sites">New sites</h3>
<p>Perhaps more alarming is that cancer is now active in new areas of Sam’s body. There are three new locations, all of which appear to be within bones (something we have not seen before). Working bottom-up, new sites of cancer are located in Sam’s</p>
<ul>
<li>left shin (tibia) slightly below his knee</li>
<li>hip (right ilium)</li>
<li>back (T3 vertebrae, between his shoulder blades)</li>
</ul>
<p>None of these are currently causing any additional impacts (e.g.&nbsp;bones are still strong, and no nerve impacts). Sam does have some back pain which is likely related to the spot there. These new sites raise questions and there will be a flurry of activity as plans of attack are made.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="next-steps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next steps</h2>
<p>The first question that is being asked is <em>what kind of cancer is this?</em> It is likely that it is the same cancer in a new location but the teams needs to know definitively. The next questions to be answered are related to how to treat the cancer. The medical team is jumping into high gear to start answering these questions. Next up:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Completed</em>, Feb 16 morning: CT scan of the T3 vertebrae to assess risk and provide imaging that will assist with treatment planning.</li>
<li><em>Competed</em>, Feb 16: Discussion with with the Orthopedic surgery team to discuss/plan a biopsy of the cancer in Sam’s shin (the easiest of the new sites to access). This was completed by our medical team and it was determined that this biopsy would not be feasible.</li>
<li>Feb 22: An alternate option is scheduled to biopsy the new cancer in Sam’s back.</li>
<li><em>Completed</em>, Feb 16: Discussion with Radiation Oncologist to discuss new radiation based treatments. Our medical team has been in communication with them and the Radiation team is ready when and if needed.</li>
<li><em>Ongoing</em>: reduce medications that have kept Graft versus Host Disease (GVHD) in-check. Increasing GVHD may help in the battle to kill the cancer … though this will need to be monitored closely to ensure Sam’s good tissues are not damaged.</li>
</ul>
<p>It has not even been 48 hours since we received the PET scan results and I hope you can sense that things are moving quickly – action is being taken.</p>
<p>Although there is a lot going on we were also able to get out and enjoy life.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-great-day-together" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-great-day-together">A great day together</h2>
<p>Despite these challenging PET scan results yesterday was a great family day – starting the Family Day holiday weekend off a little early. Yes, we had a big clinic visit in the morning where many of our questions were answered. In the afternoon we had a wonderful time at the Vancouver Aquarium! Watching some very cute creatures and exploring the long history of life on the planet through the various exhibits. Afterwards, we shared dinner together in our room (taco night at the RMH) and took in the Vancouver vs.&nbsp;Detroit hockey game.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>The cancer remains and has spread to new areas in Sam’s body. There are many questions that need to be answered and new battle strategies that need to be developed. The medical team has shifted into high gear once again.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that we have access to such incredible tools to show where the disease is in Sam’s body.</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>post-BMT</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2402/2024-02-15_cancer-war.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Happy Valentine’s Day – PET Scan</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2402/2024-02-14_PET-scan.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><em>9:30am</em></p>
<p>This morning I am writing from the BC Cancer clinic where Sam will have a PET scan (the previous scan was done prior to the radiation and BMT). Today’s scan should show the current state of cancer in his body. Ideally the cancer is gone but I will also take reduced and not anywhere new. I am not sure how long it would take the new immune system to clean up the last of the disease … of course we are looking forward to having the results but there are waves of anxiety/ fear regarding potential alternative outcomes.</p>
<p>We expect to have initial results back later today when we meet with Sam’s medical team back at BC Children’s hospital.</p>
<p>Thank you for all of your thoughts, care, and prayers.</p>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam, having been bed-ridden for much of the year, must rebuild his strength and stamina/ energy levels. This is been a slow process and it is likely we had not recognized how low down he was.</p></li>
<li><p>We have a big, and exciting transition, ahead of us: the return to home, family, and friends. A return to work and school – though these responsibilities will likely need plans and modifications. There are many practical steps and details to be sorted out. One step at a time!</p></li>
<li><p>We are no longer having medical discussions about upcoming treatments. Discussions are now about weaning medications, removing the central line, completing baseline tests for comparison with the pre-BMT testing, and preparations to return home!</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease. A PET scan will be done in late February to evaluate how the cancer has been impacted by all the treatments. The expectation is that any remaining cancer, following the chemo and radiation therapies, will be removed by the newly transplanted immune system.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>post-BMT</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2402/2024-02-14_PET-scan.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cautiously Optimistic</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2401/2024-01-29_returning.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Feb.&nbsp;9, 2024
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Just a quick update as we continue on this journey.</p>
<p>This treatment recovery phase seems long. I shouldn’t be surprised by this, all journeys seems long when you are nearing the end. It is always that last couple hours of a long drive that seem the longest.</p>
<p>In this situation, Sam has had some incredible things done to him. The pace of activities and medical interventions has slowed drastically, and Sam’s health is continuing to move in the right direction. His strength and stamina are returning/rebuilding. Sam still struggles with some pain but it has shifted from deep bone pains related to the chemical treatments to muscle pains as he rebuilds his core strength. Everything is moving in the right direction and returning home is getting closer!</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>It has been a good week. Sam has had a distinct return of his appetite and with it he is growing in strength. The discipline of choosing hope, discussed in my last post, has been getting easier given that we are not faced with so many unknowns and anxieties are being replaced with relief.</p>
<p>On the medical side, Sam’s medical team is happy to see him regaining capacity. Clinic appointments are becoming less frequent (we are transitioning from 2-3 times per week to just once), and the repeat of the baseline medical testing has been ongoing. Sam should get is central-line removed within the next two weeks.</p>
<p>Now, our thoughts are turning towards home and what it will mean to return there. Our current expectation is to return near the end of February. Returning will not be as simple as jumping back into life like-it-was. Sam’s immune system, though getting stronger, will still be compromised – the team here suggests that it will take a year before his immune system is back to full-strength. His stamina is building but we will need to guard his capacity. What does this mean practically? I am not sure, but here are a couple guesses: visits will need to be individual or in small groups and we will still need to avoid crowds – at least with Sam. Sam’s diminished strength may mean that visits are short and that he simply powers-out partway through. The return to normal will be in small steps … but we are getting there!</p>
<p>It is amazing to think of returning home. Returning to friends and family – we have missed you! It is also amazing to start counting down days! For long time we counted up – not knowing when the end would be. Now the end is in sight! Sam has made it through all of his treatments and it feels like we are on an exit-ramp – we can start preparing for home!</p>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We have a big, and exciting transition, ahead of us: the return to home, family, and friends. A return to work and school – though these responsibilities will likely need plans and modifications. There are many practical steps and details to be sorted out. One step at a time!</p></li>
<li><p>We are no longer having medical discussions about upcoming treatments. Discussions are now about weaning medications, removing the central line, completing baseline tests for comparison with the pre-BMT testing, and preparations to return home!</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease. A PET scan will be done in late February to evaluate how the cancer has been impacted by all the treatments. The expectation is that any remaining cancer, following the chemo and radiation therapies, will be removed by the newly transplanted immune system.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>post-BMT</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2401/2024-01-29_returning.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>To the Ward and Back Again</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2401/2024-01-21_ward-and-back-again.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="looking-back" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-back">Looking back</h2>
<p>Last post I wrote about the viral illness that Sam had, and the removal of some steroid supports that he had post BMT. He was making slow progress recovering from it all.</p>
<p>On Jan.&nbsp;11 we went in for a clinic appointment with the Endrocine team. However, they were not fully satisfied with how Sam responded to the treatments they initiated … unexplained low blood pressures tend to send off alarm bells for physicians. So we went up to the oncology clinic to let our regular medical team evaluate Sam and consider his situation from their perspective. The team there decided to admit Sam to the ward. I confirmed later that this was due to a number of small flags that went off for them – if any one flag was presented they would have sent us back out. However, whatever was going on with Sam, though ambiguous, added up to be significant enough to be admitted.</p>
<p>Over the next few days we saw very little improvement but then he started to come around. There were a lot of question-marks about what was going on with Sam and when we asked “<em>What is going on with Sam?”</em> the answer was”<em>We don’t know</em>.” Various tests were run and general treatments were provided.</p>
<p>The nurses called it being in for a ‘<em>tune-up</em>’ and they reassured us that it was very normal for someone, following a BMT, to come back to the ward for whatever was ailing them. The idea of a <em>tune-up</em> is not a bad analogy though it felt more like a major tune-up – like Sam was only running on 1 or 2 cylinders.</p>
<p>Sam started feeling better following about five days of treatment (fluids, antibiotics, steroids), and by day 8, this past Thursday, he demonstrated he was strong enough to leave the ward. We are now back at the RMH.</p>
<p>Ughh. All of those days of illness, including the 10 days prior to being admitted were hard. It is the not knowing: What is happening? What is the problem? Will we find a solution? Is this the cancer? To complicate things, especially for Tina, was the fact that she still had bronchitis, because of this she was not able to spend much time on the ward with Sam and I. I am thankful that Nana Mary was able to be with her during this last time on ward.</p>
</section>
<section id="looking-forward" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-forward">Looking forward</h2>
<p>In the weeks ahead we will need to keep a close eye on Sam’s energy levels. We have been given some flexibility in managing steroidal supports (e.g.&nbsp;in response to illness or injury). So if we see his energy fading we can pump him up a little. The steroids are intended to mimic natural bodily levels, as given the previous BMT related treatments his body is not yet generating natural responses – this is all expected (by the doctors). It is also expected that Sam’s own hormone balancing system will restart after a month or two. Again we wait and hope.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Hope in the waiting
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>I can’t help but remember that when we were learning Spanish, in our days working in Guatemala, that verb <em>esperar</em> means to wait, and it also mean to hope (the noun for hope is <em>la esperanza</em>). So when we say we wait – I also mean we hope. Of course, hope itself is a choice. In many ways it is a choice to expect the good and to actively reject living in anxiety. This is more than a psychological trick. Our hope and trust have true foundations. I have hope because of our incredible medical team, and ultimately we have hope in God.</p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="medical-plans" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="medical-plans">Medical plans</h3>
<p>This week will be a return to regular clinic visits. We will also start a repeat of all of the baseline testing that was done prior to the BMT. This will involve visits to all of the specialties in the hospital, and various imaging tests to evaluate if/how this whole BMT journey has impacted Sam.</p>
<p>We will also continue weaning the various drugs that Sam has been on – primarily reducing morphine levels.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>A concern for Tina and I is that it is not always easy to choose hope. The reality is that choosing hope is a discipline. Given everything that we as parents have gone through, including all of the alternate outcomes that we have seen, it is very easy to slip into anxious thinking.</p></li>
<li><p>We are no longer having medical discussions about upcoming treatments. Discussions are now about weaning medications, removing the central line, completing baseline tests for comparison with the pre-BMT testing, and preparations to return home!</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern if the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease. A PET scan will be done in February to evaluate how the cancer has been impacted by all the treatments. The expectation is that any remaining cancer, following the chemo and radiation therapies, will be removed by the newly transplanted immune system.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>post-BMT</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2401/2024-01-21_ward-and-back-again.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A chemical crutch</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2401/2024-01-11_chemical-crutch.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>The days since my last post have been rough. Whatever virus we all picked up is still lingering. Sam and I are mostly past it, and Tina is improving. Unfortunately, this cold also caused some confusion as the team cared for Sam – it was more difficult to discern what was happening with him while he was battling this illness.</p>
<section id="looking-back" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-back">Looking back</h2>
<section id="sams-medical-progress" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sams-medical-progress">Sam’s medical progress</h3>
<dl>
<dt>The challenges</dt>
<dd>
<p>Following New Year’s it was like someone flipped a switch in Sam … in that the power was turned off. Where prior Jan.&nbsp;1<sup>st</sup> Sam had increasing stamina and activity levels, this past week-and-a-half he had no energy and spent most days in bed. The virus we all had complicated the picture. We did have a couple clinic appointments but making any changes were difficult as it was hard to know what was happening in Sam’s body apart from the illness.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Last Wednesday there was a decision to stop one of the steroids used during BMT. Initially, this did not seem to affect Sam … but at the time all he was doing was sleeping (&gt;90% of the time). By the end of the weekend, Sam was mostly done with the cold but he was still sleeping… and not very responsive. It turns out the steroid was a chemical crutch and we had pulled in out from under him.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>The next clinic appointment, earlier this week, a substitute steroid was introduced. Sam is now more conscious and is beginning to get moving again.</p>
</dd>
<dt>The positive</dt>
<dd>
<p>Despite the confusion and challenges above Sam has made some good progress having successfully dropped a number of medications from his list.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Symptoms of GVHD have been minimal with minor rashes. The medical team remains vigilant watching out for this.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="visits" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visits">Visits</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>It was great to see my parents this past week. They had a couple windows of opportunity to chat with Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>Tina and I were able to get out for a nice meal with Kevin and Shannon.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We will continue with the usual clinic visits to monitor Sam’s progress.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam will be seen Endrocrinology Team. This team specializes in steroids, hormones and all of the glands in our bodies that produce them. It is not uncommon for someone who has been on steroids and then stops (e.g.&nbsp;Sam for his BMT) to have issues producing their own hormones. I expect that this team will examine Sam to determine what hormones he may need in the short-term, consider strategies for getting his own system jump-started, and worst case to determine if there has been any damage to his glands.</p></li>
<li><p>There is talk of removing Sam’s central line!</p></li>
<li><p>All of the pre-BMT baseline tests will be completed</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>It has been a hard week watching our son sleep most day and not understanding why. His brief periods of wakefulness re-assured us that he was still in-there. This was stressful and exhausting for Tina and I. We now have some direction and started on some supports for him. The biggest underlying concern is the return of his body’s ability to produce and regulate natural hormone levels.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has gotten past the his cold. His new immune system beat it back and we did not have to go into hospital. <del>Our first challenge of 2024 seems to have been exposure to a flu. Sam has been feeling rough, with higher pain levels, and lots of fatigue. We initially attributed this as a response to increased activity levels … but then Tina and I started battling colds.</del></p></li>
<li><p>We have had an great holiday season celebrating Christmas, Tina’s birthday, and New Years with family in the area.</p></li>
<li><p>We are no longer having medical discussions about upcoming treatments. Discussions are now about weaning medications, removing the central line, and preparations to return home!</p></li>
<li><p>New blood cells in Sam’s body are all from the donor! Sam’s bone marrow is pumping-out/generating new blood! The engraftment process is working! We have seen Sam’s numbers come up and now stabilize!</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern if the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease. A PET scan will be done in February to evaluate how the cancer has been impacted by all the treatments. The expectation is that any remaining cancer, following the chemo and radiation therapies, will be removed by the newly transplanted immune system.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>post-BMT</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2401/2024-01-11_chemical-crutch.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Happy New Year!!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2401/2024-01-01_happy-new-year.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Happy New Year! We have so much to be thankful for this year! Although, 2023 was incredibly challenging it ended with joy as we celebrate Sam’s new life. Looking up and looking forward we are filled with hope and joy for the year ahead.</p>
<p>Joy has been a theme for Sam. Many mornings he wakes up and the first thing he says is “<em>I’m so happy!</em>” On New Year’s day it was “<em>I’m so happy. I am immensely happy!</em>” In the last couple weeks he also commonly adds “<em>I have an amazing life!</em>”</p>
<p>Taking a van trip our to see the family and bring in the New Year, Tina brought up Psalm 23, a passage that many also sent on to us. Sam reflected on how he feels like God has lay down beside the green pastures.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<h2 id="psalm-23" class="anchored">Psalm 23</h2>
<p>The Lord is my shepherd, I lack nothing.<br>
&nbsp;He makes me lie down in green pastures,<br>
he leads me beside quiet waters.<br>
&nbsp;True to your word,<br>
you refresh my soul<br>
&nbsp;and send me in the right direction..</p>
<p>Even when the way<br>
&nbsp;goes through Death Valley,<br>
I will fear no evil,<br>
&nbsp;for you are with me;<br>
your rod and your staff,<br>
&nbsp;they comfort me.</p>
<p>You prepare a table before me<br>
&nbsp;in the presence of my enemies.<br>
You anoint my head with oil;<br>
&nbsp;my cup overflows.<br>
Surely your goodness and love will follow me<br>
&nbsp;all the days of my life,<br>
and I will dwell in the house of the <span class="smallcaps">Lord</span> forever.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.bible.com/bible/111/PSA.23.NIV?parallel=97"><em>Psalm 23</em></a> <em>(blend of NIV and The Message versions)</em></p>
</blockquote>
<section id="looking-back" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-back">Looking back</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Medical items</dt>
<dd>
<p>Sam continues to have regular visits at the clinic. Various blood tests to ensure the various medications that Sam is on are at appropriate levels. Most of the discussion with the medical team is in preparation to leave! This includes weaning Sam off of the medications. To date, everything with the BMT is going well and Sam is ahead of the anticipated schedule. Various members of the medical team have said they are amazed at how well Sam is doing.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Christmas</dt>
<dd>
<p>Christmas was… extravagant! We spent the morning sharing gifts and the evening meal and games wth family.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Life beyond the hospital</dt>
<dd>
<p>It is exciting that we ar having more an more life beyond the bounds of the hospital campus! Including:</p>
</dd>
</dl>
<ul>
<li>Visits with family Langley and in White Rock</li>
<li>A great Townsend-side buffet meal to celebrate <em>Tina’s birthday</em>. All but one of Sam’s cousins from that side of the family were able to make it.<br>
</li>
<li>A new years party at with Nana, Uncle Kevin and Auntie Shannon, and all of their children plus partners. Including the newlyweds Kurt and Marielle.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Medical appointments will continue as Sam remains under a watchful eye from the team.</p></li>
<li><p>Medicines will gradually be removed</p></li>
<li><p>There is talk of removing Sam’s central line (in a couple weeks)!</p></li>
<li><p>All of the pre-BMT baseline tests will be completed</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Our first challenge of 2024 seems to have been exposure to a flu. Sam has been feeling rough, with higher pain levels, and lots of fatigue. We initially attributed this as a response to increased activity levels … but then Tina and I started battling colds. The good thing is that Sam is now has an immune system to fight for him.</p></li>
<li><p>We have had an great holiday season celebrating Christmas, Tina’s birthday, and New Years with family in the area.</p></li>
<li><p>We are no longer having medical discussions about upcoming treatments. Discussions are now about weaning medications, removing the central line, and preparations to return home!</p></li>
<li><p>Sam continues to regain strength.</p></li>
<li><p>New blood cells in Sam’s body are all from the donor! Sam’s bone marrow is pumping-out/generating new blood! The engraftment process is working! We have seen Sam’s numbers come up and now stabilize!</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease. A PET scan will be done in February to evaluate how the cancer has been impacted by all the treatments. The expectation is that any remaining cancer, following the chemo and radiation therapies, will be removed by the newly transplanted immune system.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>post-BMT</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2401/2024-01-01_happy-new-year.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Merry Christmas</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-24_merry-christmas.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Merry Christmas everyone! We have so much to be thankful for!</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I came so they can have real and eternal life, more and better life than they ever dreamed of.<br>
— Jesus (<a href="https://www.bible.com/bible/97/JHN.10.MSG">John 10:10</a>, The Message translation)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sam is doing great! Since the last post he has continued to gain strength. We have a long road ahead of us but it seems we are on the path towards home and the return to friends, family, school, and work there.</p>
<section id="the-past-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-past-days">The past days</h2>
<div class="img-float-right">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-12_walk-to-clinic.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Sam and I walking from the RMH to the hospital for a clinic visit. This was the first morning Sam did not need to ride in the chair (Dec.&nbsp;22<sup>nd</sup>)!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam continues to have regular visits at the clinic. Various blood tests are done each time. One specific, the team looks at Tacrolimus levels, an immunosuppressant used to ensure that this BMT is successful and that any graft-versus-host-disease (GVHD) is minimized. Note: some GVHD is needed so that the new immune system continues to attack any remaining cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>Exciting news! The genetic testing of Sam’s immune system confirmed that the donor cells have fully replaced Sam’s native immune system. Ideally, in a BMT transplant the native immune system is removed to make way for the donor cells. There is always a chance that some native cells remain and that a battle for dominance can occur. For Sam, the BMT has gone as planned and all new blood is being generated by the donor cells.</p></li>
<li><p>All of the blood tests have shown Sam’s counts have come up and are stabilizing.</p></li>
<li><p>I have debated including this next thought … especially during Christmas. It is a challenging reality (skip it if you need to).</p>
<div class="tabset-margin-container"></div><div class="panel-tabset">
<ul class="nav nav-tabs"><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link active" id="tabset-1-1-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-1" aria-controls="tabset-1-1" aria-selected="true">Skip</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-2-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-2" aria-controls="tabset-1-2" aria-selected="false">Read</a></li></ul>
<div class="tab-content">
<div id="tabset-1-1" class="tab-pane active" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-1-tab">
<p><em>or click ‘Read’ above</em></p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-2" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-2-tab">
<p>Christmas at the Ronald McDonald House is amazing but strange – layered in hope and pain. There is so much generosity poured into this place you cannot help but feel cared for.<br>
<br>
During these last months, as we have weathered this cancer storm, we have also walked beside a number of other families in similar circumstances. Some are looking forward to completing treatment, while others are in the thick of the storm. Another family, is having an incredibly hard Christmas. They have reached the end of possible treatments and recently moved to hospice to spend what days remain with their child. Our hearts and prayers continue to go out to them.<br>
<br>
Here at the Ronald McDonald House joys and pains are especially visible. For me, this raises an inescapable question for life at home. If your Christmas is full of joy, and I truly hope it is, are there pains that may be close but remain unseen? Is there a way to demonstrate love and generosity into those situations?</p>
</div>
</div>
</div></li>
<li><p>Some good normal life has been happening.</p>
<ul>
<li>Sam has had energy to enjoy reading. He finished <em>The Hobbit</em> earlier this week and immediately got into another book.</li>
<li>Nana was able to visit and help us prepare for Christmas.</li>
<li>We were able to get off the hospital campus and visit the Frickers – with more family visits planned over the holidays. So great to play family games… this year games also includes some VR which actually has been an amazing physical rehabilitation tool.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>What a special Christmas this will be! We have seen Sam through a long and challenging journey and it seems we are on the other side!<br>
<br>
<em>What do I want for Christmas?</em> I already have it! My son is alive! And not just alive, he his beginning to thrive!</p></li>
<li><p>In the weeks ahead there will continue to be regular visits to the clinic as levels are check at medications are adjusted.</p></li>
<li><p>Numerous scans and tests will start in the new year to evaluate if there have been any internal impacts in Sam’s body. This will also include scans to determine if any disease remains.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam has completed his critical post-transplant period. He has now been discharged from the hospital! We will remain at the RMH for the next two months in order to monitor for potential GVHD complications.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam continues to regain strength. He is now able to walk from the RMH to the hospital.</p></li>
<li><p>New blood cells in Sam’s body are all from the donor! Sam’s bone marrow is pumping-out/generating new blood! The engraftment process is working! We have seen Sam’s numbers come up and now stabilize!</p></li>
<li><p>Sam will still be considered immune compromised for the months ahead and mostly susceptible to viral infection. It remains to be flu season and covid is still out there. We must continue to be vigilant to protect Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all of the messages of encouragement and solidarity that we have received from all of you.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
In case you missed it
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kATGCsIqALw?si=QwtKjKK690T1ljFy" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<div style="font-size:90%; margin-left: 15pt; margin-right: 15pt">
<p>On Dec.&nbsp;12<sup>th</sup> Santa paid a visit to the BC Children’s Hospital. Sam was able to welcome him onto the oncology ward. Tina and Nana Mary (1:03) were also able to meet him. Tina did an amazing job of sharing what this Christmas means to us (starting at 1:13). The original news article from the CBC is <a href="https://www.cbc.ca/player/play/2291723843615">linked here</a>.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>post-BMT</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-24_merry-christmas.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Christmas has come early! Freedom!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-13_christmas-came-early.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kATGCsIqALw?si=QwtKjKK690T1ljFy" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<div style="font-size:90%; margin-left: 15pt; margin-right: 15pt">
<p>On Dec.&nbsp;12<sup>th</sup> Santa paid a visit to the BC Children’s Hospital. Sam was able to welcome him onto the oncology ward. Tina and Nana Mary (1:03) were also able to meet him. Tina did an amazing job of sharing what this Christmas means to us (starting at 1:13). The original news article from the CBC is <a href="www.cbc.ca/i/phoenix/player/syndicate/?mediaId=2291723843615">linked here</a>.</p>
</div>
<p>Wow! It has been an amazing 48 hours!</p>
<p>Tuesday, two days ago, Santa visited a number of hospitals in the province and our family got to be a part of this celebration. Sam was able to be one of the first to welcome him to the ward and the staff loved his enthusiasm! I am still stunned by the opportunity Tina had to speak with the CBC, with how well she was able to capture what this Christmas means to us, and how it also let the medical team know how important they have been to us.</p>
<p>Yesterday, was a major Christmas present for our family: Sam was discharged from the ward and we are all back at the Ronald McDonald House!</p>
<p>Before leaving there was a short ceremony where all of the nurses gathered, a speech was given by one of the doctors to honor Sam for all of the work that he as undertaken – noting especially how he taken such responsibility in understanding the treatments and communicating so well with the team. After, Sam walked out the doors in stark contrast to his arrival by air ambulance eight months ago! He was done and ready to move on – though a part of him will miss the amazing people that have cared for him these last weeks (BMT) and months (Chemotherapy).</p>
<p>We will be based at the RMH for the next two months. In this time Sam will be at clinic 2-3 times per week to monitor for potential graft versus host disease (GVHD) which will likely mean lots of minor adjustments to his medications. He has a long list of medications but over time this will be reduced.</p>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam has completed his critical post-transplant period. He has now been discharged from the hospital! We will remain at the RMH for the next two months in order to monitor for potential GVHD complications.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam is returning to strength! Having received his discharge paper, he walked out of the hospital back towards the RMH. He made it most of the way back before powering out and transferring to the chair. With the way he has been eating his return to strength will continue to be rapid!</p></li>
<li><p>Sam’s bones are generating new blood! The engraftment process is working! We have seen Sam’s numbers come up and now stabilize!</p></li>
<li><p>Sam will still be considered immune compromised for the months ahead and mostly susceptible to viral infection. It remains to be flu season and covid is still out there. We must continue to be vigilant to protect Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all of the messages of encouragement and solidarity that we have received from all of you.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <category>hospital</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-13_christmas-came-early.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>From Step-down to Stepping-out</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-11_stepdown-to-steppingout.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It has now been 27 days since Sam received his BMT. The initial couple weeks had big challenges and Sam needed a lot of medical supports. His IV-tower was huge with a dozen lines running at once. In the last ten days that has all changed!</p>
<div class="center">
<p><em>I finally feel like myself again!</em> – Sam</p>
</div>
<p>Over the last ten days the team has been continuous reducing the number of medical supports. With one exception all his medications have been converted to pills. Sam has his appetite back and has been eating really well. The tube feed has been there as a back up for a few hours a day but I expect the we will try to stopping it’s use today. All this means Sam is IV-tower free for most of waking hours.</p>
<p>We are also seeing him return to energy. A couple weeks ago it was difficult to cross the room. Now, we are taking laps around the ward. One thing that we will miss is the Sam’s personal cheerleader-squad as the nurses literally cheer when he goes by the nurses station! On Saturday Sam had an afternoon pass – we left the hospital and wheeled over to the Ronald McDonald House. Sam loved the cool fresh air!</p>
<p>For Tina and I, it feels like a massive weight is being lifted. We knew that this time has been hard… but I don’t think we fully understood the pressure we were under. We are now beginning to be able to contemplate returning to home – though that is still a couple months away.</p>
<section id="next-steps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next steps</h2>
<p>Sam has done incredibly well and this engraftment process, so far, has gone smoothly and quickly. It is likely that Sam will be discharged from the hospital later this week – well ahead of schedule (previously we were hoping to get out a few days before Christmas).</p>
<p>Once out life should be simpler. We will be at the Ronald McDonald House (RMH) and visit the clinic 2-3 times per week to check on Sam’s progress and monitor for any Graft Versus Host Disease related issues. Practically speaking this means regular blood-work. Sometime in the weeks and months ahead Sam will receive a PET scan or two to confirm that the cancer has been defeated.</p>
<p>Once out the next major milestone will be <em>Day 100</em> (past the BMT). This will be the day we should have the green-light to go home!</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam is returning to strength! We expect to be out of the hospital and living back at the RMH later this week.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam’s bones are generating new blood! The engraftment process is working! We have seen Sam’s numbers come up and now stabilize!</p></li>
<li><p>What an incredible birthday present. Sam’s ANC blood metric went from non-detectable to 0.3. A strong indicator that the transplant is taking hold!</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that what Sam has experienced so far is within the normal for a BMT and that he has not had any complications. Although it is all in the ‘normal’, it is not all easy:</p>
<ul>
<li>Nausea is under control! We have seen the reduction of meds and will be testing removal of some anti-nausea meds. <del>Impacts from the pre-treatment, chemotherapy and radiation, remain strong. These cause deep bone and muscle pain, along with nausea. <em>These are starting to resolve!</em></del></li>
<li>Pain management is under control! Sam is on a regular dose of morphine which he will start reducing over the weeks ahead.</li>
<li>Nutrition mainly by mouth and I expect the NG tube will be removed in the next few days.</li>
<li>Energy levels are returning! – it is great to see Sam roam the halls!</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam will still be considered immune compromised for the months ahead and mostly susceptible to viral infection. It remains to be flu season and covid is still out there. We must continue to be vigilant to protect Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all of the messages of encouragement and solidarity that we have received from all of you.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <category>hospital</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-11_stepdown-to-steppingout.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Engraftment!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-01_engraftment.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Time here in the hospital feels so warped. It is hard to believe that we have been on the ward for three weeks now, having arrived a few days before the transplant. It is now <em>day 17</em>.</p>
<p>Although not without challenges, Sam has been making excellent process. It was beautiful to see the first numbers indicating success of the BMT come in on his birthday, and the numbers have been climbing everyday! On day fourteen Sams’s blood counts officially confirmed that engraftment is occurring! His bones are hard at work pushing out new blood and rebuilding a new immune system! Genetic testing to confirm that Sam’s new blood is from the donor will be done day ±30 (Dec.&nbsp;14).</p>
<section id="step-down" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="step-down">Step down</h2>
<p>Sam has now entered the <em>step-down</em> phase. It is in this period that all of the extra supports will be reduced, removed, or converted to oral; and we will be prepared to leave the hospital! Already:</p>
<ul>
<li>Anti-nausea medications have been reduced from continuous infusion to lower frequency does. We are going slow with these, as Sam is starts to get his appetite back we do not want to wreck that with a wave of nausea.</li>
<li>Nutrition is now dominantly provided via NG tube, and less so by IV/TPN which will likely be stopped today. As Sam gets his appetite, and his tastebuds back, all external supplements will eventually be removed.</li>
<li>Pain medications have been reduced and generally Sam is not needing to self administer as often.</li>
<li>Immune and transplant therapy drugs are ongoing and will eventually be converted to oral.</li>
</ul>
<p>As each day passes it is great to see less medications and fewer pumps needed. Sam is also more alert and with the help of the physio team here we expect to see him return to an energy and strength.</p>
</section>
<section id="current-challenges" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="current-challenges">Current challenges</h2>
<p>Sam has deep bone pain. This is not a new experience for him. With every round of chemotherapy his blood counts would drop and his bones, more specifically the marrow, would work hard to generate and replace the blood cells killed by the treatment. The BMT process was this again, but more intense. This time the marrow was entirely cleared out. The transplant cells have taken up home in the marrow and are cranking out new blood – but not without pain.</p>
<p>It is very exciting that Sam’s body is now generating new blood. The challenge is that this blood is still foreign to him. The medial team keeps a close eye on Sam looking for signs of Graft Versus Host Disease (GVHD) – where the new transplanted immune system could start attacking Sam. It is amazing, that cancer and immune therapy research has progressed so far that the team has a whole set of tools to address GVHD.</p>
<p>To date, and relatively speaking, Sam has not had much GVHD issues – though we will be watching for any complications in the weeks and months ahead. Sam has had painful, hot, and blotchy rashes show up – usually in the evening that may be attributed to GVHD. Although we throw everything we can at these flair-ups he often has to simply suffer through for an hour or two.</p>
<p>Sam continues to be courageous! He conveys gratefulness to everyone on the team and to Tina and I as we assist him through the days.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam’s bones are generating new blood! Engraftment is ongoing and everyday we see his numbers come up! We will be on the watch for Graft Versus Host Disease (GVHD) – which may be causing periodic rashes.</p></li>
<li><p>What an incredible birthday present. Sam’s ANC blood metric went from non-detectable to 0.3. A strong indicator that the transplant is taking hold!</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that what Sam has experienced so far is within the normal for a BMT and that he has not had any complications. Although it is all in the ‘normal’, it is not all easy:</p>
<ul>
<li>Impacts from the pre-treatment, chemotherapy and radiation, remain strong. These cause deep bone and muscle pain, along with nausea. <em>These are starting to resolve!</em></li>
<li>Pain management is constantly under revision. <em>Update: We seem to have the right mix. Pain and nausea are currently under control</em></li>
<li>Nutrition is received by ~~TPN (IV),~ NG tube, and minority by mouth.</li>
<li>Energy levels are low <em>but recovering</em>– it is great to see Sam have energy to sit up and play when he can.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>It had been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity. It is hard to see him have this strength pulled away from him.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>It is flu season and covid is still out there. If any of us get sick it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he is in a phase where he has no immune system for the next few weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all of the messages of encouragement and solidarity that we have received from all of you.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <category>hospital</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-01_engraftment.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Best Birthday Present!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-25_happiest-b-day.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="yesterday-sams-birthday" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="yesterday-sams-birthday">Yesterday, Sam’s birthday</h2>
<section id="by-the-numbers" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="by-the-numbers">By the numbers</h3>
<p>While attempting to secretly decorate Sam’s room in the early morning hours Sam’s nurse provided me with the results of that night’s bloodwork – the numbers were exciting. Sam was hoping that on his birthday there would be some indication that the BMT was taking hold. Two days ago the bloodwork hinted that something was happening. For Sam’s birthday the bloodwork numbers were more than we hoped. Our hope was that his ANC, a metric of immune system strength, would hit 0.1. All week it had been &lt; 0.1 (essentially non-detectable) and for Sam’s birthday it jumped to 0.3!</p>
<p>This is exciting news! The numbers indicate that engraftment is happening, that the BMT is taking hold, though it will not be considered definitive until the ANC exceeds 0.5 for a three consecutive days and some additional tests are run.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-great-birthday" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-great-birthday">A great birthday</h3>
<p>Sam had a great day. The ANC of 0.3 had everyone excited, the three of us, the nurses, and the doctors, and this set a great tone for the day. Sam’s body is working overtime generating new blood so he rested a lot, pain and nausea have been under control for the last 48 hours.</p>
<p>Sam was able to have video-calls with his grandparents. Thoughout the afternoon, as a family, we loved reviewing messages, and video messages with birthday greetings. The nurses on shift all piled into the anteroom to sing Sam happy birthday and deliver a cake – he was even able to eat some of it! Of course there were presents which Sam took his time opening, reading the cards and enjoying every word written and gift sent. Thank you!</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="next-steps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next steps</h2>
<p>We will get more clarity on the next steps in the days ahead. Here is what I currently understand:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>We will be watching for the day the BMT is officially considered engrafted (3 consecutive days of ANC <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cgeq%200.5">).</p></li>
<li><p>Sam will begin a step-down process as his body heals from the intense chemotherapy and radiation therapy that was used to condition his body to receive the transplant. Currently, he receiving significant external supports: nutrition is being delivered via NG tube and TPN (IV delivery), and he is on a continuous schedule of numerous drugs. In the step down process these supports will slowly be removed, and drugs will be converted to oral delivery.</p></li>
<li><p>Over the next couple months Sam will be watched closely for signs of Graft versus Host Disease (GVHD)– essentially that the new immune system does not harm Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>We should be out of hospital and back the Ronald McDonald House before Christmas.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>What an incredible birthday present. Sam’s ANC blood metric went from non-detectable to 0.3. A strong indicator that the transplant is taking hold!</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that Sam has felt the love of his community around him – especially on his birthday.</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that what Sam has experienced so far is within the normal for a BMT and that he has not had any complications. Although it is all in the ‘normal’, it is not all easy:</p>
<ul>
<li>Impacts from the pre-treatment, chemotherapy and radiation, remain strong. These cause deep bone and muscle pain, along with nausea.</li>
<li>Pain management is constantly under revision. <em>Update: We seem to have the right mix. Pain and nausea are currently under control</em></li>
<li>Nutrition is received by TPN (IV), NG tube, and minority by mouth.</li>
<li>Energy levels are low – it is great to see Sam have energy to sit up and play when he can.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>There will be ongoing concern as many known and unknown pitfalls that may present themselves during the BMT process. Potential illness, establishment/engraftment of the donated bone-marrow/ stem cells. Numerous other potential complications.</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Update: Sam did have an infection earlier this week. Within about 45 minutes of detection he was on antibiotics and was cleared out quickly. The team here says that this happens to everyone going through a BMT.</em></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all of the messages of encouragement and solidarity that we have received from all of you.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that it seems Sam’s pain management is now mostly under control, including options to address any spikes in pain.</p></li>
<li><p>It had been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity. It is hard to see him have this strength pulled away from him.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>It is flu season and covid is still out there. If any of us get sick it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he is in a phase where he has no immune system for the next few weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that had to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Done! Thank you! <del>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</del></li>
<li>Continuing: We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>Done! <del>The medical team has a huge coordination task ahead of them. From our meetings with them it seems all of the pieces are coming together, but with so many moving parts it is easy for things go wrong.</del></li>
<li>Done! Although it was rough at points the BMT conditioning was successful! <del>These last days leading up to the BMT are very busy with lots of drugs running all day. Concerns during this time are that everything is able to be delivered as planned and that Sam does not have any overly negative reactions to any of this.</del></li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <category>hospital</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-25_happiest-b-day.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
