<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Sam Chisholm</title>
<link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>News updating friends and family on our journey</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.361</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2023 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Round 3 out-patient life</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-14_outpatient-life.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>There have been too many new-normals over the last number of years. Covid and post-covid transitions being the most obvious in our collective consciousness. It seems that we are finding another new-normal here as patterns of life are established. At the 3-4 week scale we have the pattern of hospital in-patient period of ~5 days (drug-delivery) followed by out-patient life.</p>
<p>Out patient life is where life begins to feel most normal, with meals, and activities. I am still amazed that activities are possible and that we have seen such a good return of Sam’s health. This week we had some unexpected encounters that brought some home-normality to life.</p>
<section id="the-last-few-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-last-few-days">The last few days</h2>
<dl>
<dt>July 10 - 13</dt>
<dd>
<p>Tuesday was the first clinic day following this round of chemo’s drug delivery. We also had a chance to review the results of the latest PET scan in more detail with Dr.&nbsp;C. Great to see the imagery of how the cancer is being reduced, and how Sam’s heart and lungs are now clear.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>We bumped into a classmate of Sam’s on our way out of the hospital. Tyler was here to have a check-up. Sam had a great visit him. Lisa and Tina had a great connection.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Shoshanna is here with her family. Great to catch up with them and plays some family games.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Ronald McDonald House provided a trip to Science World – we spent a couple hours there yesterday.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Another regular life item: our van is in the shop … usual stuff: brakes and fluid leak repairs.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>Clinic appointments to monitor Sam’s ongoing health and blood levels.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are thankful for the successful completion of round three’s drug delivery phase! So far the side effects have been minimal with intermittent nausea and general fatigue.</p></li>
<li><p>Great to have some visits with our Prince George people.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for BC Children’s and the medical team here. Amazing that Sam is returning to health!</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-14_outpatient-life.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Round 3 hospital time and release</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-10_round3-hospital-time.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>We are now all back at the RMH. These last few days Sam was in hospital to receive the chemical delivery of ths current round of chemotherapy. All-in-all this round seems to be going well. Sam has such a great understanding of the process and because of that he asked to get his drugs pushed a little earlier each day. He had a goal in mind and with the assistance of the medical team he was able to achieve it. It was a simple goal – <em>Get out on Saturday</em>. And that is exactly what we did… it was a little late but it was worth it. We left the hospital a little before midnight and had a good sleep – without interruptions.</p>
<section id="the-last-few-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-last-few-days">The last few days</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Tuesday, July 4</dt>
<dd>
<p>Clinic day and start of round 3 of chemo.</p>
</dd>
<dt>July 5 - 8</dt>
<dd>
<p>Days in hospital for chemo drug delivery. Sam received a variety of different drugs. Generally, he had anywhere from two to four lines of medication including additional hydration running the whole time we were in hospital. The additional hydration was to ensure that his body not only received the chemicals but was able to process them without damaging his liver or kidneys. The inconvenience of hydration is that Sam was up every ~2.5 hours (day and night; I was up with him).</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Nana was here and had great visits. Tina and her mom spent the much of their time at the RMH with visits to Sam. On the Friday Cal, Tricia, and Jane visited as well. Nana returned home on Saturday.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Sunday, July 9</dt>
<dd>
<p>Our first full day out. So far the only side effect that Sam has felt is fatigue but even this fatigue is better then his best days from a couple months ago. Kevin was able to come by and we hosted him with a BBQ here.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>Clinic appointments to monitor Sam’s ongoing health and blood levels. With each treatment his immune system is expected to crash. If the pattern from the previous rounds hold Sam should have a 3-4 more days of grace before he is left without immune defenses. He will have around a week where we will have to be careful and keep him away from any potential disease.</p>
<p>In a week-and-a-half my parents will be back down and they have arranged to bring Buddy with them.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that family for such a supportive family.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the successful completion of round three’s drug delivery phase!</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam has not had significant side effects from this round … though concern that they may yet arise.</p></li>
<li><p>We miss home: our friends and family there, our house, the neighborhood…<br>
I miss my work, my team, the forest, and the work itself.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that it remains effective to fully remove the cancer.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-10_round3-hospital-time.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Treatment progress and the start of round 3</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-05_round3-and-results.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Sam’s clinic appointment went as expected yesterday: bloodwork confirmed that his body was ready to start round 3. We were also able to discuss results of last week’s PET scan and lumbar puncture.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Last Thursday Sam had a lumbar puncture. A small amount of spinal fluid was removed and an equal amount of chemo-drugs was inserted. Analysis of the spinal fluid confirmed that there is no cancer in the central nervous system!</p></li>
<li><p>PET scan results – the treatment is working! Sam has two main cancerous masses one in his chest, and a smaller one in his neck. Results from the PET scan indicate that:</p>
<ul>
<li>Both masses are smaller then in the previous scan</li>
<li>The activity level of the cancer in the body is reduced</li>
<li>No new locations of cancer have been detected (i.e.&nbsp;it has not moved to other locations in the body)</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p><em>Note: Sam is receiving additional monitoring (i.e.&nbsp;more scans) then normal because his case is … not a normal cancer case. Since so little is known about this form of cancer additional monitoring is taking place. I expect this is for two purposes. First to confirm that the treatment is working. Second, to document that the treatment is working – adding to the pool of knowledge on cancer.</em></p>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>The next number of days will be here at the hospital while Sam receives his treatment. I will be with him through the nights. Tina and her mom will join us through the day. Tina and I may even get away for some additional time together while Nana visits.</p>
<p>This round of chemo includes some nastier drugs, though Sam is in a much stronger place then the last time he experienced them. Potential side effects are likely to include pain, nausea, GI sores, and further hair loss.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are thankful for positive results – that the treatment is working!</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that it remains effective to fully remove the cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>Specific more immediate concerns are the side effects from this current round of chemotherapy.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <category>treatment</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-05_round3-and-results.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Happy anniversary and Canada Day</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-03_anniversay-canada-day.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/canada-day-delta.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Canada Day in Delta</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="highlights-from-the-past-few-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights-from-the-past-few-days">Highlights from the past few days</h2>
<p>This past weekend was spent like many of yours – celebrating Canada Day.</p>
<p>Sam’s day-to-day health is much improved. To look at him, other than the thin short hair, your might no know there was anything wrong. Since my last post:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Tina and I celebrated our 27<sup>th</sup> anniversary! We celebrated as a family out for a great meal and then ice cream.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam had his lumbar puncture and PET scan – results are pending.</p></li>
<li><p>Nana (Tina’s mom) arrived – she will be here for the week.</p></li>
<li><p>Celebrated Canada Day in North Delta where Kevin and Kelsey F. were the MCs for the activities there.</p></li>
<li><p>Townsend reunion with Tina, her mom, her siblings and most of their families – four generations.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>Tomorrow Sam returns to the hospital. We will check in at the day-clinic where:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>We will hear the results of this past weeks scans.</p></li>
<li><p>Check blood levels.</p></li>
<li><p>Start round 3 (i.e.&nbsp;begin delivery of chemotherapy drugs) – assuming blood levels are where they need to be.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Assuming all goes as planned Sam will be admitted tomorrow evening for a total of five days of chemo-drug delivery.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for my wife! We have had an amazing journey together though this latest chapter is the hardest we have faced. I am grateful to be able journey this storm with her.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that we are able to take part in normal activities! Happy Canada Day! Great to be with family.</p></li>
<li><p>Round 3 starts tomorrow. It has a different drug delivery regime then the last round and impacts will likely it will feel stronger.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that the treatment is working. There is also concern that it is effective to remove the cancer fully.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-03_anniversay-canada-day.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Round 2 complete and some family fun</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-28_round-2-complete.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Chemo round 2 officially ended on the weekend and it has felt like a great success. Aside from 4 nights during the initial chemical delivery days and several clinic days, Sam spent the remainder of the time out of hospital. The majority of the days have been within the hospital campus, and over the last week we were able to spread our wings a little further as Sam’s immune system strengthened.</p>
<p>Though the lived experience of this round felt better, tests this week will determine what the unseen impacts were on the cancer. Sam will have a lumbar puncture and a PET scan over the next few days.</p>
<p>Next week Sam will return for some hospital days to begin round 3 of chemotherapy which, given it’s chemical makeup, may be harder on him then this last round.</p>
<section id="highlights-from-the-past-few-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights-from-the-past-few-days">Highlights from the past few days</h2>
<p>This past weekend we have had good time as a family and with the extended family.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>We were able to celebrate little Jayme’s birthday. Though Auntie Tricia and Uncle Cal also took the chance to spoil our boy – providing him a huge steak, which he enjoyed immensely.</p></li>
<li><p>Uncle Kevin started his new position in Delta and so we have been able to connect with them more. We spent an afternoon with Kevin and Kaden at Granville Island. Over the last few years Sam, Tina and I have made it there a number of times and have our favourite spots for snacks.</p></li>
<li><p>What do you do if your immune system is low and you want to go to the movies. The drive-in is a great option. The three of us had a great night taking in a double header … though we paid for it the following day.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam has completed his second round of chemo as an out-patient.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that we have family in the area.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that we are getting to know some families here.</p></li>
<li><p>Round 3 starts next week. It has a different drug delivery regime then the last round and impacts will likely it will feel stronger.K</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that the treatment is working. There is also concern that it is effective to remove the cancer fully.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-28_round-2-complete.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Out-patient life</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-24_out-patient.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/bike_kerrisdale.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Tina and I got out on bikes to the neighborhood of Kerrisdale.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Over a month ago one of our nurses told us that Sam would become an out-patient. At the time it seemed impossible. We were in the middle of round one, Sam was weak and sick, but it seems we have arrived at out-patient status. This morning marks day 19 of this round of chemotherapy – Sam has made it through the chemo-valley without the need of hospital time (his numbers are starting to recover). What a difference!</p>
<p>It is really weird as it seems we stumbled our way into this out-patient status. With the exception of four nights, when Sam received the chemo-chemicals, he has been out of the hospital for this round. Sam has had clinic appointments twice a week, and at each one we half-expected that he may need to be admitted. We know now that, even with dropping blood levels, if Sam keeps feeling good there was no need to return to the hospital. Living on the hospital campus makes out-patient life feasible as in the event Sam got sick (e.g.&nbsp;due to his chemo-compromised immune) we would simply visit the ER here and follow the oncology patient protocols.</p>
<section id="looking-back" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-back">Looking back</h2>
<p>The week as been a quiet one. Sam was in the valley where his blood levels were lowest. Yet his time there was dramatically better then last time. His energy levels were low and given that his immune system was at its weakest point he hid out for much of the week. A few highlights from this past week:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Playing cards with Minecraft with Sam</p></li>
<li><p>Slurpee-run therapy walks – the local corner store is about six blocks away. Sam is getting closer to walking all of the way there.</p></li>
<li><p>A couple outings for Tina and I. Including a bike ride to Kerrisdale.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="looking-ahead" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-ahead">Looking ahead</h2>
<p>The week ahead will include:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Continued recovery from this last round of chemo</p></li>
<li><p>Tests to monitor the state of the cancer in Sam’s body – to confirm it is still being reduced and that we can continue without having to adjust the treatment regime.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that it Sam has made it through the second round of chemo as an out-patient.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the Ronald McDonald House, all the generosity supporting it, and all the volunteers serving here. This place makes living through this journey … almost feel like normal life.</p></li>
<li><p>Currently, one of our greatest challenges is that we have been away for over two months and it hard to stay connected with home. We miss you. We are thankful that Sam has been able to connect with friends on-line. We are thankful for visits and notes. However, despite these interactions, the nature of this cancer journey can feel isolating – for all of us.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that we are getting to know some families here.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that Sam has made it through round two!</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that the treatment is working. There is also concern that it is effective to remove the cancer fully.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-24_out-patient.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A second weekend at the RMH</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-19_rmh-weekend-2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I am not writing as often as, simply, there is not as much to say. Our days are normal<em>ish</em> – a good thing! Currently, we are not trying to understand what is happening, or what is next. It is good to have the stress level come down and have some time for mental recovery.</p>
<section id="the-last-couple-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-last-couple-days">The last couple days</h2>
<p>This weekend has been at the Ronald McDonald House (RMH) – our home away from home. On Saturday my parents got into town. It has been great to share meals and visit with them. A few quick highlights:</p>
<ul>
<li>Card games. Including Sam’s ongoing winning streak in crib. … I will attempt to humble him, if I can, in the week ahead.</li>
<li>A walk and ice cream. We continue to be encouraged with how Sam’s strength is returning.<br>
</li>
<li>A coffee date with Tina while Sam visited with his grandparents.</li>
<li>Father’s Day BBQ hosted by the RMH.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>Tomorrow, June 20, we will have a fourth clinic appointment to evaluate how Sam’s blood-levels are doing and if his immune system is holding.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for normal<em>ish</em> days.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for time with my parents.</p></li>
<li><p>Again, we are thankful that Sam is not feeling the effects of this chemotherapy round. The pending valley-of-gross appears to be getting smaller and smaller. Of course there is some concern as Sam’s blood levels continue to drop. Some days in hospital are still expected.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that the treatment is working. There is also concern that it is effective to remove the cancer fully.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-19_rmh-weekend-2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Another extension to our days of freedom!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-17_rmh-extra-days-2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/richmond-night-market.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Freedom!! We spent the evening exploring the Richmond Night Market.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Wow!</p>
<p>It is currently sixty days since we started this journey, and day twelve of the current/ 2<sup>nd</sup> round of chemotherapy. Today is also marks 7 days of not being in the hospital!</p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Cheng has told us a number of times that we need to remain flexible on this journey as each round of chemo is different. There are different sets of chemotherapy drugs in each round. With each round Sam is also different. Starting this round Sam has had a amazing return of his health as compared with the first. A few points to compare:</p>
<ul>
<li>Sam’s lungs and heart are clear of fluids</li>
<li>The cancerous mass has been reduced in size and density</li>
<li>Our boy has his appetite back</li>
<li>Sam is gaining his physical strength back</li>
</ul>
<p>I thank God. I thank all of you for your care. I thank the medical team for all their great work.</p>
<section id="the-last-couple-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-last-couple-days">The last couple days</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Thursday, June 15</dt>
<dd>
<p>A relaxed day at the RMH. The simple and normal things of life: chores, meals, playing cards, strumming a guitar. Sam and I started playing crib again.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>In the afternoon, Cal T. paid us a visit. We had a great talks and Sam had a new challenger for crib. Yes, Sam beat both Cal and I.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Friday, June 16</dt>
<dd>
<p>We had an appointment at the oncology-day-clinic. Checked Sam’s blood levels, cleaning and dressing changes for Sam’s central-line. The lab is fast – blood levels were back levels are dropping, but again they are still above any levels of concern.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>I clarified with the doctor, wondering if it was possible to skip the valley caused by chemotherapy. As I understand it:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The valley will come. Sam’s immune system will collapse to zero (as indicated by the ANC<sup>1</sup> metric). … Yes, I have created a graph for this.</li>
<li>Be flexible, each round of chemo is different. Some rounds the valley is short. Some the valley is long. Be flexible, as it is not possible to know.</li>
</ol>
<p>In the afternoon, we had a great visits Chris and Jane, and David C. We all took Dave to the airport, and based on Hunter’s recommendation from over a month ago we shared a meal at the Fairmont – delicious!</p>
<p>The evening was a shock. Tina and I were not ready for this. Sam, energized by a great meal was not done. As many of you know, Tina often starts to come alive as the sun gets low. So we were off to the [Richmond Night Market](https://richmondnightmarket.com). We spent over two hours exploring the booths. Sam loved it! Tina loved it!</p>
<p>We are all stunned by how well Sam is doing!</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for regular days! I encourage you to do the same. Take joy in all the little moments. They may seem simple but they are times of grace.</p></li>
<li><p>Again! Celebrating and addition to our additional days of freedom. This days were a welcome surprise. I hope this can be part of the pattern going forward – we will take each day as it comes.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for visits with friends and family.</p></li>
<li><p>Again, we are thankful that Sam is not feeling the effects of this chemotherapy round … yet. The pending valley-of-gross seems to be getting smaller and smaller. Of course there is some concern as Sam’s blood levels continue to drop. Some days in hospital are expected.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that the treatment is working. There is also concern that it is effective to remove the cancer fully.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>ANC: absolute neutrophil count, a measure indicative of the body’s immune system. Measured via a blood test. <a href="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/def/absolute-neutrophil-count">see</a>↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>outings</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-17_rmh-extra-days-2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Extended days of freedom!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-15_rmh-extra-days.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>This morning I am writing from our room at the RMH – because we are all still here!</p>
<p>Two days ago Sam went in for his clinic appointment. We had expected that he would be admitted, as his blood counts would be falling. But we received great news! Although his counts had dropped they had not dropped as to cause any concern. The result is we got a bonus 72 hours away from hospital admission. Sam has a clinic appointment tomorrow am – likley he will need to be admitted then.</p>
<section id="the-last-couple-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-last-couple-days">The last couple days</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Tuesday, June 13</dt>
<dd>
<p>Following the clinic appointment in the morning we had relaxed afternoon at the Ronald McDonald House. I got out for a bike ride. Margaret and Daniel joined us for the evening. It warmed my heart to see the cousins chatting together!</p>
</dd>
<dt>Wednesday, June 14</dt>
<dd>
<p>I drove Margaret and Daniel to the airport using our van (my sister drove the van down and then flew home). In the afternoon, the three of had a good time playing family games. Of note: <em>Connect 4</em> the card game is far better than the original. For Tina, we also made a gluten-free-goods run to the <a href="https://www.glutenfreeepicurean.ca">Gluten-Free Epicurean</a>.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for a weekend away and additional days this week! This days were a welcome surprise. I hope this can be part of the pattern going forward – we will take each day as it comes.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for visits with family.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for a video from the Westwood youth group. Great to see familiar faces. Thank you for sending your care and friendship.</p></li>
<li><p>Again, we are thankful that Sam is not feeling the effects of this chemotherapy round … yet.<br>
Concern, Sam’s blood levels are dropping and the days ahead could feel gross as the effects of the chemotherapy take hold.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that the treatment is working. There is also concern that it is effective to remove the cancer fully!</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-15_rmh-extra-days.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A weekend at RMH</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-13_rmh-weekend.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-06-11_ma-daniel-sam-colin.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A relaxed weekend visiting with family at the RMH</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It has been a few days since I have provided an update. The pace of everything is changing – for the good. No longer is everyday a new experience, or sitting in expectation of some procedure. The pace has slowed and life has become somewhat more predictable.</p>
<p>Sam is currently on day 8 of his second round of chemotherapy. The medical team really wants to maximize his time away from the hospital so, given that he was doing well having received all the medications on Saturday morning, they discharged him for the weekend! The plan is that he goes back into the hospital before his blood counts drop too low and his immune system becomes compromised.</p>
<p>This morning we will go to the hospital to get his blood levels tested and either be admitted for be sent back out for 48 hours.</p>
<section id="reflections-on" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on">Reflections on …</h2>
<p>We have had a great weekend. Here is a quick recap:</p>
<dl>
<dt>Friday, June 9</dt>
<dd>
<p>Was in hospital – receiving doses of chemotherapy. In the evening the most of the Fricker family here. Sam had a good visit with these cousins whom he had not seen since before all of this started.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Saturday, June 10</dt>
<dd>
<p>The morning was at the hospital for a final dose of chemo drugs for this round of therapy. In the afternoon we were out to the Ronald McDonald House.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Sunday, June 11</dt>
<dd>
<p>The beauty of not being in the hospital is that there are no interruptions! Sam and Tina both slept in until mid-morning. At about the same time my sister Margaret and cousin Daniel arrived! We had a great brunch and visit with them!</p>
</dd>
<dt>Monday, June 12</dt>
<dd>
<p>Similar to Sunday, we had another slow day. Margaret and Daniel spent some good time with us simply hanging out at the RMH. The five of us also managed a short outing to grab ice at the Dairy Queen on Main St.&nbsp;Sam is also getting to know another young man here. J. was diagnosed with cancer a couple weeks after Sam – I expect we will be connecting with him and his family over the weeks ahead.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for a weekend away! This was a bit of a surprise. I hope this can be part of the pattern going forward but we will take each day as it comes.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for visits with family.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for a video from the Westwood youth group. Great to see familiar faces. Thank you for sending your care and friendship.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern, that the next week or so could be feel gross as the effects of the chemotherapy take hold.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that the treatment is working. There is also concern that it is effective to remove the cancer fully!</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-13_rmh-weekend.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What does a round of chemo look like? An overview</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-08_chemo-overview.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>We are back at BC Children’s Hospital, once again receiving the amazing care that this place provides. Sam has just started his second round of chemotherapy. Today I thought I would provide a brief sketch of what Sam’s chemotherapy looks like – there is no one method for chemotherapy, rather plans are tailored to each circumstance. As such, though there may be some similarities with other chemotherapies this is Sam’s – and really it is the only one that I can speak to.</p>
<p>Considering chemotherapy in days and weeks:</p>
<ul>
<li>A round of chemotherapy is 21 days long.</li>
<li>The first five days are intensly chemical. Numerous does of various chemotherapy specific drugs, along with drugs to help Sam not feel sick from receiving the prior are delivered. These days Sam is attached to the IV pole and has anywhere from 2-5 lines delivering chemical treatment to him via his central line (Hickman CVC<sup>1</sup>).</li>
<li>The following ~10 days are the valley, the chemicals take effect and life gets gross. Chemotherapy is intense. It hammers actively growing cells, in hammers your immune system. The benefit is that it hammers the caner the hardest. Over this time:
<ul>
<li>Blood counts will drop and there may be need for transfusions.</li>
<li>Sam’s immune system will be entirely wiped out leaving him with no defences and secondary infections are a risk.</li>
<li>In addition, he will likely experience some level of mucositis where sores can develop in the mouth and possibly anywhere in the GI<sup>2</sup> system.</li>
<li>Drugs during this phase are generally for pain and nausea control with additional drugs, as needed, for secondary infection management.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The final days of the treatment are when we expect to see Sam’s body recover from treatment with a return to normal blood counts and life starts to feel better again.</li>
</ul>
<p>Following a round of chemotherapy Sam, well all of us, will get a few days of a break … before starting this pattern all over again.</p>
<p>This is written on day 4 of 21. In the 2<sup>nd</sup> round of treatment – a day or two before we start into the valley.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-june-7-and-8" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-june-7-and-8">Reflections on June 7 and 8</h2>
<p>The 7<sup>th</sup> was our first full day back at the hospital and day 2 of this round chemotherapy. There were many visits by the various members of the medical team – making it feel like a day of interruptions, but this is the work of getting well.</p>
<p>Nurses trained me how to change Sam’s dressing – a clear bandage protecting his central line. Even now, when home seems so far away, they are preparing us to be there. Maybe it is weird but I enjoyed this – taking on a new challenge and also caring for my boy.</p>
<p>V., Sam’s physiotherapist, is thrilled with how improved he is, and the strength that he is regaining. She has provided additional tools to keep him moving – a stationary bike, and the next day some resistance bands and weights.</p>
<p>The next morning was more routine filled with various drug deliveries and fluids testing. In the afternoon: Tina and I got away, stocked her up on food that she can eat, after we returned, we had a good visit with Cal and Tricia.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for the team here at BC Childrens’s Hospital. For their expertise, the hard work that they do, and also the personal care they invest.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for the care of friends and family. Many thanks to for encouraging notes received through this site, email, and FaceBook.<br>
<em>Note: if you ever feel that you do not want to bother us – please ignore that feeling and send us a note. Hearing from you is always encouraging.</em></p></li>
<li><p>Concern, that Sam seems to be losing weight, despite eating well. We may have to supplement his diet sooner than we had hoped (i.e.&nbsp;a new NG tube)</p></li>
<li><p>Concern as we head into the valley and life for Sam will feel gross (mucositis/GI sores, nausea…).</p></li>
<li><p>Concern that the cancer will be fully removed and that it will continue to respond to the treatment.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Central venous catheter↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>gastrointestinal↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>info</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-08_chemo-overview.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Results and the return for round 2</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-07_results-and-round2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Once again I am writing from Sam’s bedside here at BC Children’s Hospital – our second arrival. Compared with the first, this is so much easier. Sam’s health has dramatically improved and it is much easier to be in hospital when you plan to go there. We are also returning to people that know and care for Sam.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-june-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-june-7">Reflections on June 7</h2>
<p>Yesterday was a business day. Sam’s return to the hospital. We checked into the Oncology day-clinic, Sam had a few tests, we met with Dr.&nbsp;Cheng to discuss the progress made and the plans moving forward. In the afternoon Sam would receive his first chemical doses of chemo round 2<sup>1</sup>.</p>
<section id="results" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results">Results</h3>
<p>We had an opportunity to look at before and after imagery from Sam’s PET scans. I am glad I had not seen the first scans until now. The difference is dramatic.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The size and density to the cancerous mass is greatly reduced</li>
<li>The impacts on Sam’s other organs has been removed – or is minimal. The first scans showed high impacts on Sam’s lungs heart – mostly causing high levels of fluid build up and pressure. Now his lungs are now clear of fluid and only a residual amount of fluid remains around the heart – this is expected to resolve over time. 3. Currently Sam has two main masses of cancer. The main one in his chest and a smaller one in his neck. They are greatly reduced since our arrival seven weeks ago. I need to get a copy of the results again so I can quantify the amount of reduction.</li>
</ol>
<p>This is exciting – the cancer is responding to treatment.</p>
</section>
<section id="plans" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="plans">Plans</h3>
<p>It is exciting to see such progress. In moments of weakness it is also terrifying. The remains a lot of work to be done these cancerous masses are measurable in centimetres – there are billions of cancerous cells to be removed<sup>2</sup>.</p>
<p>Despite the challenges, for the first time we actually have a plan! Until now, none of us have known what the plan would be. Sam’s cancer is extremely rare, and how it would respond to treatment was not known. Now that we know the treatment is working. We will move forward with a treatment regime. The plan is to complete six rounds of chemotherapy with on-going evaluation to adapt the plan as needed.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are thankful for positive results and that Sam is doing so well.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for a plan, though we need to gear ourselves for a marathon. We have heard it said around here numerous times that this cancer journey is both a roller-coaster and a marathon.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern that the cancer will be fully removed and that it will continue to respond to the treatment.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>This is the actual round 2. What I referred to previously as round to was actually round 1, and the very first week of chemo … well they don’t actually count that one.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p><em>cell densities in human tissues are on the order of 1 billion to 3 billion cells/ml</em>.<br>
McClelland, Randall E., Robert Dennis, Lola M. Reid, Jan P. Stegemann, Bernard Palsson, and Jeffrey M. Macdonald. “Chapter 6 - Tissue Engineering.” In Introduction to Biomedical Engineering (Third Edition), edited by John D. Enderle and Joseph D. Bronzino, 273–357. Boston: Academic Press, 2012. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-374979-6.00006-X.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-07_results-and-round2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Amazing family weekend</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-06_amazing-weekend-rmh.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/weekend-vacation.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">A family vacation weekend! Left our dinner out at Whitespot. Auntie Tina with nephew Chris and neice Jane (upper left). Right – time simply being outside.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Our break away from the hospital comes to an end today, yet we can bask in the joy that this weekend provided! We have had an incredible weekend as a family and with some of our extended family. It was amazing to see how well Sam is doing. I don’t know if the cancer i gone – but I do know that it has been dramatically reduced.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-this-past-weekend" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-this-past-weekend">Reflections on this past weekend</h2>
<section id="june-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="june-3">June 3</h3>
<p>Our first full day off. A day of rest and simply exploring the RMH (Ronald McDonald House). We also took care of all the medical items ourselves – medications and needles and NG tube feeding. We had it all down all the steps were going well – until we hit a glitch. We do not have a reason for it, and we have seen it happen a number of times while in the hospital: The NG tube clogged and this time we could not get it back. After working at it for about an hour we decided togive up for the night and pushed as much Coca-cola into it as we could (a hack that sometimes works to dissolve clogs).</p>
<p>Saturday afternoon<sup>1</sup>, we had a wonderful visit with Bob and Wendy H. Sam shocked me as he was also up for the visit. Wendy and Tina had a good catch-up, while Bob, Sam, and played on a digital game table. Sam and Bob broke the game after Sam discovered a glitch and they both exploited it.</p>
</section>
<section id="june-4" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="june-4">June 4</h3>
<p>Sunday morning the NG remained clogged. We were fairly quick to recognize that this was a blessing! Sam had a new job – to eat and ensure that he met or exceeded the calories that he would have received via the NG tube. He did not disappoint –our boy has his appetite back. About mid-afternoon, Tina pulled the tube.</p>
<p>Also in the afternoon we had some great visits. First with Uncle Kevin and then joined by cousins Chris and Jane (Cal’s children). We all chatted and hung out outside. That evening the cousins and the three of us got Sam off hospital property for the first time since this whole journey began! We got out for a meal – at the Kerrisdale White Spot where Sam had a milkshake and a double-double.</p>
</section>
<section id="june-5" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="june-5">June 5</h3>
<p>Another great day as a family starting with a full breakfast provided by volunteers at the RMH. Times talking together, imagining, drawing – including time outside (outside can be precious following weeks of being in hospital). In the afternoon we grabbed an ride-share down the Marine Gateway Cineplex and took in the new Guardians o the Galaxy movie – loved it!</p>
<p>These last few days have felt like a vacation!</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Celebrating how well Sam has been doing</p></li>
<li><p>A joyful family weekend – letting medical issues be in the background of our lives.</p></li>
<li><p>Bonus physiotherapy for Sam. The elevator at the RMH was under repair for most of the weekend. This initially forced Sam to take the stairs – two flights up to the room. By the end of the weekend he chose the stairs to keep restoring his strength.</p></li>
<li><p>Today we will learn the results of last Friday’s PET and CT scans – the current state of the cancer.<br>
We will discuss with the medical team what the next steps are. Once again we will be stepping into the unknown. For now we know what life looks like until mid-day.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>added on June 7<sup>th</sup>↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-06_amazing-weekend-rmh.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Freedom from hospital life</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-03_freedom-release-to-rmd.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Good morning!<br>
Here we are having a good morning as we are experience a good level of freedom. All three of us are currently at the Ronald McDonald House. This am, Sam and I have had breakfast together, and as I write this Tina is sleeping in.</p>
<p>Sam made it through, we made it through this last round of chemotherapy!</p>
<section id="reflections-on-june-1-and-2" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-june-1-and-2">Reflections on June 1 and 2</h2>
<p><em>June 1</em> Sam was still in hospital. In consultation with the medical team most all of Sam’s meds moved from a) being on a delivery schedule to list as take-as-needed, b) changed from IV delivery to oral. The purpose of this day was to prepare us to get out – to give us control of Sam’s care.</p>
<p><em>June 2</em>, yesterday, was very full with procedures and our transition out of the hospital. Forty-five days prior we made the emergency move from Prince George to the hospital. We have lived there full time and now we had the day to prepare to leave.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The day started with trip to the BC Cancer Clinic for a PET and CT scan. This was much easier than the last trip. Last time the Ambulance service transported Sam which was needed given the state of his health at that time. This time, the three of us went downstairs, got in a taxi, and walked into the clinic.</p></li>
<li><p>Next were the steps to leave including:</p></li>
<li><p>A trip to the pharmacy – to collect all of Sam’s medications. This was actually simple, as the pharmacy is just downstairs. I would realize hours later, well after closing that I bought the wrong needles for Sam’s blood thinner…</p></li>
<li><p>Trips to move our lives over to the RMH<sup>1</sup>. In our time here we have lived full-time at the hospital with minor respite at the RMD. During our time here we have only added materials to our lives as we bought or people brought us life-essentials, and gifts arrived. We are blessed to have all that we need and more. I did spend a couple hours moving our things – very glad that the RMD had utility wagon that we could borrow.</p></li>
<li><p>Trip to the Red Cross – to get some hardware for Sam. He has some strength to regain so in moments of weakness or fatigue he can fall back to the wheelchair or shower-transfer-bench.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>We were fully here by 7:00pm. We are loving it! The feelings this morning are almost reminiscent of family vacations that we have had in the past. We are not home but we are free to be ourselves!</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for this opportunity to get out for a few days.</p></li>
<li><p>Upcoming we have to return to the hospital on Tuesday, June 6 when we will hear the results of the PET and CT scans and likely be admitted to start the next round of chemotherapy.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful, for the amazing care Sam received at BC Children’s Also thankful that we have a break from it – that we can sleep through the night without the need to take vitals, take blood, deliver medications, or listen to alarms.</p></li>
<li><p>Challenges of side-effects have mostly resolved! I will need to go in search of a vacuum cleaner as Sam’s hair rains from his head.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern, a recent scan flagged a the potential for a problematic kidney stone.</p></li>
<li><p>As always, we will remain concerned about any cancer in his system.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Ronald McDonald House↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>procedures</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-03_freedom-release-to-rmd.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A weekend pass, friends, and a date!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-01_pass-and-concert.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/hugs-4kc-concert.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Unexpected hugs at just prior to the start of the For King and Country concert</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Today is day 44 in hospital. Aside from one afternoon weeks ago Sam has not left these halls – it is time to have a change of scenery. Expectations are that this will happen over this weekend! As I write this my family is sleeping and I am only listening to the sound of a single pump pushing supplemental food into Sam’s body. No other lines are attached to him and no alarms were ringing through the night!</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-31" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-31">Reflections on May 31</h2>
<p>Yesterday the medical team started preparing to have us leave for a few days! We will be out in the small gap of time between chemotherapy rounds. All of Sam’s medications were converted to oral and I was trained up on how to use the food pump which the team wants to keep going. We are excited to have a change of scenery, to get Sam out, and for all three of us to have comfortable beds (<em>we will be staying at the RMH – Ronald McDonald House</em>). Honestly, we also have a little anxiety to make this change and leave the safety of these four wall. But bring it on – let’s get out for a few days!</p>
<p>Aria and family were able to visit again. Aria and Tina hit up a local gluten free bakery. Sam was able to have a short visit with David and Lucas H. and a little longer with David. We are thankful for their friendship.</p>
<p>In the evening Tina and I attended a concert! For several years Tina was been dreaming of attending a <a href="https://open.spotify.com/artist/3sDbKMebVH2VYcRSl7u1VC?si=6FcIxJJtS6uwiBK8RLl0qA">For King and Country</a> concert and we were able to get tickets. Tina loved it! She also loved huge hugs from Carlene and Kendra S., and Kim P. who happened to be sitting fairly close by!</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for the upcoming opportunity to get out for a few days. Round 3 of chemo will likely start next Tuesday. There will be adjustments as we take on a new routine.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for the chance to visit with friends.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for date nights!</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful to see Sam’s blood counts returning to normal including the numbers indicating the strengthening of hi immune system.</p></li>
<li><p>Challenges of side-effects continue. Sam, although have a return of energy, is becoming physically exhausted. This whole regime, and being bed-bound for a full week, has led to parts of his system being bound – constipation is significant issue. It will pass but likely not without pain. GI sores from the chemotherapy also complicate this.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern, a recent scan flagged a the potential for a problematic kidney stone.</p></li>
<li><p>Upcoming, this Friday June 2, Sam is books for a PET scans. The purpose of this scan is to determine the current state of the cancer. We look forward to knowing the results. We are excited that previous scans suggest significant reductions in the cancer, and that this scan should confirm that. As always, we will remain concerned about any cancer in his system.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-01_pass-and-concert.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Visits and a date</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-31_visits-date.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="reflections-on-may-29-and-30" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-29-and-30">Reflections on May 29 and 30</h2>
<p>Medically, the last couple days for Sam have been mostly positive as we see his numbers come back and see him gain energy back, be mostly over his cold/flu. The chemo-side-effects have presented themselves further as Sam has begun to lose his hair, I discuss additional challenges in the concerns below.</p>
<p>During this time, it has been great to have Nana here to visit with all of us but especially with Sam. Her time here also allowed Tina and I to get out together for a few hours away from the hospital. Vancouver has been good to us in that we have not struggled to find good food for Tina. However, most of this has been ordered in. On the 29<sup>th</sup> we were able go out for some good food – to have a date. We took the Skytrain into Yaletown, walked the neighbourhood and had a meal together. I know this is shocking to many – I don’t think we took one picture on our date… if we had I would have posted something.</p>
<p>The 30<sup>th</sup> is marked as being Nana’s last day visiting with us – we expect she will be back in a number of weeks. Uncle Cal, and cousins Amanda and Chris were also able to stop by for a quick visit. Nana and the family left in the evening. Sam also had a friend stop by, David H. spent the evening with him, while Aria and Tina visited. An additional visit earlier today, Tina and I had a great catch-up with Sam, Nick and Elara G.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for visits from Nana, local family, and friends.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful to see Sam’s blood counts returning to normal including the numbers indicating the strengthening of hi immune system.</p></li>
<li><p>Challenges of side-effects. Sam, although have a return of energy, is becoming physically exhausted. This whole regime, and being bed-bound for a full week has led to parts of his system being bound – constipation is significant issue. It will pass but likely not without pain. GI sores from the chemotherapy also complicate this.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern, a recent scan flagged a the potential for a problematic kidney stone.</p></li>
<li><p>Upcoming, this Friday June 2, Sam is books for a PET scans. The purpose of this scan is to determine to current state of the cancer. We look forward to knowing the results. We are excited that previous scans suggest significant reductions in the cancer and that this scan should confirm that. As always, we will remain concerned about any cancer in his system.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-31_visits-date.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Weekend Review</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-29_weekend.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I am writing this am simply to keep the updates coming. Perhaps it is a good thing that there is little of significance to communicate as this past weekend was much of the same – generally holding a pattern and continuing on with the chemotherapy – now day 17 of 21.</p>
<section id="weekend-highlights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="weekend-highlights">Weekend highlights</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Nana is here and has spent some good time with Sam. I am especially thankful that Tina has had some great visits with her mom.</p></li>
<li><p>I got out for a couples hours to ride around the city.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has struggled with secondary illness – basically he has a cold. He started a different antibiotic and was starting to feel better by Sunday afternoon.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Friends in PG did a major yard clean-up for us – thank-you!</p></li>
<li><p>We are starting to see Sam’s blood counts return to normal … though his immune system has not recovered yet.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that early indications are that the cancer is being removed from Sam’s body. Though we choose to hope and trust that he will see complete return to health, we will remain concerned that any cancer persists in his body.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-29_weekend.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>An update and a meditation: Psalm 91</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-27_psalm-91.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>The Psalms are a great place to read and be inspired. The writers pour out their hearts in song and prayer providing beautiful expressions from the heart that can cover a broad range of emotion from pain and frustration to hope and praise. Several people have given Psalm 91 to us to read, meditate on, and pray through. I encourage you to read this Psalm, and pray it for Sam!</p>
<section id="therapy-update" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="therapy-update">Therapy update</h2>
<p>Before you do just a few quick points to update you on how his journey is going and the next steps as we know them:</p>
<ul>
<li>We are currently just past the halfway mark in round 2 of chemotherapy. The heavy chemical part of the treatment is over and now Sam’s body has to work through the effects. Effects include (these are generally expected):
<ul>
<li><p>collapse of the immune system: Sam’s blood counts are monitored daily. Over the last number of days drops in the red and platelet cells have been managed with transfusions. We need to simply wait for the white cells to come back. It seems Sam may be through the worst of this part as cell counts are beginning to return on their own.</p></li>
<li><p>sores in the GI system. Sam had some sores in his mouth earlier in this process. They have healed but he has other much further on in the system that are painful. These will heal in time.</p></li>
<li><p>Most of Sam’s time is spent in bed … his body is doing a lot of work. The downside of being in bed this long is that he is stiff and sore; he has a lot of muscle tension and very little energy to stretch it out or move to loosen it up. We will get there but there is work to be done.</p></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>Next steps and current state of the cancer:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The truth is the next steps are very much unknown. The treatment plan will depend on how the cancer has responded to this latest round of therapy.</p></li>
<li><p>We are encouraged, Sam had an X-ray to rule out that the flu he had was not causing a pneumonia. This scan confirmed that he did not have pneumonia. What was unexpected, is that the scan also gave us a glimpse at the state of his cancer, and the doctors confirmed that the cancer-mass has shrunk.</p></li>
<li><p>Once this current therapy is complete on June 2<sup>nd</sup> Sam will be booked for a scan. Once the results of the scan are known a new plan will be made.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="meditation-psalm-91" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="meditation-psalm-91">Meditation <a href="https://www.bible.com/bible/111/PSA.91.NIV">Psalm 91</a></h2>
<p>Thank you for journeying with us. May this Psalm inspire your thoughts and prayers:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Whoever dwells in the shelter of the Most High</p>
<p>will rest in the shadow of the Almighty.</p>
<p>I will say of the <span class="smallcaps">Lord</span>, “He is my refuge and my fortress,</p>
<p>my God, in whom I trust.”</p>
<p><br>
Surely he will save you</p>
<p>from the fowler’s snare</p>
<p>and from the deadly pestilence.</p>
<p>He will cover you with his feathers,</p>
<p>and under his wings you will find refuge;</p>
<p>his faithfulness will be your shield and rampart.</p>
<p>You will not fear the terror of night,</p>
<p>nor the arrow that flies by day,</p>
<p>nor the pestilence that stalks in the darkness,</p>
<p>nor the plague that destroys at midday.</p>
<p>A thousand may fall at your side,</p>
<p>ten thousand at your right hand,</p>
<p>but it will not come near you.</p>
<p>You will only observe with your eyes</p>
<p>and see the punishment of the wicked.</p>
<p><br>
If you say, “The <span class="smallcaps">Lord</span> is my refuge,”</p>
<p>and you make the Most High your dwelling,</p>
<p>no harm will overtake you,</p>
<p>no disaster will come near your tent.</p>
<p>For he will command his angels concerning you</p>
<p>to guard you in all your ways;</p>
<p>they will lift you up in their hands,</p>
<p>so that you will not strike your foot against a stone.</p>
<p>You will tread on the lion and the cobra;</p>
<p>you will trample the great lion and the serpent.</p>
<p><br>
“Because he loves me,” says the <span class="smallcaps">Lord</span>, “I will rescue him;</p>
<p>I will protect him, for he acknowledges my name.</p>
<p>He will call on me, and I will answer him;</p>
<p>I will be with him in trouble,</p>
<p>I will deliver him and honor him.</p>
<p>With long life I will satisfy him</p>
<p>and show him my salvation.”</p>
</blockquote>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-27_psalm-91.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Preliminary findings (round 2)</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-25_preliminary-findings.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>The days have been blurring together in this time-warp experience here at BC Children’s hospital. This morning is the beginning of day 37 – now just over five weeks since our arrival. This current round of chemotherapy will come to an end in another ten days. In some ways it feels like we are on a long waiting period, yet everyday brings its own challenges or occasional bits of news. Each day we:</p>
<ul>
<li>get updates on Sam’s blood counts</li>
<li>manage pain related to the effects of chemo</li>
<li>try to stay active</li>
<li>try to play a game or read … but often the energy/concentration level is not there so there is a lot of TV. <em><br>
We would love some recommendations of shows or movies that you have enjoyed.</em></li>
</ul>
<section id="findings-from-an-x-ray" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="findings-from-an-x-ray">Findings from an X-ray</h2>
<p>Two days ago Tina and I had a good conversation with Dr.&nbsp;S. Cheng. We love how honest she is with us, that she shares what she knows and how she lets us know what she does not know. In our meeting, she told us about Sam’s latest chest X-ray – the purpose of which was to rule out the potential for pneumonia related to Sam’s cold. There was also enough information in the image that Dr.&nbsp;Cheng could provide a preliminary report: the tumour is smaller than shown in the previous CT scan (taken after round 1 of chemo). We are headed in the right direction – round 1 saw a reduction in the cancerous mass, and round 2 appears to be doing the same! We will know better in with the next scan in a couple weeks when a scan will be done to image the cancer itself.</p>
<p>As to what the next steps will be following this round of chemo – that is simply unknown.</p>
</section>
<section id="reflections-on-may-23-and-24" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-23-and-24">Reflections on May 23 and 24</h2>
<p>The 23<sup>rd</sup> was a day filled with the love from friends and family. The three of us had a good visit with Craig and Lisa R, followed by Tina and I having time with them. Nana spent much of the day sitting with Sam, and much of the evening with Tina. Yesterday, was quieter in Sam’s room. As per doctor’s recommendations we reduced his visitor hours. I spent most of the day with Sam, less a couple hours, when Nana sat with him. Outside the room, Tina and Mary (Nana) had a great visit with Tina’s nieces Amanda and Jayme, and Jane, and her brother Cal.</p>
<p>It has also been nice to seen the familar faces of Jarod and Erin S. as we either meet with them or simply bump into them in the halls here.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for friends and family supporting us.</p></li>
<li><p>The medical team here continues to be amazing.</p></li>
<li><p>Side effects of the chemo-therapy. No hair loss yet, but significant muscle pain, and pains related to sores in the GI track<sup>1</sup>.</p></li>
<li><p>The constant cancer concern. We will not know how the cancer has responded to this treatment for another week-and-a-half. Once the full therapy cycle is complete the team here will scan for changes.</p></li>
<li><p>Homesickness and boredom. Sam has been a champ making the best of his time here. Yesterday, Sam and I had a great conversation about home, that we miss it, and we imagined/ dreamed of what we love about home from simple things of regular life, to friends, to dreaming of what we would like to do when we return. Longing for home and feeling trapped in this hospital ward may become significant challenges in the days ahead.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Gastrointestinal track – from the mouth all the way through and out of the digestive system↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-25_preliminary-findings.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Nana is here!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-23_nana-arrives.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Although I am wiped out from a short night of sleep, I have joy. Sam is awake beside me acting himself. I do hope that he takes a nap later – but this is good to see. He has energy to play a game – something he simply has not had the concentration power to do. Last night had actually been a hard one. I am not sure it was the flu or other effects of the chemo but his sleep had been interupted and thereby mine was as well.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-22" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-22">Reflections on May 22</h2>
<p>Medically, yesterday was a day of discomfort. Sam had the flu, a result of the chemo taking out his immune system, and with this illness he had quite a bit of muscle pain. Blood tests also showed his counts were down again. In response, Sam received transfusions in the afternoon.</p>
<p>The highlight of the day was the happy reunion of Sam and Nana in the early afternoon! I had taken the skytrain out to the airport and we travelled straight back to the see Tina and Sam. Tina and her mom were also able to spend some good times catching up. Hopefully they are having a good sleep-in over at the RMH.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for Nana</p></li>
<li><p>The medical team here continues to be amazing.</p></li>
<li><p>The constant cancer concern. We will not know how the cancer has responded to this treatment for another week-and-a-half. Once the full therapy cycle is complete the team here will scan for changes.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-23_nana-arrives.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
