<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Sam Chisholm</title>
<link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/</link>
<atom:link href="http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>News updating friends and family on our journey</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.56</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>A Surgery to Celebrate!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2408/2024-08-16_surgery-celebration.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- ::: {.callout-note icon="false"}
## TL;DR [Too long didn't read (i.e. the short version)]{.small}

-   Scan results show that the cancerous mass in Sam's chest has grown.
-   The cancer is impacting Sam's vascular system and threatens his
    heart.
-   Plans are in place to protect Sam's heart.
-   Nivo dose is quadrupled.
-   Love of friends and family
::: -->
<!-- :::{layout="[60, 40]"} -->
<section id="success" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="success">Success</h2>
<div id="photo" class="img-float-right">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-08-16_preop-stc.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Pre-op: Sam is ready to head into the operating room. Colin is gowned-up to go in with him – until they sedate him.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>Yesterday’s surgery went better than we had hoped!</p>
<p>The original plan was to install one or two stents to maintain the function of Sam’s limited but existing blood-flow (i.e.&nbsp;reinforce one of his small collateral veins). However, the surgeons<sup>1</sup> presented a new plan. The new ‘Plan A’ would be to reestablish flow through the brachiocephalic vein ! They were hopeful they could reopen the left side. They would fall back to ‘Plan B’ as described in my <a href="../../posts/2408/2024-08-13_threat-response.html">previous post</a> if they were not able to do so.</p>
<p>Plan A was a success! It took significantly longer than planned but 3.5 hours later the doctors came and talked with us. They were obviously pleased that they were able to do this. Tina and I are are ecstatic! Sam is feeling good! We are currently in the hospital for observation but we expect to be back to the RMH by the end of today.</p>
</section>
<section id="where" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="where">Where?</h2>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="2">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div id="img-heart" class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://oncohemakey.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/B9781455728657000485_f048-001-9781455728657.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The heart and major veins retuning deoxygenated blood from the upper body to the heart.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div id="fn-text" class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<p>The left and right bracheocephalic veins were believed to be fully occluded. The right was occluded when we first arrived due to blood clotting associated with the disease. As of last week’s scans the left is also fully blocked.</p>
<p>During yesterday’s surgery the team was able to reestablish flow in the left bracheocephalic and to install a stent there to keep it open. This result gives Sam much more ‘normal’ blood-flow and takes the literal pressure off his collateral vascular network.</p>
<p>In addition, measurements during surgery indicated that the Superior vena cava (SVC) is functioning normally.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are celebrating the success of Sam’s surgery. The outcome was far better than we had hoped for resulting in a return to near-normal blood-flow!</p></li>
<li><p>The cancer has grown and the impacts of the disease are threatening Sam’s vascular system and thereby his life.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam will have surgery, planned for August 15, to install stents to protect the blood-flow returning to his heart. This is an unusual surgery as Sam’s vasculature is abnormal - the most trusted doctors with the most expertise to deal with this risky procedure have been asked to perform it.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam is on higher levels of Nivolumab. Side effects of this medication include fatigue and agitation of the liver. In the past we were not able to use this drug for numerous weeks due to liver inflammation. Current support medications are being used to reduce negative side effects.</p></li>
<li><p>To date, the medicines and interventions that have been tried have not had any significant or lasting effect at controlling this disease. We need something that will work. We need a miracle.</p></li>
<li><p>It was amazing to see Sam join the <a href="https://www.nesslakebiblecamp.com">Ness Lake Bible Camp</a> team (July 28 - 31) . He served, ran, talked, played – he got to be fully there! Many thanks to the NLBC team who welcomed him in.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam (we are also thankful for everyone praying for Sam whereever you are). If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for such supportive family and friends caring for us all through this journey.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is free of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>technically these doctors are <em>Interventional Radiologists</em>↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2408/2024-08-16_surgery-celebration.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-08-16_preop-stc.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Threat Responses</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2408/2024-08-13_threat-response.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Success!
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><em>Update: 2024-08-16</em></p>
<p>The surgery was more successful than we could have dreamed!<br>
Dis-regard the planned surgery specifics below as the doctors came up with a new and better plan. See my next post: <a href="../../posts/2408/2024-08-16_surgery-celebration.html">A Surgery to Celebrate</a></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Scan results show that the cancerous mass in Sam’s chest has grown.</li>
<li>The cancer is impacting Sam’s vascular system and threatens his heart.</li>
<li>Plans are in place to protect Sam’s heart.</li>
<li>Nivo dose is quadrupled.</li>
<li>Love of friends and family</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<section id="current-situation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="current-situation">Current situation</h2>
<p>Last week Sam’s cancer journey reached a higher level of intensity. This has been a hard journey and now it is downright scary. Threats to Sam’s life are incredibly intense. First, there is the immediate threat-to-life as the cancer has caused significant damage to Sam’s vascular system and now threatens the heart itself. Second, despite the valiant effort of our medical team and Sam’s incredible courage to both understand and take on the treatments, the cancer itself continues to grow (see <a href="../../posts/2408/2024-08-07_scan-results.html">previous post</a>). Medically speaking our options are limited – we need a miracle.</p>
<p>Despite the intensity of the current medical situation in many ways Sam appears to be healthier than he has been since before this disease began.</p>
</section>
<section id="medical-response-and-plans" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="medical-response-and-plans">Medical response and plans</h2>
<section id="maintaining-blood-flow" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="maintaining-blood-flow">Maintaining blood-flow</h3>
<p>The cancer directly or indirectly has blocked/occluded some of Sam’s major blood vessels<sup>1</sup>. As a result, blood from his head and upper body is being re-routed through an extensive network of small collateral vessels that Sam’s body has developed in compensation.</p>
<p>This past week we met with the intervention radiology surgical team. They have made plans to try to keep Sam’s remaining blood-flow pathways open.</p>
<p>On Thursday August 15 Sam is scheduled to have surgery during which stents will be inserted to maintain existing blood-flow to his heart. One will be placed in a small collateral vein that is returning the bulk of Sam’s upper body blood volume. A second stent will be used to keep the Superior vena cava open.</p>
</section>
<section id="additional-scare-er-visit" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="additional-scare-er-visit">Additional scare – ER visit</h3>
<p>Given everything that was revealed in the last scan our vigilance has been increased (can it go any higher?). On Sunday evening Sam started to have new/novel pains in his chest – at his heart - and strange pulsing sensations in his neck. So we went into the ER.By the time we arrived and settled in, Sam’s vitals were great. As nothing requiring immediate intervention could be determined, and given that we had a visit planned with Sam’s medical team the next day, we returned to RMH.</p>
</section>
<section id="disease-control" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="disease-control">Disease control</h3>
<p>It is unknown if this cancer can be controlled but that does not mean we will stop trying. In response to the latest scans we will push on and push harder. Greater risks must be taken. Treatments must be accelerated.</p>
<p>The original plan was to attempt an increase in Sam’s Nivolumab by doubling the dose. Given the latest results we have chosen to push harder. Wednesday the dose was quadrupled in an effort to find an effective dose – though it will take a few weeks to know if it is having the desired effect.</p>
<p>In addition, Sam is back on high-dose steroids (prednisone). One of the primary reasons to use this drug is to quickly reduce inflammation in the body. Sam has also used it in the past to protect his liver which the Nivolumab can harm. Within 24 hours of starting the drug it was possible to visibly see positive impacts.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="friends-and-family" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friends-and-family">Friends and family</h2>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="2">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div id="txt" class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<p>This past week it was amazing to have the in-person support of some friends and family from Prince George. We had great visits and times that simply felt normal.</p>
<p>Joel, Joanna, and Chase were here for Friday evening and Saturday. We shared meals, went to a movie (Inside Out 2 – it is great!), made an ice cream run, Chase and Sam threw a football around, and played some video games together.</p>
<p>Sunday and Monday my parents came to spend time with us. The effects of the Nivolumab started to set in on Sunday – causing fatigue. However, that did not stop us from spending time and sharing meals together. Sam loved having his grandparents here. Sam seems to be loving his ice cream these days (could be the prednisone) so to wrap up our time together we celebrated with an ice cream cake that Sam requested from DQ.</p>
</div>
<div id="photo" class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-08-11_sam-with-gram-papa.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Sam with Gram and Papa C.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>The cancer has grown and the impacts of the disease are threatening Sam’s vascular system and thereby his life.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam will have surgery, planned for August 15, to install stents to protect the blood-flow returning to his heart. This is an unusual surgery as Sam’s vasculature is abnormal - the most trusted doctors with the most expertise to deal with this risky procedure have been asked to perform it.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam is on higher levels of Nivolumab. Side effects of this medication include fatigue and agitation of the liver. In the past we were not able to use this drug for numerous weeks due to liver inflammation. Current support medications are being used to reduce negative side effects.</p></li>
<li><p>To date, the medicines and interventions that have been tried have not had any significant or lasting effect at controlling this disease. We need something that will work. We need a miracle.</p></li>
<li><p>It was amazing to see Sam join the <a href="https://www.nesslakebiblecamp.com">Ness Lake Bible Camp</a> team (July 28 - 31) . He served, ran, talked, played – he got to be fully there! Many thanks to the NLBC team who welcomed him in.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam (we are also thankful for everyone praying for Sam whereever you are). If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for such supportive family and friends caring for us all through this journey.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is free of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="2">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div id="fn-text" class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<p>The left and right bracheocephalic veins are fully occluded. The right was occluded when we first arrived due to blood clotting associated with the disease. As of last week’s scans the left is also now fully occluded. Sam’s body has adapted rerouting blood through collateral vessels. One of these small vessels returns blood directly into the Superior vena cava (SVC). Blood return through other collaterals is collected by the Azygos vein.</p>
<p>An additional issue is that the SVC is also partially occluded (~50%).</p>
<p>Surgery this week will insert stents to ensure that a) the one collateral returning blood directly to the SVC remains open, and b) That the SVC itself remains open.</p>
</div>
<div id="img-heart" class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://oncohemakey.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/B9781455728657000485_f048-001-9781455728657.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The heart and major veins returing deoxygenated blood from the upper body to the heart.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
↩︎</li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2408/2024-08-13_threat-response.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-08-11_sam-with-gram-papa.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Threats – Scan Results</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2408/2024-08-07_scan-results.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Scan results show that the cancerous mass in Sam’s chest has grown.</li>
<li>The cancer is impacting Sam’s vascular system and threatens his heart.</li>
<li>Sam is on the ward to receive a higher dose of Nivolumab.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<!---
::: {#photo}
![Sam had an amazing week serving on the Ness Lake Team! Here Dave
Horton presented Sam with a team shirt, and coveted Ness Lake button
awards.](https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-07-31_dave-sam-buttons-ness-lake.jpg)
:::
--->
<p>This past weekend was filled with the love of family and friends but it carried an underlying inescapable anxiety as we waited for scan results. Yesterday, the fears we battled through the weekend were realized – the cancer has grown. Today Sam received an elevated dose of Nivolumab in an effort to get the cancer under control and again we wait, hope, and pray that one of these treatments will finally work.</p>
<section id="an-anxious-weekend" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="an-anxious-weekend">An anxious weekend</h2>
<p>Last Friday was filled with numerous appointments the most important being a PET scan to determine the current extent of Sam’s cancer. However, it is a rare day that we get the results on the same day – so we had to wait-out this past long/holiday weekend before getting the results.</p>
<p>In addition, given that Sam has been on morphine for such a long time, on Saturday we attempted a plan (suggested by our doctors) to switch him over to methadone (i.e.&nbsp;start replacing morphine with methadone). I do not fully understand why it did not work but by mid-day-Saturday Sam was writhing in pain. It would take another 36 hours before he would start feeling himself again. During this time we were able be with with Nana and the Fricker family (Saturday and Sunday). We would have loved for Sam to take part more with the family but the medication switch had taken him down – he was able to see everyone but he had very limited capacity to be with the family.</p>
<p>By Monday Sam was feeling better, having returned to his regular drug regime. Mid-day we had a nice visit/lunch with friends, Donna and Ciaro, whom we had met through RMH. In the evening we saw the Townsends. It was great to see Sam feeling better and he was even able to enjoy a game with his cousins. We were back at the RMH for the night as we had clinic the next morning.</p>
</section>
<section id="scan-results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="scan-results">Scan results</h2>
<p>It had been a long wait through the weekend to finally get to clinic yesterday and hear the results of last week’s scans. As always our medical team was amazing, especially given the hard task before them. The results are not what any of us wanted. The cancer had grown again. In retrospect, now that we have enough scans of the same type (i.e.&nbsp;not mixing results from different types of scans), it seems that the cancer has grown fairly consistently and none of the medicinal treatments have had measurable impacts at slowing the disease. Additional concerns were also raised as this disease is having further impacts on Sam’s vascular system as it grows into and around some of Sam’s major vessels and heart. The left and right <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brachiocephalic_vein">brachiocephalic veins</a> are blocked by impacts of the disease (the main veins transporting blood from Sam’s head to his heart). Sam’s body has adapted as he has an extensive network of smaller/collateral vessels that move the blood around this blockage. Flow is also partially restricted in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Superior_vena_cava">superior vena cava</a>, the major collection chamber for blood returning to the heart from the upper body – again caused by the cancer.</p>
</section>
<section id="next-steps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next steps</h2>
<p>Today, Sam received a dose of Nivolumab at a rate 4-times what he has received previously. This increased dose was done in effort to find a level that may show some effect. However, in doing so we recognize that this may also cause side effects that we have been hoping to avoid. He will remain in hospital for monitoring overnight and if he remains stable he may be discharged to the RMH over the weekend.</p>
<p>Next week Sam will have another contrast-CT in an attempt to image if any impacts can be measured.</p>
<p>So how are we doing through all of this you ask? It would be a lie to say we are not scared. The disease has been a constant threat and now more than ever. However, there are great moments of joy. It is impossible not to smile when Sam wakes from a nap with a big smile on his face saying “<em>I’m so happy.</em>” He is happy – he knows he is cared for and he knows that he is loved.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>The cancer has grown and the impacts of the disease are threatening Sam’s vascular system and thereby his life.</p></li>
<li><p>To date medicines have not had any significant effect at controlling this disease. We need something that will work. We need a miracle.</p></li>
<li><p>It was amazing to see Sam join the <a href="https://www.nesslakebiblecamp.com">Ness Lake Bible Camp</a> team (July 28 - 31) . He served, ran, talked, played – he got to be fully there! Many thanks to the NLBC team who welcomed him in.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam (we are also thankful for everyone praying for Sam whereever you are). If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for such supportive family and friends caring for us all through this journey.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is free of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2408/2024-08-07_scan-results.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post-Camp Scan Day</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2408/2024-08-02_post-camp-scan-day.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>It was an amazing week at home connecting with friends and family.</li>
<li>Sam joined in serving at Ness Lake Bible Camp.</li>
<li>We are now in Vancouver for a PET scan, various tests, and hopefully Sam’s next Nivolumab treatment.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div id="photo">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-07-31_dave-sam-buttons-ness-lake.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Sam had an amazing week serving on the Ness Lake Team! Here Dave Horton presented Sam with a team shirt, and coveted Ness Lake button/awards.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>I am currently writing in the dark as Sam is having a nap, waiting for his turn in the PET scan machine. I would be lying if I said that all of us are feeling great this morning. The reality is that scan days are always stressful as they mark significant chapters in Sam’s treatment. They mark significant pivot points where treatment plans are adjusted – either to keep going with the treatment regime or change it up. Perhaps today’s scan is all the more stressful as it is to determine if one of our last treatment options (immunotherapy combined with a new medication) is working or not. Additionally, being back in Vancouver and being under the watchful eye of our medical team is in stark contrast to the freedom, fun-living, and joy had with friends this past week.</p>
<section id="an-amazing-week-at-home" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="an-amazing-week-at-home">An amazing week at home!</h2>
<p>I am still stunned at how good this last week has been! Since my last post:</p>
<dl>
<dt>Saturday</dt>
<dd>
<p>This day was a turning point. Most of this day and all of the days prior that week Sam had been feeling the effects of his immunotherapy drugs – generally wiped-out/lethargic and achy.</p>
<p>In the evening he had a return of energy and the Bandstra, Claus, and Cross families rearranged their plans and came over. We had a great summer evening in the back yard talking and playing games. Sam was especially encouraged receiving the care of friends.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Sunday</dt>
<dd>
<p>Tina and I made it to church… well we made it in the door and then spent the time connecting with people. Sam slept in that morning but gave me a call asking to come greet people following the service. It was encouraging for all!</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>In the evening, Sam having heard from his friends the night before about how great working at <a href="https://www.nesslakebiblecamp.com">Ness Lake Bible Camp</a> was, he asked to go and visit – which we did. However, Sam wasn’t satisfied with visiting and by the end of the evening he had spent several hours working in the kitchen or wherever else he was able.<br>
<!-- five hours at camp --></p>
</dd>
<dt>Monday</dt>
<dd>
<p>We figured that Sam would need a rest day – we were wrong! That afternoon Tina took Sam out to camp again where he worked, visited, and took part in cabin time with the kids!</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>That evening some of the church leaders came by to support and pray with us and for Sam – more encouragement.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Tuesday</dt>
<dd>
<p>I spent the morning at work – made it out to the forest. It was great to be there again. Also, to connect with my work-world people!</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Sam was not going to miss out, and he was out to serve at camp again. Tina had expected to take him home at any point, but he stayed until late in the evening! He even had energy for the evening <em>Safari</em> game where leaders dress up as animals and the campers have to <em>hunt</em> them. He had an amazing time. Though a fall during the game resulted in us putting him in an air-cast. An x-ray, if needed, will be completed while we are here in Vancouver. This leg pain was all worth the experience of joining the team.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Wednesday</dt>
<dd>
<p>As a family, we focused on packing up to be ready to head south.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Sam was thinking he would have a rest day but having received an invite from camp to join in on activities, he was not going to miss out. That evening Sam, although hobbling with the air-cast, took part in work projects, discussion times, and then the end-of-week <em>button ceremony</em> where Sam was awarded two buttons. The encouragement definitely went both ways: camp leaders were so impressed with Sam, while Sam had his heart-bucket filled to overflowing.<br>
<br>
From <a href="https://www.facebook.com/share/p/6Wbygpy8NLnhsAvp/">Dave Horton’s post</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Sam Chisolm earned his summer team shirt and both director pins (which does not happen ever)…</p>
<ul>
<li>for serving others (through some physical pain) before himself</li>
<li>for going from a visitor to “what can I do to help.”</li>
</ul>
<p>Dude helped with dishes, A team, camper supervision and more. We could not find enough for him to do.</p>
</blockquote>
</dd>
</dl>
<p>Tina, Sam, and I have been so encouraged by these days that Sam had in camp. It was amazing to see him rise and have the energy to engage. Amazing to see the joy he had. A huge thank you to all of the Ness Lake Crew – thank you for welcoming Sam onto the team!</p>
<dl>
<dt>Thursday</dt>
<dd>
<p>We got away from Prince George in great time. Had a great visit with family in Langley and then settled into the RMH that evening.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="looking-forward" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-forward">Looking forward</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Today (Friday)</dt>
<dd>
<p>Will be a full day: PET scan, abdominal ultrasound (to check liver), bloodwork, and meetings in the oncology clinic. It is very likely that we will not receive scan results until after this long weekend.</p>
</dd>
<dt>This weekend</dt>
<dd>
<p>Hoping to connect with Nana and the rest of the family</p>
</dd>
<dt>Tuesday, August 6</dt>
<dd>
<p>Clinic at BC Children’s to review scan results and hopefully for Sam to receive his next dose of Nivolumab in his ongoing imnuno-therapy treatment. It is our hope that we can return home the next day.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>It was an amazing week as Sam was able to join the <a href="https://www.nesslakebiblecamp.com">Ness Lake Bible Camp</a> team. He served, ran, talked - he got to be fully there!</p></li>
<li><p>It is scan day. Anxieties are high and we will likely need to live with them until after the long weekend.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam’s immune therapy plan has continued to move forward. Following three doses of Nivolumab Sam has not had any severe adverse side effects!</p></li>
<li><p>Results from the July 4<sup>th</sup> MRI indicated that the cancer mass in Sam’s chest has not grown!</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that we can look ahead a little and that we can be home again!</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is free of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2408/2024-08-02_post-camp-scan-day.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-07-31_dave-sam-buttons-ness-lake.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Home Again</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2407/2024-07-26_homeward-bound-again.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>We are home again! We got home on the 23<sup>rd</sup> following a short medical trip to Vancouver (July 18 - 22).</li>
<li>Sam has successfully received his latest dose of Nivolumab and his body continues to tolerate this set of medications.</li>
<li>Sam is scheduled for a PET scan on August 2<sup>nd</sup>.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div id="photo">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-07-21_chisholm-cresent-beach.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Enjoying some hours at Crescent Beach! Great visit with Nana Mary and the Frickers.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>I can understand it if you were feeling like you were missing our on our lives and wondering what is going on – it has been over two weeks since I last wrote.</p>
<p>In that time we were at home, travelled to Vancouver, and returned home again. During our times at home, we had some good visits with a number of our friends here, and I started to feel that I was maybe beginning to recover from burnout. Sam, of course, despite often feeling physically exhausted from it all, continues to be amazing, maintaining his positive attitude throughout this long journey.</p>
<section id="looking-back" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-back">Looking back</h2>
<p>Most recently, last Thursday, July 18, we made a roadtrip down to BC Children’s. We chose to drive as it allows for more flexible timing and gives us some freedom while there. On that Friday, there was a minor question-mark related to some of Sam’s bloodwork and the team chose: to adjust some of Sam’s supporting medications<sup>1</sup>, and to wait out a cold that he had.</p>
<p>Over the weekend we were able to have a visit with the Frickers and Nana including a nice afternoon watching the tide come in at Crescent Beach.</p>
<p>The next Monday Sam’s cold and bloodwork had improved and he was able to receive another dose of Nivolumab. In addition an echocardiogram showed that there were no significant negative impacts on Sam’s heart. Despite not leaving the clinic until 4:30 that afternoon we decided to start our trip home. We made it to Kamloops that night and the rest of the way on Tuesday.</p>
<p>This last trip down marks our shortest visit to BC Children’s Hospital and the Ronald McDonald house. It is our hope that this will become a more normal pattern. Yet it is too soon to discuss patterns or plans for life.</p>
</section>
<section id="looking-forward" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-forward">Looking forward</h2>
<p>On August 2<sup>nd</sup> Sam is due back in Vancouver. We will spend several days there as he is scheduled for a PET scan, an ultrasound, and another dose of Nivolumab.</p>
<p>In the meantime we have just over a week at home. We are loving it here – however in some ways it is a strange adjustment (including not having Tina’s parents here). Many thanks to whoever mowed our backyard! In this time we will celebrate birthdays, I will get to work for some part days, and we hope to continue reconnecting with our Prince George friends and family.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam’s immune therapy plan continues to move forward. Following three doses of Nivolumab Sam has not had any severe adverse side effects!</p></li>
<li><p>Results from the July 4<sup>th</sup> MRI indicated that the cancer mass in Sam’s chest has not grown!</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that we can look ahead a little and that we can be home again!</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is free of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Supporting meds being the switch from prednisone to hydrocortisone for increased adrenal support. Note that weaning off of prednisone seemed to not provide enough adrenal support, including support to effectively battle the cold he had.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2407/2024-07-26_homeward-bound-again.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-07-21_chisholm-cresent-beach.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scan results</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2407/2024-07-09_mri-scan-results.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Happy Anniversary – Tina and I celebrate 28 years.</li>
<li>Pain management for Sam (again).</li>
<li>Sam is able to continue with the latest mix of medications.</li>
<li>MRI results indicate no growth in the cancer mass!</li>
<li>Other family challenges.</li>
<li>Going home!</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<!-- ::: {#photo}
![On May 29^th^ we checked out of the Ronald McDonald House for the
first time since starting this cancer battle! We took a ten day break
home -- it was amazing to be
there!](https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-05-29_rmh-checkout.jpg)
::: -->
<p>It has been a week-and-a-half since my last post. Despite some challenges the overall picture is good as Sam’s body has tolerated the new combination of medications. In addition, the MRI scan showed that the cancer has not grown since the previous scan.</p>
<section id="challenges" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="challenges">Challenges</h2>
<section id="june-29th" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="june-29th">June 29<sup>th</sup></h3>
<p>We have had a few challenges since I last wrote – I am glad they are not all focused on Sam.</p>
<p>The last weekend of June was tough. Tina and I celebrated our 28<sup>th</sup> anniversary (love you Tina!) while visiting Nana in White Rock (the Frickers were away). Sam had received his dose of Nivolumab a week earlier and what we now know/remember is that it takes about a week for effects and corresponding pains to set in. One of the hardest things in this whole journey is to watch your child when they are in pain and to not understand what is causing it. Over the next couple days we were able to get his pain under control allowing to feel himself again.</p>
<p>Also that weekend, Nana Mary was having some heart related symptoms that gave us a scare – she seems to be good now.</p>
<p>To celebrate our anniversary, instead of going out for dinner, Tina and I chose to stay in and eat with our beloved Sam and mother Mary. It was a good evening, despite the uncertainty of everything going on.</p>
</section>
<section id="july-6---8" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="july-6---8">July 6 - 8</h3>
<p>In addition to waiting for these situations to resolve, one reason that this post is a few days late coming is that this past weekend I was laid flat. A head cold took all my energy for the better part of Saturday through Monday.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="current-medical-situation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="current-medical-situation">Current medical situation</h2>
<p>Sam’s medical situation over the last couple weeks is generally good news!</p>
<p>First, Sam’s body is tolerating the latest mix of medications – specifically, <a href="http://www.bccancer.bc.ca/drug-database-site/Drug%20Index/Nivolumab_monograph.pdf">Nivolumab</a> and <a href="http://www.bccancer.bc.ca/drug-database-site/Drug%20Index/Ruxolitinib_monograph.pdf">Ruxolitinib</a>. The initial attempt to use Nivolumab, at the end of Feb., did not go well and resulted in lost time recovering from side effects (primarily liver inflammation). Currently, the combination of these two drugs seems to be working well – specifically, metrics related to Sam’s liver are stable and even in normal ranges.</p>
<p>Sam also had an MRI of his chest last week the results of which were encouraging. Though it is too soon to tell, or to relate the scan to the latest drug regime, the results indicated that the cancerous mass had not grown (in contrast to the previous PET scan). We are once again hopeful that the cancer can be held back/ controlled. The MRI also provided incredible details of Sam’s upper body and the medical team will continue to review this latest set of images to evaluate future treatment options.</p>
</section>
<section id="looking-forward" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-forward">Looking forward</h2>
<p>It is hard to believe, but a pattern to life may be starting to emerge. We have learned (along with every oncology family we know) that we must be cautious in having plans as anything or everything can change at anytime. However, we are now starting to make plans with our medical team that extend beyond the next clinic visit. Given that Sam is tolerating the medications we are starting to look to the weeks ahead.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Sam will need to be in Vancouver every two weeks to receive the dose of Nivolumab.</li>
<li>Coupled with this approximately every four weeks he will have some sort of scan (likely alternating between PET and CT)</li>
</ol>
<p>Sam received his latest dose this past Friday and yesterday’s numbers looked good.</p>
<p>Given that there is nothing to do here in Vancouver until July 19, we plan to head for home tomorrow!</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam’s immune therapy plan is going forward. The medical team is keeping a close eye on Sam to ensure that he does not have any adverse side effects. Following two weeks of Nivolumab Sam has not had any adverse side effects!</p></li>
<li><p>Results from the July 4<sup>th</sup> MRI indicate that the cancer mass in Sam’s chest has not grown!</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that we can look ahead a little and that we can make it home again!</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2407/2024-07-09_mri-scan-results.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Moving forward</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2406/2024-06-28_moving-forward.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- ::: {.callout-note icon="false"}
## TL;DR [Too long didn't read (i.e. the short version)]{.small}

-   Sam's immunotherapy treatment has been delayed. We hope to see this
    treatment start by the end of this week.
-   GVHD effects have continued since Sam received his BMT. One effect
    of GVHD is that fluid has accumulated around his heart making it
    unsafe with other treatments until that is dealt with.
::: -->
<!-- ::: {#photo}
![On May 29^th^ we checked out of the Ronald McDonald House for the
first time since starting this cancer battle! We took a ten day break
home -- it was amazing to be
there!](https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-05-29_rmh-checkout.jpg)
::: -->
<p>Following a delay Sam’s treatment is now going forward.</p>
<p>Sam is on a new mix of medications that will hopefully slow the cancer and empower his immune system to attack the cancer. The two main immunotherapy drugs include:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.bccancer.bc.ca/drug-database-site/Drug%20Index/Nivolumab_monograph.pdf">Nivolumab</a> – is referred to as a check point inhibitor. Essentially, this drug disables a protein that allows the cancer cells to hide from the immune system. The downside is that it intensifies GVHD.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.bccancer.bc.ca/drug-database-site/Drug%20Index/Ruxolitinib_monograph.pdf">Ruxolitinib</a> – is being used to offset the impacts of GVHD. Some research suggests that this medication may also be synergistic with Nivolumab.</li>
</ul>
<p>We continue to be in Vancouver as Sam starts these treatments. We need to be sure that Sam can tolerate this new set of medications so potential adverse side effects are being monitored. The medical team also wants to keep a close eye on the cancer – a new scan of Sam’s chest is scheduled for next week (an MRI).</p>
<!-- ## Medical plans -->
<!-- ## Life together -->
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam’s immune therapy plan is going forward. The medical team is keeping a close eye on Sam to ensure that he does not have any adverse side effects.</p></li>
<li><p><del>We are concerned as cancer treatments have been delayed. The effects of GVHD caused fluid build-up around Sam’s heart making it unsafe to proceed with immunotherapy.</del></p></li>
<li><p>Results from the latest PET scan (June 12) are challenging. The cancer has grown. Though we remain thankful that it has not spread to other areas of Sam’s body.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for a great break at home and time to connect with friends and family! Thankful that Sam was able to connect with his friends and jump back into school work .</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the three new disease centers, treated using targeted radiation, have been removed (confirmed by April 5<sup>th</sup> PET scan).</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2406/2024-06-28_moving-forward.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Safety Delay</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2406/2024-06-19_safety-delay.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Immunotherapy Started!
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Today Sam was able to start his immune therapy.</p>
<p>It was safe to start as the fluid around Sam’s heart had decreased and his bloodwork confirmed an improvement in Sam’s liver numbers.</p>
<p>Now we wait.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Sam’s immunotherapy treatment has been delayed. We hope to see this treatment start by the end of this week.</li>
<li>GVHD effects have continued since Sam received his BMT. One effect of GVHD is that fluid has accumulated around his heart making it unsafe with other treatments until that is dealt with.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<!-- ::: {#photo}
![On May 29^th^ we checked out of the Ronald McDonald House for the
first time since starting this cancer battle! We took a ten day break
home -- it was amazing to be
there!](https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-05-29_rmh-checkout.jpg)
::: -->
<section id="medical-plans" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="medical-plans">Medical plans</h2>
<p>We had to know if Sam’s new immune system from the BMT would be able to stop the cancer – we now know that it cannot. The results of the June<sup>12th</sup> PET scan simply sucked – the cancer had grown, and likely spread into two lymph nodes close by.</p>
<p>So we pivot and move onto the next plan which will be a combination of different immunotherapy drugs. Past research suggest that these drugs could be effective at 1) interrupting a key metabolic pathway in the cancer cells, and 2) disable some of the cancer’s defenses that allow it to hide from the immune system.</p>
<p>Last Friday we were hoping to see Sam start on this modified immunotherapy drug treatment plan, but it was not safe to do so. Since receiving his BMT<sup>1</sup> Sam has had some level of GVHD<sup>2</sup>. One ongoing effect of GVHD is that fluid has built up around his heart (measured using an echocardiogram). To date this has not impacted his heart function. The challenge and safety concern is that the new immunotherapy treatment will likely intensify GVHD impacts that could put his heart at risk.</p>
<p>So instead of treating the cancer, last week Sam was started on a steroid to reduce GVHD effects. Yesterday, a repeat echocardiogram and blood metrics suggest that this GVHD treatment is working and this should allow Sam to start on the immunetherapy/cancer-treatment later this week.</p>
</section>
<section id="life-together" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="life-together">Life together</h2>
<p>We have all had our moments this past week. It has been emotionally challenging and at times each of us has had to confront our fears. We have also had beautiful times as we have been able to do that together.</p>
<p>We have received many notes of support and encouragement – thank you!</p>
<p>We have also enjoyed watching the hockey playoffs with family in the area. Uncle Cal also did his faithful visit after teaching in Richmond.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are concerned as cancer treatments have been delayed. The effects of GVHD caused fluid build-up around Sam’s heart making it unsafe to proceed with immunotherapy.<br>
At the same time we are thankful that Sam’s medical team continues to be diligent and thorough to protect him and to bring him to a healthier/safer place before starting this next treatment.</p></li>
<li><p>Results from the latest PET scan are challenging. The cancer has grown. Though we remain thankful that it has not spread to other areas of Sam’s body.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for a great break at home and time to connect with friends and family! Thankful that Sam was able to connect with his friends and jump back into school work .</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the three new disease centers, treated using targeted radiation, have been removed (confirmed by April 5<sup>th</sup> PET scan).</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>bone marrow transplant – providing his new immune system↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>graft versus host disease↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2406/2024-06-19_safety-delay.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Unfavourable Results</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2406/2024-06-14_unfavourable-results.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- ::: {.callout-note icon="false"}
## TL;DR [Too long didn't read (i.e. the short version)]{.small}



::: -->
<!-- ::: {#photo}
![On May 29^th^ we checked out of the Ronald McDonald House for the
first time since starting this cancer battle! We took a ten day break
home -- it was amazing to be
there!](https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-05-29_rmh-checkout.jpg)
::: -->
<p>Two days ago, Wednesday June 12, Sam had his latest PET scan. Yesterday afternoon the three of us met with Sam’s doctor to review the results.</p>
<p>The results are unfavourable – they are not what we want. Sam is still in the fight and there are still medical options to pursue. So, despite taking a hit, we hold hope and prepare for the next steps.</p>
<section id="results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results">Results</h2>
<p>The latest scan showed growth of the central mass in Sam’s chest. The cancer has expanded, it is not by a lot but it is distinct and beyond any possible measurement errors. In addition, two lymph-nodes in close proximity to the cancer show increased activity – we have to assume that the disease is now there as well.</p>
</section>
<section id="plans" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="plans">Plans</h2>
<p>The last few weeks have been a test to determine if Sam’s new immune system could battle the cancer on its own. Unfortunately, this test failed. During that time Sam has also had some of his best living. We were able to be home and he was able to enjoy his life, time with friends, and time learning at school.</p>
<p>Moving forward, Sam’s treatment plan will involve the re-introduction of some immune-therapy drugs. Nivomulab is an check-point-inhibitor will be given at a lower dose than previous. Other medications will be introduced in an attempt to reduce the more intense graft-versus-host impacts that Nivomulab has caused in the past.</p>
<p>Sam will also be closely monitored utilizing an alternating schedule of contrast-CT and PET scans.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Results from the latest PET scan are challenging. The cancer has grown. Though we remain thankful that it has not spread to other areas of Sam’s body.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for a great break at home and time to connect with friends and family! Thankful that Sam was able to connect with his friends and jump back into school work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the three new disease centers, treated using targeted radiation, have been removed (confirmed by April 5<sup>th</sup> PET scan).</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2406/2024-06-14_unfavourable-results.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>We have had a real break</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2406/2024-06-11_real-break.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Liver numbers were good, giving us a ‘green-light’ to go home</li>
<li>We made it home for ten days</li>
<li>Sam lived life to the fullest with the time and energy he had!</li>
<li>We are now back in Vancouver for planned scans</li>
<li>Next steps all depend on PET scan tomorrow</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div id="photo">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-05-29_rmh-checkout.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>On May 29<sup>th</sup> we checked out of the Ronald McDonald House for the first time since starting this cancer battle! We took a ten day break home – it was amazing to be there!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>It has been just over two weeks since my last post and in that time we have had an amazing break!</p>
<section id="current-medical-situation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="current-medical-situation">Current medical situation</h2>
<p>Two weeks ago Sam’s regular blood work confirmed that his liver numbers were continuing to drop. This allowed us to continue to test if his new immune system would be effective, on its own, to battle the cancer. Sam was off all immune system suppressants for just over three weeks (May 15 - June 6). However, bloodwork at the Prince George clinic showed that liver inflammation was starting again. This past Friday Sam started on a lower dose of immune suppressant in an attempt to find a balance of allowing the immune system to do its work while protecting his liver.</p>
<p>Currently, we are near the end of this wait-and-see period with a PET scan scheduled for tomorrow.</p>
<p>The earlier improved liver enzyme numbers, coupled with the results of the previous CT scan, also meant that we had what the medical team considered a safe window of time to return home! On May 29 we checked out of the Ronald McDonald House and made the drive back to Prince George! It was an amazing break!</p>
</section>
<section id="living-life" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="living-life">Living life</h2>
<p>I can’t express how good it was to get back home – to be in our own space, and to connect with some of our Prince George friends and family (though not near enough time to see everyone). We spent the first couple of days at my parents home where it was great to see them and for Sam to be reunited with Buddy. After a couple of days our own home was ready to return to.</p>
<p>During this break it was most encouraging for me to simply watch our boy! He loved being home and jumped full into life there:</p>
<ul>
<li>Sam loved connecting with friends.</li>
<li>He chose to jump right back into school despite having missed the last third of grade 9 and almost all of grade 10. Many thanks to the staff and students at <a href="https://cedars.bc.ca">Cedars</a> who welcomed Sam back in and allowed him to engage with his academics.</li>
<li>He pushed hard to catch up on a couple topics often spending 2-3 hours a day on homework. … Honestly he had seemed to have more energy than I did.</li>
<li>This last Friday, after writing a three hour math test during the day, Sam even attended the school dance. His muscles are still sore from having had a great time with friends and dancing the evening away!</li>
</ul>
<p>Tina and I were able to connect with various friends. So good to see you and we look forward to our next return!</p>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>We are now back at the RMH having finished our latest drive down yesterday. Tomorrow morning Sam will have a PET Scan at the BC Cancer clinic. Preliminary results may be available in clinic that afternoon though the full report may have to wait until Friday. Results of this scan will dictate next steps. If the results are positive then we can proceed with our preferred treatment option: to simply keep doing what we have been doing over the last number of weeks – let the immune system do its work and wait-and-see. If results are more challenging we will discuss options with the team here at BC Children’s.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for a great break at home and time to connect with friends and family! Thankful that Sam was able to connect with his friends and jump back into school work.</p></li>
<li><p>We celebrate that the cancer has not shown any significant signs of growth/progress since Feb.&nbsp;14<sup>th</sup>. A PET scan tomorrow, June 12, will reveal the current state of the cancer. Scan days always carry some stress.</p></li>
<li><p>We celebrate that Sam was able to be off immune suppression for over three weeks. Recently, his liver started to become inflamed again. He is currently on a lower dose of immune suppression with the hope of finding a balance of protecting his liver while allowing the immune system to attack the cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the three new disease centers, treated using targeted radiation, have been removed (confirmed by April 5<sup>th</sup> PET scan).</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2406/2024-06-11_real-break.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-05-29_rmh-checkout.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Living with Cancer</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2405/2024-05-24_immune-system-only.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Cancer has not progressed – no detectable change.</li>
<li>Sam is now off all immune suppression.</li>
<li>Great family memories.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="video">
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5-HwgeE7x5I" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<div class="figure-caption">
<p>Sam was selected to be a <a href="https://community.canucks.com/beneficiaries/">Canucks for Kids</a> Superfan. We had an amazing time at this game and it was great to see this win. Vancouver did an amazing job in the series. Sam has followed the Canucks closely during his cancer journey, and as they battled and exceeded expectations, so did he. Sam’s battle continues and we will look forward to seeing how Vancouver does next year. Additional photos are linked <a href="https://photos.app.goo.gl/skYyJU64bVu3uUpX9">here</a></p>
</div>
</div>
<p>The last two weeks have been a whirlwind. Key highlights included: attending game 5 of the Vancouver versus Edmonton series, a CT Scan, and regular bloodwork, a new bike for Colin, some family visits, and all the regular clinic check-ins.</p>
<section id="current-medical-situation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="current-medical-situation">Current medical situation</h2>
<p>Over the last two months we have been most concerned about getting Sam’s liver inflammation under control. There have been various medicines used in this. The meds likely helped, but perhaps what was also needed was simply time. Sam’s liver numbers have settled into a safe range and he is now off all immune suppression medications. This is great as, for the first time, his new immune system is able to fight the cancer without the influence of other medications.</p>
<p>The challenge is knowing if relying on Sam’s new immune system will be enough – will it be effective? In an attempt to answer that, last week Sam had a contrast CT of his chest, one week of being off immune suppression, and he will be scheduled for additional CT scans in the weeks ahead. He will also continue with regular PET scans to ensure that the cancer has not moved to new locations in his body. The great news is that there has been no detectable significant change in the size of the cancerous mass<sup>1</sup>. The last known change in the disease centre was between Feb.&nbsp;14 and April 5.</p>
<p>For Sam the downside of being off immunosuppression is that symptoms of Graft Versus Host Disease (GVHD) have started to return. However, he knows that these pains most likely mean that the cancer is also being fought. I don’t know if it will stick but our current motto is:</p>
<div class="center">
<p><em>Bring on the pain, kill the cancer, live life!!</em></p>
</div>
<p>To sum-up the current situation – Sam is now in a wait-and-see period. Our hope is that his immune system will, at minimum, hold the cancer back, and at best remove it. We are thrilled that it seems the cancer has not progressed. We are hopeful that the current plan could finally work. We also fear that the cancer will change and develop again. So now we wait and we try to live life with, and in spite of cancer.</p>
<p>Moving forward we will continue with Sam’s regular bloodwork and every few weeks complete further scans (CT and/or PET scans).</p>
</section>
<section id="living-life-together" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="living-life-together">Living life together</h2>
<p>The pictures above highlight one amazing evening that we had as a family. We have also been able to spend some time with the Fricker family and Nana Mary with visits at their place as well as here at the RMH.</p>
<p>I have been taking time to be refreshed riding my new bike thanks to a recent specified generous donation<sup>2</sup>! There are so many to thank for their support. Please know that all of your gifts are so appreciated. This journey is hard and I do not know how much harder it would be without the support, financial and otherwise, that we have received.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We celebrate that the cancer has not shown any significant signs of growth/progress since Feb.&nbsp;14<sup>th</sup>.</p></li>
<li><p>We celebrate that Sam is not longer on any immunosuppression and that his liver numbers have stabilized.</p></li>
<li><p>The minor challenge to being off immune suppression is that symptoms of GVHD have returned. General itchiness and GI sores.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the three new disease centers, treated using targeted radiation, have been removed.</p></li>
<li><p><del>Ongoing immune therapy has deregulated Sam’s immune system. Side-effects were becoming dangerous as Sam’s liver is inflamed. In order to continue with the immune therapy drugs, Sam’s immune system needs to be brought back to a regulated state. Recent bloodwork suggests that things are returning to normal function.</del></p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>The cancerous mass is actually very heterogeneous. Remembering back to early November targeted radiation had been used on the area. As a result, what we have now is a mass that is mix of healthy, dead, calcified, and cancerous/diseased tissues.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>This gift was given in response to my other bike being stolen↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2405/2024-05-24_immune-system-only.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-05-24_canucks-jumbotron.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scan results</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2405/2024-05-12_PET-results.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>PET Scan Results – Celebrating no new sites. Concern remains as disease continues at the original site.</li>
<li>Liver numbers are continuing in the right direction.</li>
<li>Next steps include a couple options with no clear right choice.</li>
<li>We have been able to enjoy life together.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div id="photo">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-05-12_mothers-day.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Happy Mothers Day Tina! You are an amazing mother! We love you!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<section id="current-medical-picture" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="current-medical-picture">Current medical picture</h2>
<p>This past Wednesday Sam had his most recent PET scan. Scan days are always stressful. Our experience with this type of stress is not unique. Talking with other parents, we all recognize that scan days and at minimum the day leading up to them are intense. It is weird because the scans do not change anything, but what they do is reveal what is happening. They cause use to confront all that we hope for and all that we fear. To add to this, the results from the scan often do not align with either our hopes or the fears that we try to prepare ourselves for. This dissonance, just adds to the stress of it all.</p>
<p>The results of this last scan, like many others, has mixed news.</p>
<section id="cancer-status" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cancer-status">Cancer status</h3>
<p>The good news is that since Feb 5<sup>th</sup> there are no new disease sites.</p>
<p>The difficult news is that the site in the center of Sam’s chest remains and has grown a small amount. The previous scan, April 5, showed no detectable change at that site and so to have this new growth strongly suggests that the cancer is active there. Options for treatment are limited and it is unknown if they will be effective.</p>
</section>
<section id="liver-status" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="liver-status">Liver status</h3>
<p>The previous PET scan raised concern that a more metabolically active site in Sam’s liver could be cancer. This has been ruled out via biopsy. We have known for sometime that Sam’s liver has been stressed due to side-effects of his immune therapy treatment causing his immune system to become deregulated. Latest metrics of Sam’s liver health have been improving. Recent ultrasound of the liver shows a minor increase in size. The Doctors want to continue monitoring this mass as it is not an urgent priority right now.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="next-steps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next steps</h2>
<p>We are in a hard place with two potential options for treatment – it is not known which is best or if either will be effective.</p>
<section id="option-1-rely-on-the-new-immune-system" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="option-1-rely-on-the-new-immune-system">Option 1: Rely on the new immune system</h3>
<p>Sam’s new immune system is fairly well established (although not completely until about one year after the bone marrow transplant). To date we have not had the opportunity to see what it can do. The previous treatments had side-effects that required steroids to calm/ suppress his immune system so that permanent liver damage could be avoided. If he was taken off the immunosupressants and just let his own (new) immune system work, this option would allow Sam to live and enjoy his life without medications and risk of side-effects. However, we do not know if his new immune system will effectively battle the cancer.</p>
<!-- and there is no way of
measuring effectiveness in a timely manner (ie. cannot have another PET
scan for 6 weeks, and that is too much time to risk the cancer growing).-->
</section>
<section id="option-2-resume-immune-therapy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="option-2-resume-immune-therapy">Option 2: Resume immune therapy</h3>
<p>This option would require the use of Nivomulab (an immune therapy drug) again. We know that this drug can make the cancer in Sam’s body ‘visible’ to the immune system. However, this is also the drug that resulted in Sam’s liver being inflamed and the subsequent need for steroids to calm the immune system (Catch-22). If we go this route, the team would use the lessons learned from last time to modify their therapy plan in an attempt to limit side-effects.</p>
<ul>
<li>If side-effects can be avoided, this will likely be the more effective treatment.</li>
<li>If side-effects cannot be avoided, this treatment could cause permanent harm (eg. the risk of liver failure).</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="life-together" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="life-together">Life together</h2>
<p>Despite all of the challenges and the ongoing threat to Sam’s life, we have been able to enjoy life as a family. The cancer aside, Sam is healthy, regaining weight, growing, and getting stronger.</p>
<p>In the last couple of weeks we have been instituting Sam’s <em>foodie-rehab</em> plan. This is where we walk from RMH to the small mall at Oak and King Edward. Once there, Sam has been enjoying most items at Kim’s Express (Vietnamese food). One evening Sam led our family for a larger walk, one that I did not know he was capable of, down to Cambie Village about 1.5kms away. We had some great ice cream before walking back. This was an epic evening for our family.</p>
<p>Over this past weekend we were able to join some of the Frickers and the Townsend side of the family to experience the animals at Aldor Farms near Ft. Langley. I loved watching Sam take some time to groom Rob, a huge Percheron work horse.</p>
<p>Yesterday, we celebrated Mothers Day. Ronald McDonald House put on a beautiful brunch. In the evening, we took in the Canucks vs.&nbsp;Oilers hockey game (which Sam mostly slept through due to being tired from his big farm day Saturday).</p>
<!-- \
Tina and I want to express a special thank you to all of you who have
sent funds to assist us in this journey. This extra funding is allowing
us to simply live and enjoy life, meals, and activities together without
needing to worry about a budget. -->
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We celebrate that a year following the start of all his varied treatments, and despite the ongoing cancer battle, Sam is feeling the best he has felt in a long time.</p></li>
<li><p>We are very concerned as the original central mass/ disease center is active.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the three new disease centers, treated using targeted radiation, have been removed.</p></li>
<li><p>Ongoing immune therapy has deregulated Sam’s immune system. Side-effects were becoming dangerous as Sam’s liver is inflamed. In order to continue with the immune therapy drugs, Sam’s immune system needs to be brought back to a regulated state. Recent bloodwork suggests that things are returning to normal function.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2405/2024-05-12_PET-results.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-05-12_mothers-day.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Holding Pattern – Waiting</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2405/2024-05-05_waiting.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
::: {.callout-note icon="false"}
## TL;DR [Too long didn't read (i.e. the short version)]{.small}
::: -->
<p>It has been ten days since we returned to Vancouver. Life has been fairly routine, even slow. We have we been checking in with the hospital clinic and so far the metrics associated with Sam’s liver numbers are going the right direction. This suggests that the liver is healing/ becoming less inflamed.</p>
<p>This week we have a few items on the agenda: a) Clinic check-ins; b) Ultrasound of the liver to verify that the non-cancerous mass there is either stable or improving; and c) PET scan (possibly). The PET scan is the big item as it will show us the status of the cancer in Sam’s body. Results of the PET will also strongly inform Sam’s next treatment(s).</p>
<p>This journey has been long and we are tired. This past weekend family facilitated giving me a break. Tina and Sam stayed with Mary and the Fricker family (Tina’s sister’s family) giving me almost 24 hours off. It was great to have that time without responsibilities.</p>
<p>Sam remains positive and continues to get stronger. Tina and I are glad to see this. However, we cannot escape feelings of needing-to-be-vigilant and anxiousness about what could be happening undetected – the results of the PET scan this week will be very helpful.</p>
<!-- 
::: {#photo}
![Sam was a great copilot in our journeys north and then south](https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-04-21_road-trip.jpg)
::: -->
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We celebrate that we were able to have a trip home. So good to connect with friends and family!</p></li>
<li><p>We celebrate that a year following the start of treatment, Sam is feeling the best he has ever felt.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the original central mass is stable. Thankful that three disease centers, treated using targeted radiation, have been removed.</p></li>
<li><p>Ongoing immune therapy has de-regulated Sam’s immune system. Side effects are becoming dangerous as Sam’s liver is inflamed. In order to continue with the immune therapy drugs, Sam’s immune system needs to be brought back to a regulated state. Recent bloodwork suggests that things are returning to normal function.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2405/2024-05-05_waiting.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Break at Home!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-25_first-break-home.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
::: {.callout-note icon="false"}
## TL;DR [Too long didn't read (i.e. the short version)]{.small}
::: -->
<div id="photo">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-04-21_road-trip.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Sam was a great copilot in our journeys north and then south</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>It has been a whirlwind trip back home. We connected with more people than we expected and yet missed too many of you. I hope you can forgive us if you were missed – we really have more love than we had time. Three days in the city was not enough but we were glad for it! It was also incredible to re-connect, even if just in-part, with the community that has been supporting us.</p>
<section id="travel-log" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="travel-log">Travel log</h2>
<p>The initial idea to travel was presented last Wednesday, April 17. However, actual travel plans were dependent on metrics on Sam’s bloodwork that would allow the medical team to decide if it would be safe for Sam to travel. Specifically, if Sam’s numbers were not good on the Friday, we check again on the Monday, and if they were not good then the trip would be cancelled. So to keep things flexible we chose to drive. As a family we have always done road trips and Sam was looking forward to this pilgrimage drive home.</p>
<section id="day-1-travel" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-1-travel">Day 1 – Travel</h3>
<p><em>Sunday, April 21</em></p>
<p>We got away from Vancouver at a good time. It was a cool cloudy day with some showers heading into the Fraser Canyon. We had a great early lunch at Horsting’s Farm near Cache Creek. In the afternoon we stopped to see Renee near Williams Lake. Refreshed and fed we travelled on arriving at my parents as the sun was setting.</p>
<p>We received a loving welcome from Mom and Dad and all of us loved seeing Sam reconnect with Buddy – his dog was crazy excited to see him! We were also able to catch the last two periods of the first Vancouver vs. Nashville playoff game.</p>
</section>
<section id="day-2-family" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-2-family">Day 2 – Family</h3>
<p><em>Monday</em></p>
<p>This was really the only day that we had any sort of plan which was to make family our priority. The earlier part of the day was spent with my parents and the evening with Tom, Margaret, Daniel and Alex. Good times connecting, talking, and playing games together.</p>
</section>
<section id="day-3-school" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-3-school">Day 3 – School</h3>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="2">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div id="photo2" class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-04-23_school-friends_x.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Sam loved reconnecting with his friends at school and later at youth group!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div id="Tuesday" class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<p><em>Tuesday</em></p>
<p>We let this day be driven by Sam and how he was feeling – he was feeling good. Mid-morning Sam had a great idea of visiting his friends at school over the lunch break. It was so good to see him simply slip into life at the school. We ended up spending the entire afternoon there as Sam joined in to classes. Tina and I connected with staff and a number of friends as parents rolled in for afterschool pickup.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- The evening was spent at Mom and Dads -- Dave and Ben joined to watch hockey. -->
</section>
<section id="day-4-whirlwind" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-4-whirlwind">Day 4 – Whirlwind</h3>
<p><em>Wednesday</em></p>
<p>Wednesday was more of a whirlwind. Sam had an appointment at the hospital pediatric clinic. This was our first connection with the Prince George team. Although they do not specialize in cancer treatment it was good to see how much ca be taken care of at the hospital back home. In the afternoon we squeezed in some visits with friends and dinner with the grandparents. In the evening Sam was able to attend youth group at the church!</p>
<!-- - Breakfast with Brian -->
<!-- - Medical team visit (I)
- Sam visited with Chase and Ben, while Tina had a quick visit with Joanna I ran out and got food for Sam (prednisone / 15-year-old Sam is always hungry)
- Tina had coffee with Jesse and Aria 
- Sam and I returned to the hospital clinic (II) to review labwork -- which was looking good
- Sam and I ran a couple errands and then returned to Mom and Dad's for dinner
- I ran out to get Edo Japan for Sam, Mom, and I. 
- Ran Sam to youth group
- Ran Tina to visit Sengas
- An hour at our house 
- Picked up Sam from youth group -->
</section>
<section id="day-5-return-to-vancouver" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-5-return-to-vancouver">Day 5 – Return to Vancouver</h3>
<p><em>Thursday</em></p>
<p>We had to head back to Vancouver. It was a great road trip. Sam is looking forward to the day when he can be the driver. In the meantime he watched the road and acted as a good copilot.</p>
<p>It was a great first trip home and hopefully our next one will be in the near future and with more days at home.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="next-steps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next Steps</h2>
<p>In the weeks ahead we are hoping to restart Sam’s immune therapy. This has been delayed as we wait for his immune system to come under control – bloodwork in Prince George suggested that Sam is headed in the right direction. Additionally, he will likely have another PET scan which will hopefully reveal good progress in this ongoing cancer battle.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We celebrate that we were able to have a trip home. So good to connect with friends and family!</p></li>
<li><p>We celebrate that a year following the start of treatment, Sam is feeling the best he has ever felt. We are incredibly grateful.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the original central mass is stable. Thankful that three disease centers, treated using targeted radiation, have been removed.</p></li>
<li><p>Ongoing immune therapy has de-regulated Sam’s immune system. Side effects are becoming dangerous as Sam’s liver is inflamed. In order to continue with the immune therapy drugs, Sam’s immune system needs to be brought back to a regulated state. Recent bloodwork suggests that things are returning to normal function.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-25_first-break-home.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-04-21_road-trip.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Happy Anniversary –Celebration!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-18_one-year.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>One year at BCCH</li>
<li>Gratitude for all of the support and care</li>
<li>Celebrating that the cancer is stable and more so that Sam is feeling good</li>
<li>A year in review – milestones of this journey</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div id="photo">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-04_chisholms-spring.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Enjoying a spring walk together. This photo was taken on Easter Monday and was Sam’s biggest walk in over a year.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>It has taken me <del>three</del> four days to write this post. Sam has had such great energy lately. He has been waking up at the same time as me and we have spent our days together – talking, playing, reading, and even sharing the chores.</p>
<p>In the early morning just over a year ago, on April 18, 2023, Sam arrived at BC Children’s hospital. Oh, how far he as come along this incredible journey of seeing him return to health. He is by no means out-of-the-woods yet, but now he can “walk-in-the-woods” with us. Sam is joyful, he has increasing energy and stamina, and his courageous attitude seems to have no limits.</p>
<p>One year ago Tina and Sam had been sent down by air ambulance and were admitted directly to the Pediatric Intensive Care Unit (PICU). I arrived about twelve hours later. Sam remained in PICU for the next number of days while the medical team stabilized him, and initial imaging and biopsies were completed. It would be 10 days later that the biopsy reports were completed and Sam’s cancer was identified. Once identified, we knew we would be travelling a challenging road – one that was not mapped by any procedures or protocols that the medical team could follow.</p>
<section id="gratitude" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gratitude">Gratitude</h2>
<p>We have so much to be grateful for throughout this journey (in no way is this quick list complete).</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam has received incredible medical care at the BC Childrens’ Hospital and BC Cancer Centre</p>
<ul>
<li>The doctors have pooled their collective expertise having to make untold numbers of decisions based on their professional judgement and not just established protocols.</li>
<li>The nurses on the oncology ward and later in clinic have shown Sam (and his parents) incredible care. We will forever treasure the compassion and personal connections that we have had all of you.</li>
<li>Access to incredible tools used to diagnose and accurately locate the disease in Sam, and all of the diligent technicians and radiologists.</li>
<li>All of the support staff, seen and unseen, that have made Sam’s care possible</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>A stranger who provided Sam a new immune system.</p></li>
<li><p>Incredible charities that have supported us</p>
<ul>
<li>The Ronald McDonald House has provided us a home away from home.</li>
<li>Canuck Place has advised on Sam’s care and provided great counsel for Tina and I.</li>
<li>Friends of Children provides assistance to families from northern BC</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>The love of friends and family supporting us. We treasure your visits and communications.</p></li>
<li><p>The hundreds of people praying and caring for Sam – thank you.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="celebration-despite-ambiguity" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="celebration-despite-ambiguity">Celebration despite ambiguity</h2>
<p>There is so much unknown. We know that Sam’s cancer remains. It is unknown if the treatments he has ongoing will be wholly effective.</p>
<p>Despite this ambiguity we celebrate! Currently, Sam is doing well. The last PET scan on April 5<sup>th</sup> suggests that Sam’s cancer has been stable! The central mass remains but has not grown and the immune system has been actively working there. The three disease centres found earlier have been neutralized.</p>
<p>More than the state of the cancer, we celebrate that Sam is feeling good! He is gaining strength. He is active and enjoying life!</p>
<p>There is much work to be done but for the time being it seems we are winning – I pray that this is true and continues to be true.</p>
</section>
<section id="major-milestones" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="major-milestones">Major Milestones</h2>
<p>What a journey this has been. Sam has been through three eras of cancer treatment: 1) chemotherapy, 2) BMT, and now 3) immune therapy. Radiation was given both before the BMT and also concurrent with immunotherapy. Below is provided a quick review of the major milestones.</p>
<section id="chemotherapy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="chemotherapy">Chemotherapy</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 20%">
<col style="width: 41%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Date</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>2023</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>April 17</td>
<td>An alarming x-ray in Prince George provided evidence that Sam needed urgent care at BCCH.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>April 18</td>
<td>Air Ambulance in the early morning and admission to BCCH’s PICU.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>April 22</td>
<td>Transfer to BCCH Oncology Ward (T8).</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>April 28</td>
<td>Diagnosis of a extremely rare form of lymphoma.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>April 29</td>
<td>Chemotherapy is initiated. Sam will receive an additional 6 full rounds of chemotherapy taking him into October.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>June 2</td>
<td>Following his second round of chemotherapy Sam was discharged from the hospital for the first time. This marks the beginning of our family life at RMH. The next months we would visit the oncology clinic regularly. When it was time for each round of chemotherapy we would check into the ward for about 5 days.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>July 14</td>
<td>Plans for a bone marrow transplant were initiated. By mid-summer it became apparent that the chemotherapy would not remove all of the cancer. The remaining rounds of chemotherapy would reduce the cancer as much as possible, and keep it from spreading to new locations, while the BMT was being organized.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Sept.&nbsp;26</td>
<td>Preparations for BMT, baseline testing of Sam was initiated to evaluate impacts of the BMT (i.e.&nbsp;eye, ear, skin, and lung capacity testing).</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Oct.&nbsp;15</td>
<td>Sam completed his final round of chemotherapy.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Oct.&nbsp;23</td>
<td>Targeted radiation therapy over three days to destroy the central mass in Sam’s chest is initiated. This was completed at the BC Cancer Centre over 10 days.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Nov.&nbsp;8</td>
<td>Total body radiation is used to completely remove Sam’s existing immune system – to kill the blood producing cells in his bone marrow. This was done to make way for the bone marrow transplant.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="bone-marrow-transplant" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bone-marrow-transplant">Bone Marrow Transplant</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 20%">
<col style="width: 37%">
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Nov.&nbsp;14</td>
<td>Bone marrow transplant is received. Sam had been admitted to the oncology ward a few days prior in preparation and would remain on ward in isolation for the next number of weeks. This was a particularly intense time as the medical team had to provide so many supports to his body</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Nov.&nbsp;25</td>
<td>First indications that the BMT was establishing – engraftment. Official engraftment would be established on Dec.&nbsp;1 based on metrics from Sam’s blood.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Dec.&nbsp;13</td>
<td>Sam is discharged from the hospital with plans to continue regular check-ins at the oncology clinic.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>2024</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Jan.&nbsp;11</td>
<td>Stepping down from all of the various medications had its challenges. Sam was admitted to the ward for eight days to determine what was causing his extreme lethargy. It was a complicated picture as we all had a flu in the days prior but what Sam was experiencing was more. In the end the main issue seemed to be adrenal insufficiency.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="immune-therapy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="immune-therapy">Immune therapy</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 22%">
<col style="width: 40%">
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Feb.&nbsp;14</td>
<td>PET scan, that we were all hoping to be Sam’s last before having to go home, revealed a horror – the cancer had spread to three new locations. New battle strategies are brought into play. Plans to return home are canceled.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Feb.&nbsp;29</td>
<td>Sam receives his first dose of Nivomulab used to intentionally de-regulate Sam’s immune system and to turn off specific protein markers on the cancer cells that allow them to hide from the immune system.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>March 11</td>
<td>Targeted radiation starts against the three new sites. The shin and hip sites would see higher doses over four days. The T3-vertebrae would see lower daily radiation doses over ten days.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>April 5</td>
<td>PET scan demonstrated that: a) The three new disease sites had been effectively killed using radiation, b) the central mass was stable c) However, a new site in Sam’s liver raised new alarm bells.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>April 11</td>
<td>Biopsy of the liver revealed that this mass is not Sam’s original cancer but an indistinct mass that will be monitored.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We celebrate that a year following the start of treatment, Sam is feeling the best he has ever felt. We are incredibly grateful.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the original central mass is stable. Thankful that three disease centers, treated using targeted radiation, have been removed.</p></li>
<li><p>The newest growth in Sam’s liver is not the original cancer though it will be monitored.</p></li>
<li><p>Ongoing immune therapy has de-regulated Sam’s immune system. Side effects are becoming dangerous as Sam’s liver is inflamed. In order to continue with the immune therapy drugs, Sam’s immune system needs to be brought back to a regulated state.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-18_one-year.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-04_chisholms-spring.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Catch-22, Biopsy Results</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-16_catch22.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-caution callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
April 18 – Strike out inaccuracies
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>In clinic yesterday, April 17, some of the medical strategies and understandings of Sam’s ongoing treatments were changed.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Primarily, a lower priority is being placed on the mass in Sam’s liver. This tissue is thought to be benign and <em>not</em> the source of stress to his liver.</li>
<li>The source of stress to Sam’s liver is now believed to related to his immune system continuing to run out of control. The use of steroids to bring the immune system in-check has not wholly been effective. New drug therapies have been initiated.</li>
</ol>
<p>I have edited the post below – striking out what is no longer believed to be accurate. <em>New additions are italicized</em>.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Initial biopsy results are complicated.<br>
</li>
<li>The new growth/tumour in Sam’s liver is not the original cancer – what it is, is still being determined.</li>
<li><del>This new spot does need to be treated.</del> The new spot will be monitored but is now thought to be benign.</li>
<li>The main method of treatment for <del>this new growth</del> <em>the immune system running at de-regulated/higher levels</em> is in conflict with ongoing cancer treatment.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<p>Sam and I are up early this morning in anticipation of an ultrasound appointment to image Sam’s liver. It is so nice to chat with my boy in the mornings. His energy has continued to improve over the last 10 days. He does not need to sleep as much and he is able to walk most places now and we are rarely using the wheelchair to transport him around.</p>
<section id="cancer-war" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cancer-war">Cancer war</h2>
<p>Below I attempt to convey the latest biopsy results and what this means for Sam’s cancer treatment. I suggest taking it slow. The picture is complicated as we now how two issues to resolve – the liver, and the cancer.</p>
<section id="initial-biopsy-results" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="initial-biopsy-results">Initial biopsy results</h3>
<p>Last Wednesday, Sam had a biopsy of his a growth in his liver, and yesterday we received some preliminary results. The good news is that this new growth is not Sam’s original cancer! However, we do not yet know definitively what it is – that will need to wait for the full report. <del>What we do know is that this growth is likely a source of dangerous agitation of Sam’s liver, and that it needs to be treated</del>. <em>It is now believed that the source of ongoing agitation to the liver is the on-going de-regulation of Sam’s immune system … effectively GVHD though it can be debated if this is the right term.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="treatment" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="treatment">Treatment</h3>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<dl>
<dt>Catch-22</dt>
<dd>
<p>… a dilemma or difficult circumstance from which there is no escape because of mutually conflicting or dependent conditions (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catch-22_(logic)">Wikipedia</a>)</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</blockquote>
</div>
</div>
<p>We are in ‘catch-22’ situation. The <del>new site in Sam’s liver</del> <em>immune system needs to be brought under control</em> as it is likely the major source of ongoing agitation to Sam’s liver. This is indicated in Sam’s regular bloodwork where various chemicals indicative of liver health and function are dangerously high. <del>The best chemical method for treating growths like this involve using steroids (i.e.&nbsp;Prednisone) – Sam is currently on these</del>. <em>Initial efforts to bring the immune system in-check used steroid (i.e.&nbsp;Prednisone). However, the steroids have shown themselves to only be partially effective and an alternate drug therapy has been initiated.</em></p>
<p>However, this steroidal treatment suppresses the immune system.</p>
<p>In the treatment of Sam’s cancer we have been using drugs to cause Sam’s immune system to be hyperactive (i.e.&nbsp;the opposite of suppressed). As such we are in a catch-22 situation. To treat the liver we must suppress the immune system, to treat the cancer we must make the immune system hyperactive<sup>1</sup>.</p>
<p><em>…Ughhh…</em></p>
<p>The imaging from this morning’s ultrasound, <em>April 16, suggested that the mass in the liver is stable and likely benign – it will be monitored but no further action is currently needed. Medical actions will focus on bringing the immune system under control.</em><del>should provide the medical team enough new information to determine how the current treatment is working and what alternate treatment options may exist.</del></p>
<p>I think what much of this comes down to may simply be timing.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Treat the liver quickly.</li>
<li>With the liver treated we can return to the immune therapy of the cancer.</li>
</ol>
<p>Once the liver agitation is resolved (or mostly resolved). We can return to managing Sam’s cancer.</p>
</section>
<section id="hope-and-anxiety" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hope-and-anxiety">Hope and anxiety</h3>
<dl>
<dt>Hope</dt>
<dd>
<p>If there is anything exciting from all of this it is that the new site is not Sam’s original cancer. This means that Sam’s cancer has been stable since the treatments following the PET scan back in February. This also means that the BMT-immune therapy treatment combination seems to be working.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Anxiety</dt>
<dd>
<p>In waiting for the liver <em>agitation</em> issue to be resolved we are delaying immune therapy treatments for the cancer. During this period it is possible that Sam’s original cancer could get going again.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
</section>
<section id="living-life" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="living-life">Living Life</h2>
<section id="friends-and-family" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friends-and-family">Friends and Family</h3>
<p>We had a good weekend. It has been great to see Sam with more energy and able to engage with people more. An upside of the current steroid treatment is that it has released Sam to have increased energy and we have seen more of chatty-Sam. We were also able to have some great visits. Brian and Hunter were here from Prince George. We were able to visit family and watch the Edmonton-Vancouver hockey game together. Nana Mary arrived yesterday and will stay with us for a few days.</p>
<!-- In the hours and days between clinic and family/friend visits Sam is devouring his latest novel, we haved enjoyed playing board games with other families here at the RMH, and playing some video games.  -->
<p>Sam remains courageous, hopeful, and generally joyful.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that the original central mass is stable. Thankful that three disease centers, treated using targeted radiation, have been removed.</p></li>
<li><p>The newest growth in Sam’s liver is not the original cancer! However, it needs to be treated in order to continue on with Sam’s cancer treatment.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam’s energy has increased!</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam’s pain levels have been stable and generally easy to manage.</p></li>
<li><p>The new immunotherapy drugs seems to have released Sam’s immune system to hit harder. As the immune system was starting to get out of control brakes have been able to slow the immune system back down. It is good to know that the chemical brakes work, at the same time we do not want to suppress the immune system too long as it is the main method of battling the cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>We mourn the loss of Dani – grieving in solidarity with her family.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>The cancer remains and has spread to new areas in Sam’s body. The sites are a mass in the center of his chest (the original), <del>and newer sites in his back (T3 vertebrae), his hip (right ilium), and left shin (tibia just below the knee).</del> Latest scan revealed a potential new site on Sam’s liver.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>It is not quite as simple as this… as the treatments are a not a 1:1 exchange, but alternate treatments do strongly impact each other.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-16_catch22.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Victories and challenges – we battle on</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-07_battles-won.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
April 11
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Sam came through the biopsy without any issues.</p>
<p>Now we have to wait for the pathology report to let us know what we are dealing with. Initial findings may be available before the weekend, but a full report may take 10 days.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>PET Scan with results this past Friday</li>
<li>Victories at several sites</li>
<li>Stability at the initial site</li>
<li>One new site under investigation</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<section id="cancer-war" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cancer-war">Cancer war</h2>
<p>Sam has summarized this the past two PET scans in the following way (parap hrased):</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The PET scan in February was like someone dumped a load of bricks on me.<br>
This last PET scan was like someone removed all the bricks but then threw a single one at me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sam is great spirits. As the impacts of radiation therapy are behind him, and the effects of GVHD<sup>1</sup> are lessening he is seeing his energy return. Today he wants to go grocery shopping with me.</p>
<section id="review" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="review">Review</h3>
<p>The previous PET, back on Feb 14, provided really hard news. Following months of seeing a new immune system be established in Sam (Nov.&nbsp;- Feb) that imaging showed three new disease sites – it seemed that all of the previous efforts were for naught and that we were losing the cancer war. Despite all of the efforts of the BMT to establishing a new immune system, it did not seem to be effective at beating back the cancer.</p>
<p>Since the discovery of the new sites Sam has received immunotherapy (via the drug Nivomulab) as well as targeted radiation treatment to the new disease centers. The radiation therapy was straight forward and ended a couple weeks ago. With the immune therapy Sam was only able to have a single dose of the Nivomulab which triggered more GVHD<sup>2</sup> than he had seen during his BMT<sup>3</sup>. Although this GVHD was not physically comfortable (e.g.&nbsp;hot rashes, GI<sup>4</sup> effects) it was mentally comforting – if the immune system was attacking healthy tissue it meant that it was most likely also attacking the cancer. Most recently, the immune system started getting dangerously out of control by stressing Sam’s liver. In response, he was started on some steroids to put the brakes on his immune system and bring it back in-check.</p>
<p>This sets the stage for the PET scan this past Friday (April 5).</p>
</section>
<section id="pet-scan-results" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pet-scan-results">PET scan results</h3>
<p><em>April 5<sup>th</sup> scan</em></p>
<section id="radiated-sites" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="radiated-sites">Radiated sites</h4>
<p>We have clear wins! No cancer was detectable in the three sites discovered back in Feb.&nbsp;The cancer in his T3 vertebrae, hip, and shin has been wiped out by the radiation therapy.</p>
</section>
<section id="central-mass" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="central-mass">Central mass</h4>
<p>The mass in the center of Sam’s chest, the one that brought us down here to start with, is stable. There is increased metabolic activity in the area but it remains the same size as previous – and potentially a little smaller. What is exciting about this is that the only thing keeping this site in-check would have been Sam’s immune system. The fact that this site is stable suggests that the immune system is able to battle whatever cancer is still in this area.</p>
</section>
<section id="challenges" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="challenges">Challenges</h4>
<p>A single new site has been located. The new site is located in Sam’s liver. For now we have to assume that this is new disease site (i.e.&nbsp;the same type of cancer in a new location). However, it is possible that is something else. The liver is a big organ, one that is hard to do surgery on, but this new site is superficial (near the surface) just below Sam’s lower rib on the right side. Given where this site is we are hoping that a biopsy can be completed this coming week.</p>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="living-life" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="living-life">Living Life</h2>
<section id="friends-and-family" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friends-and-family">Friends and Family</h3>
<p>Although not planned this way it was great to have my parents visit this weekend. Initial scheduling of the PET scan was not until next week. I am glad they were here to be with us – PET scans are often stressful. Nana Mary, Uncles Kevin and Cal were also able to come in the afternoon that we received the PET scan results.</p>
<p>Yesterday, Tina and I were able to visit with Brian, Beth, David, and Luke. A definitely highlight from that visit was seeing Sam have energy to talk with his friend!</p>
</section>
<section id="tragedy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tragedy">Tragedy</h3>
<p>Yesterday’s visits were filled with joy. But the day was also filled with sorrow. Our hearts break for R, and her whole family, as her daughter Dani passed away in the early morning. Dani had fought hard.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that three disease centers have been removed. Thankful that the original central mass is stable. We battle on to determine what the latest site is and how best to attack it.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam’s energy has increased!</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam’s pain levels have been stable and generally easy to manage.</p></li>
<li><p>The new immunotherapy drugs seems to have released Sam’s immune system to hit harder. As the immune system was starting to get out of control brakes have been able to slow the immune system back down. It is good to know that the chemical brakes work, at the same time we do not want to suppress the immune system too long as it is the main method of battling the cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>We mourn the loss of Dani – grieving in solidarity with her family.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>The cancer remains and has spread to new areas in Sam’s body. The sites are a mass in the center of his chest (the original), <del>and newer sites in his back (T3 vertebrae), his hip (right ilium), and left shin (tibia just below the knee).</del> Latest scan revealed a potential new site on Sam’s liver.</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Graft versus host disease↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Graft versus host disease↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Bone marrow transplant↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>gastrointestinal↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-07_battles-won.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Spring break(?)</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-02_spring-break.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Friends visit</li>
<li>Hockey games</li>
<li>Waiting for treatment</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="2">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div id="canucks" class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-03-28_us-canucks.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>We had a great time at the Canucks versus Stars game. Sam is loving his new jersey.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div id="friends" class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-03-26_sam-ben-chase.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>It was spring break and some of Sam’s friends were able to come and visit. Chase, Sam, and Ben have been friends since they were all four.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="recap" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recap">Recap</h2>
<section id="cancer-war" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cancer-war">Cancer war</h3>
<p>Generally, we are in a holding pattern. Radiation therapy wrapped up a week-and-a-half ago and seems to have gone well. No further immune therapy treatments have happened as we are waiting for Sam’s immune system to return to normal/safe levels. The initial treatment ramped-up Sam’s immune system, ideally to fight the cancer, but a side effect has been that the immune system is running on the edge of out-of-control causing graft versus host disease and agitating his liver. So we wait. At clinic yesterday, we changed meds to slow the immune system down/ bring it under control.</p>
<p>During this waiting period he have seen Sam generally been lethargic with some itchiness related to graft versus host disease. It is unclear what causes the lethargy in Sam, it could be effects of the radiation or immune therapy, it could be the disease, all of the above or something else … We do get glimpses of the real Sam full of energy and life. These times are encouraging though it is hard to watch him drop back to lethargy.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
April 4 addition
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>In the last 3-4 days Sam has had much better energy… I hope it continues.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Generally, we are in a very ambiguous situation – not knowing what is happening with the cancer or if the treatments are having the desired effects. Sam will have a PET scan tomorrow (Friday, April 5) which should give us a picture of where things are at.</p>
</section>
<section id="living-life-and-special-memories" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="living-life-and-special-memories">Living life and special memories</h3>
<p>The previous two weeks have been busy. In adddition to medical appointments we had good visits with friends, family, and we attended a couple hockey games.</p>
<section id="friends-and-family" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friends-and-family">Friends and family</h4>
<p>We have been encouraged by visits with friends. Most importantly – Sam’s friends. It was spring break for the schools and a few friends were able to visit during this time.</p>
<p>Chase came and stayed with us/Sam for a number of days. Ben, along with the rest of his family, was able to visit a couple different times. I am thankful that these boys were able see Sam when he was up and when he was down and simply accept him where he was at.</p>
<p>We also love the times we can connect with family, here at the RMH, at their homes, and at a hockey game.</p>
</section>
<section id="hockey" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hockey">Hockey</h4>
<p>Sam has really been enjoying hockey during this difficult period. He looks forward to watching games. Since I last wrote we were able to attend two.</p>
<p>First, we attended the WHL’s Vancouver Giants versus Kelowna Rockets. This was a special family time as we were gifted box seats to the game. Family including Cal, Tricia, Jane, and Nana Mary were able to meet the three of us plus Chase there.</p>
<p>This past Friday (Feb.&nbsp;29), The three of us were able to attend the Vancouver Canucks versus Dallas Stars game. We had a great time together! Sam enjoyed it so much and this will be a core memory for each of us. Although Vancouver lost it was a great hard-fought game and with a party atmosphere at the arena!</p>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>We will be at clinic 2-3 times this week. Sam will have a PET scan tomorrow (Friday, April 5).</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam’s energy and capacity for simple living have swung up and down over the last month. The majority of the time his energy is low but we do get glimpses of our real Sam full of energy and life.</p></li>
<li><p>The ambiguity of not knowing if treatments are working and delays in treatment are challenging – to the point of terrifying. We have managed the not-knowing well, but our reserves/defenses are drained/weakened.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam’s pain levels have been stable and generally easy to manage. The main challenges are related to the GVHD, specifically with rashes, which are not painful but are at times very itchy and hot.</p></li>
<li><p>The new immunotherapy drugs seems to have released Sam’s immune system to hit harder. Though we look forward to this pushing the cancer back, side effects of the new immune system attacking healthy tissues are also big concern (i.e.&nbsp;GVHD). Sam has had some adverse effects and we need to allow these to resolve before proceeding with new treatments.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Childrens’ Hospital</a> who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>The cancer remains and has spread to new areas in Sam’s body. The sites are a mass in the center of his chest (the original), and newer sites in his back (T3 vertebrae), his hip (right ilium), and left shin (tibia just below the knee).</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>new-sites</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2404/2024-04-02_spring-break.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2024-03-28_us-canucks.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Graft versus host</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2403/2024-03-19_gvhd.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Immune therapy treatment was initiated on Feb 29<sup>th</sup>. It took about 10 days before symptoms of Graft versus host disease started to present themselves. It is our hope that the Graft versus disease processes (i.e.&nbsp;destruction of cancer cells) is even stronger.</li>
<li>Targeted radiation therapy for the new disease sites, discovered on the Feb.&nbsp;14<sup>th</sup> PET scan, is ongoing and will be complete by the end of this week.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<section id="recap-of-the-last-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recap-of-the-last-week">Recap of the last week</h2>
<section id="cancer-war" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cancer-war">Cancer war</h3>
<p>It has been over a week since I last wrote and we have been continuing along two lines of attack against the cancer in Sam’s body.</p>
<dl>
<dt>Radiation Therapy</dt>
<dd>
<p>Each weekday we have made a trip down to the BC Cancer Centre, about a 10 minute drive away. Sam is/has undergone targeted radiation for the three new disease sites discovered last month. These visits are fairly quick with about 15 minutes needed per site and most of that time is simply setting up/positioning Sam to target the sites the same way each time. Last week treatment of the sites below his knee and on his hip were completed – as these were not near critical organs they received higher doses of radiation per treatment. Treatment of the disease on Sam’s back will be completed at the end of this week. Evaluation of how well the treatments worked will not be for a minimum of 2-3 weeks.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Immune therapy</dt>
<dd>
<p>Last Thursday, Sam was due to have another dose of <a href="http://www.bccancer.bc.ca/drug-database-site/Drug%20Index/Nivolumab_handout.pdf">Nivolumab</a> two weeks following his initial dose. However, this second dose was delayed as his bloodwork suggested that his liver was inflamed and as such it could be dangerous to give another dose. It was a good decision! Over this past weekend Sam has much stronger symptoms of Graft Versus Host Disease (GVHD) than we have seen the entire time since receiving his bone marrow transplant (BMT).</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>As a reminder, the intent of the BMT was to give Sam a new immune system that would recognize the cancer and destroy it. The weeks following the transplant Sam was on a medication to keep the new immune system in-check and reduce symptoms of GVHD. Now that we know that there is more cancer, steps are being taken to release the new immune system to be more aggressive. Essentially, using different drugs, we went from applying the brakes to the immune system to adding fuel to it. The goal: activate/jump-start the immune system to attack the cancer. Of course doing this has the potential to unleash the immune system to also attack Sam’s healthy tissues.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>This past weekend Sam had intense rashes and evidence that the GVHD was not only active on the outside of his body but also the inside (e.g.&nbsp;loss of taste, increased liver enzymes). The GVHD seemed to reach a peak on the weekend. Recent bloodwork seems to align with the symptoms we have been observing. If Sam’s immune system continues to settle back down we will likely continue with this line of treatment.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="general-living" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="general-living">General living</h3>
<p>Sam’s life is pretty simple: watching too much YouTube, and when he has more energy, he reads, plays video games (only rarely able to sit up to play on his PC), and occasionally reviews some studies. Lately, his activity has been limited to short walks, mostly around the RMH. He also enjoys visiting with people, though his capacity can often be low causing visits to be short (e.g.&nbsp;30 minutes). Despite the length of this journey and current challenges Sam still maintains a positive attitude with statements like: <em>“I love my life.”, “I am so happy”</em>, <em>“We have a great family”.</em></p>
<p>Our parental pride swelled earlier this week. A boy here at the RMH, I’ll call him B., is about five years old and has looked up to Sam. B. was having a hard week and mad at the world – Sam decided to brighten his day. Sam chose a lego set which I purchased when I was out. Sam was able to give it to him the next day and also spent some time helping him assemble it. B. was thrilled! So great that Sam took the opportunity to care for this young man!</p>
<p>We continue to enjoy visits with family. Tina’s family members, who live in the region, try to make a point of being here each week. We look forward to seeing them on their usual days.</p>
<p>We also love to see friends as they are able to come through. This past week it was great to see Jess and John with Kate and John (Jr.).</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam’s energy and capacity for simple living have swung up and down over the last two weeks. Currently, his energy levels are low – mostly likely related to the ongoing treatments.</p></li>
<li><p>This is a long journey and all of our energy levels are tapped (physically and emotionally). Part of the challenge is the ambiguity. We are now in a third period (we call it “era”) of treatment (i.e.&nbsp;1: chemotherapy, 2: BMT, 3:immune-therapy). The previous therapies had protocols to follow and expected end dates. The current therapy is day-by-day, becoming week-by-week… there is no clear timeline …</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam’s pain levels have been stable and generally easy to manage. The main challenges are related to the GVHD, specifically with rashes, which are not painful but are at times very itchy and hot.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has a cold. It has now been identified as common cold that he would have had as a young child. The upside is he has a new immune system to battle it. The downside, his new immune system is like that of a newborn – needing to create antibodies for all of the diseases that Sam has already seen through life.</p></li>
<li><p>New battle strategies against the cancer have been developed but carry some higher risks.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The new immunotherapy drugs seems to have released Sam’s immune system to hit harder. Though we look forward to this pushing the cancer back, side effects of the new immune system attacking healthy tissues are also big concern (i.e.&nbsp;GVHD).<br>
<br>
Sam has had some adverse effects and we need to allow these to resolve before proceeding with new treatments.</p></li>
<li><p>Targeted radiation therapy began last week and will complete this week. We are thankful this tool can be used to reduce the burden of disease on Sam. However, radiation also comes with risks.</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation We cannot thank you enough.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and medical care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the gift of a place to stay so close to where Sam is receiving his care. The <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">Ronald McDonald House (RMH)</a> has provided us a home away from home. This place is an amazing example of charity at work.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>The cancer remains and has spread to new areas in Sam’s body. The sites are a mass in the center of his chest (the original), and newer sites in his back (T3 vertebrae), his hip (right ilium), and left shin (tibia just below the knee).</p></li>
<li><p>We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>new-sites</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2403/2024-03-19_gvhd.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Again we wait</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2403/2024-03-08_again-we-wait.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR <span class="small">Too long didn’t read (i.e.&nbsp;the short version)</span>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Immune therapy treatment was started with no adverse reactions.</li>
<li>Radiation planning was completed with treatments to start next week.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
March 11
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>A few quick notes as we head into this week</p>
<ul>
<li>Today Sam starts his radiation therapy. Radiation therapy will be Monday - Friday for this week and next.</li>
<li>A couple victories:
<ul>
<li>We have had good control of Sam’s pain over the last week.</li>
<li>Sam has had more energy over the weekend than we have seen since before the BMT.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>With the ongoing immune therapy Sam has had more minor Graft-Versus-Host-Disease symptoms (GVHD, itchy rashes). We are hopeful that this means there is active Graft-Versus-Disease.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<p>The past week has come and gone and in general it has been a good week for Sam (all things considered). The next wave of treatments and treatment planning has begun. Though we will need to wait several weeks before we know how well or if the treatments are working.</p>
<section id="this-past-weeks-medical-journey" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="this-past-weeks-medical-journey">This past week’s medical journey</h2>
<p>Just over a week ago, on Thursday, Sam was started on <a href="http://www.bccancer.bc.ca/drug-database-site/Drug%20Index/Nivolumab_handout.pdf">Nivolumab</a> with the intention of ramping up his immune system to battle the cancer. We had expected to spend 3-4 nights in the hospital to monitor for potential adverse reactions to the drug. He did not have any adverse reactions! Sam was thrilled when the medical team offered to discharge him to leave hospital after one night.</p>
<p>On Friday morning, we made the quick trip down to BC Cancer where we met with the radiation oncologist. Initial discussions had suggested that radiation would only be used on the disease site in Sam’s back (T3 vertebrae). However, following a quick discussion the team at BC Cancer agreed to use radiation on all three of the new sites. To plan for this treatment, the radiation therapy team made some molds of Sam - his back and the front of his upper body - and then took him for a CT scan (this is a planning CT). These molds and measurements will ensure that Sam is in the exact same position during treatment – ensuring that the upcoming treatment is very precise.</p>
<p>Compared with my previous post, Sam’s health and pain levels have been quite stable with no significant pain spikes.</p>
<!-- We were leaving from the hospital and there had been some confusion around how we would get to BC Cancer.  An ambulance had been planned but their team was obviously not going to get to us to make our appointment on time at VGH.  Instead we chose to take our personal van.  This allowed us to arrive on time.   Arriving on time allowed us the opportunity to discuss options further with Dr. Goddard.  In addition, the team had the time they needed to do proper planning -->
</section>
<section id="next-steps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next steps</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Nivolumab immune therapy</dt>
<dd>
<p>This therapy is provided by IV once every two weeks. This coming Thursday (March 14) Sam will receive a second dose. This next dose will be double that of the first.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Radiation therapy</dt>
<dd>
<p>Targeted radiation of the three new disease sites will begin this coming Monday. Sam will receive a dose of radiation to each site every day for two weeks (10 business days). Assuming all goes well this will simply mean a short drive to BC Cancer clinic for the treatment and then a return to RMH.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Results and effectiveness</dt>
<dd>
<p>We are not going to know how any of these treatments are working for some time. It is too soon to tell if the immune therapy is working. Following radiation, we will need to wait a couple weeks for that treatment to take effect. … So we wait.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>For now the best indicator of how things are going is with Sam. How he is feeling. Where is pain levels are. How his body reacts to the treatments.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="life-together" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="life-together">Life together</h2>
<p><em>So how are we doing?</em></p>
<p>Last week, I felt beyond exhausted, physically and emotionally, this has been a long journey. Sam reminded me that we have been here five months longer than expected. He is right. The initial plan if everything had gone as expected/hoped would have seen us go home this past October. Next, the BMT process, should have seen us go home last week. Now, when are we going to get home? Simply, we just do not know.</p>
<p>In the meantime, we are enjoying life together. It is a simple life that includes medical care, meals, and time together. When Sam has the energy we get out of the building. Lately, he has enjoyed a trip to a local bookstore. In our room, Tina and I are thrilled when Sam has the energy to connect with friends and play some online games (which he has been able to do a couple times this week). Programs here at the Ronald McDonald House have been helpful. Sam has taken to playing the drums – I don’t know where he gets his rhythm from but he is a natural. I have enjoyed playing and learning a few new things on guitar. Tina has made it to a couple painting classes. We have also been able to connect with a number of other families including playing some board games together.</p>
<p>We are encouraged by visitors, Grace and Darren from Prince George, Tina’s Uncle Dave and Aunt Ruth originally from England but now in Abbotsford, and Tina’s family: siblings, Nana Mary, and Sam’s cousins are all in the Lower Mainland and we see some of them weekly.</p>
<p>One highlight from this past week was that we have moved to a larger room. This will allow us to enjoy our space more including providing some space for some anticipated guests.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam has had a good week. Pain levels have been stable and generally easy to manage.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has a chest cold. The upside is he has a new immune system to battle it. The downside, well it is a cold that is taking energy from him – energy we want him to have to battle the cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>The cancer remains and has spread to new areas in Sam’s body.</p></li>
<li><p>New battle strategies have been developed but carry some higher risks.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The new immunotherapy drugs will release Sam’s immune system to hit harder. Though we look forward to this pushing the cancer back, side effects of the new immune system attacking healthy tissues are also big concern.<br>
<br>
We are thankful that Sam has not had any adverse reactions to this drug. The next dose will be double the first so concerns remain.</p></li>
<li><p>Targeted radiation therapy begins next week. We are thankful this tool can be used to reduce the burden of disease on Sam. However, radiation also comes with risks.</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>We cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>new-sites</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2403/2024-03-08_again-we-wait.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
