<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Sam Chisholm</title>
<link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>News updating friends and family on our journey</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.361</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>A chemical crutch</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2401/2024-01-11_chemical-crutch.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>The days since my last post have been rough. Whatever virus we all picked up is still lingering. Sam and I are mostly past it, and Tina is improving. Unfortunately, this cold also caused some confusion as the team cared for Sam – it was more difficult to discern what was happening with him while he was battling this illness.</p>
<section id="looking-back" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-back">Looking back</h2>
<section id="sams-medical-progress" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sams-medical-progress">Sam’s medical progress</h3>
<dl>
<dt>The challenges</dt>
<dd>
<p>Following New Year’s it was like someone flipped a switch in Sam … in that the power was turned off. Where prior Jan.&nbsp;1<sup>st</sup> Sam had increasing stamina and activity levels, this past week-and-a-half he had no energy and spent most days in bed. The virus we all had complicated the picture. We did have a couple clinic appointments but making any changes were difficult as it was hard to know what was happening in Sam’s body apart from the illness.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Last Wednesday there was a decision to stop one of the steroids used during BMT. Initially, this did not seem to affect Sam … but at the time all he was doing was sleeping (&gt;90% of the time). By the end of the weekend, Sam was mostly done with the cold but he was still sleeping… and not very responsive. It turns out the steroid was a chemical crutch and we had pulled in out from under him.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>The next clinic appointment, earlier this week, a substitute steroid was introduced. Sam is now more conscious and is beginning to get moving again.</p>
</dd>
<dt>The positive</dt>
<dd>
<p>Despite the confusion and challenges above Sam has made some good progress having successfully dropped a number of medications from his list.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Symptoms of GVHD have been minimal with minor rashes. The medical team remains vigilant watching out for this.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="visits" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visits">Visits</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>It was great to see my parents this past week. They had a couple windows of opportunity to chat with Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>Tina and I were able to get out for a nice meal with Kevin and Shannon.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We will continue with the usual clinic visits to monitor Sam’s progress.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam will be seen Endrocrinology Team. This team specializes in steroids, hormones and all of the glands in our bodies that produce them. It is not uncommon for someone who has been on steroids and then stops (e.g.&nbsp;Sam for his BMT) to have issues producing their own hormones. I expect that this team will examine Sam to determine what hormones he may need in the short-term, consider strategies for getting his own system jump-started, and worst case to determine if there has been any damage to his glands.</p></li>
<li><p>There is talk of removing Sam’s central line!</p></li>
<li><p>All of the pre-BMT baseline tests will be completed</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>It has been a hard week watching our son sleep most day and not understanding why. His brief periods of wakefulness re-assured us that he was still in-there. This was stressful and exhausting for Tina and I. We now have some direction and started on some supports for him. The biggest underlying concern is the return of his body’s ability to produce and regulate natural hormone levels.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has gotten past the his cold. His new immune system beat it back and we did not have to go into hospital. <del>Our first challenge of 2024 seems to have been exposure to a flu. Sam has been feeling rough, with higher pain levels, and lots of fatigue. We initially attributed this as a response to increased activity levels … but then Tina and I started battling colds.</del></p></li>
<li><p>We have had an great holiday season celebrating Christmas, Tina’s birthday, and New Years with family in the area.</p></li>
<li><p>We are no longer having medical discussions about upcoming treatments. Discussions are now about weaning medications, removing the central line, and preparations to return home!</p></li>
<li><p>New blood cells in Sam’s body are all from the donor! Sam’s bone marrow is pumping-out/generating new blood! The engraftment process is working! We have seen Sam’s numbers come up and now stabilize!</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern if the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease. A PET scan will be done in February to evaluate how the cancer has been impacted by all the treatments. The expectation is that any remaining cancer, following the chemo and radiation therapies, will be removed by the newly transplanted immune system.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>post-BMT</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2401/2024-01-11_chemical-crutch.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Happy New Year!!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2401/2024-01-01_happy-new-year.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Happy New Year! We have so much to be thankful for this year! Although, 2023 was incredibly challenging it ended with joy as we celebrate Sam’s new life. Looking up and looking forward we are filled with hope and joy for the year ahead.</p>
<p>Joy has been a theme for Sam. Many mornings he wakes up and the first thing he says is “<em>I’m so happy!</em>” On New Year’s day it was “<em>I’m so happy. I am immensely happy!</em>” In the last couple weeks he also commonly adds “<em>I have an amazing life!</em>”</p>
<p>Taking a van trip our to see the family and bring in the New Year, Tina brought up Psalm 23, a passage that many also sent on to us. Sam reflected on how he feels like God has lay down beside the green pastures.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<h2 id="psalm-23" class="anchored">Psalm 23</h2>
<p>The Lord is my shepherd, I lack nothing.<br>
&nbsp;He makes me lie down in green pastures,<br>
he leads me beside quiet waters.<br>
&nbsp;True to your word,<br>
you refresh my soul<br>
&nbsp;and send me in the right direction..</p>
<p>Even when the way<br>
&nbsp;goes through Death Valley,<br>
I will fear no evil,<br>
&nbsp;for you are with me;<br>
your rod and your staff,<br>
&nbsp;they comfort me.</p>
<p>You prepare a table before me<br>
&nbsp;in the presence of my enemies.<br>
You anoint my head with oil;<br>
&nbsp;my cup overflows.<br>
Surely your goodness and love will follow me<br>
&nbsp;all the days of my life,<br>
and I will dwell in the house of the <span class="smallcaps">Lord</span> forever.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.bible.com/bible/111/PSA.23.NIV?parallel=97"><em>Psalm 23</em></a> <em>(blend of NIV and The Message versions)</em></p>
</blockquote>
<section id="looking-back" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-back">Looking back</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Medical items</dt>
<dd>
<p>Sam continues to have regular visits at the clinic. Various blood tests to ensure the various medications that Sam is on are at appropriate levels. Most of the discussion with the medical team is in preparation to leave! This includes weaning Sam off of the medications. To date, everything with the BMT is going well and Sam is ahead of the anticipated schedule. Various members of the medical team have said they are amazed at how well Sam is doing.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Christmas</dt>
<dd>
<p>Christmas was… extravagant! We spent the morning sharing gifts and the evening meal and games wth family.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Life beyond the hospital</dt>
<dd>
<p>It is exciting that we ar having more an more life beyond the bounds of the hospital campus! Including:</p>
</dd>
</dl>
<ul>
<li>Visits with family Langley and in White Rock</li>
<li>A great Townsend-side buffet meal to celebrate <em>Tina’s birthday</em>. All but one of Sam’s cousins from that side of the family were able to make it.<br>
</li>
<li>A new years party at with Nana, Uncle Kevin and Auntie Shannon, and all of their children plus partners. Including the newlyweds Kurt and Marielle.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Medical appointments will continue as Sam remains under a watchful eye from the team.</p></li>
<li><p>Medicines will gradually be removed</p></li>
<li><p>There is talk of removing Sam’s central line (in a couple weeks)!</p></li>
<li><p>All of the pre-BMT baseline tests will be completed</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Our first challenge of 2024 seems to have been exposure to a flu. Sam has been feeling rough, with higher pain levels, and lots of fatigue. We initially attributed this as a response to increased activity levels … but then Tina and I started battling colds. The good thing is that Sam is now has an immune system to fight for him.</p></li>
<li><p>We have had an great holiday season celebrating Christmas, Tina’s birthday, and New Years with family in the area.</p></li>
<li><p>We are no longer having medical discussions about upcoming treatments. Discussions are now about weaning medications, removing the central line, and preparations to return home!</p></li>
<li><p>Sam continues to regain strength.</p></li>
<li><p>New blood cells in Sam’s body are all from the donor! Sam’s bone marrow is pumping-out/generating new blood! The engraftment process is working! We have seen Sam’s numbers come up and now stabilize!</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease. A PET scan will be done in February to evaluate how the cancer has been impacted by all the treatments. The expectation is that any remaining cancer, following the chemo and radiation therapies, will be removed by the newly transplanted immune system.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>post-BMT</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2401/2024-01-01_happy-new-year.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Merry Christmas</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-24_merry-christmas.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Merry Christmas everyone! We have so much to be thankful for!</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I came so they can have real and eternal life, more and better life than they ever dreamed of.<br>
— Jesus (<a href="https://www.bible.com/bible/97/JHN.10.MSG">John 10:10</a>, The Message translation)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sam is doing great! Since the last post he has continued to gain strength. We have a long road ahead of us but it seems we are on the path towards home and the return to friends, family, school, and work there.</p>
<section id="the-past-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-past-days">The past days</h2>
<div class="img-float-right">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-12_walk-to-clinic.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Sam and I walking from the RMH to the hospital for a clinic visit. This was the first morning Sam did not need to ride in the chair (Dec.&nbsp;22<sup>nd</sup>)!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam continues to have regular visits at the clinic. Various blood tests are done each time. One specific, the team looks at Tacrolimus levels, an immunosuppressant used to ensure that this BMT is successful and that any graft-versus-host-disease (GVHD) is minimized. Note: some GVHD is needed so that the new immune system continues to attack any remaining cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>Exciting news! The genetic testing of Sam’s immune system confirmed that the donor cells have fully replaced Sam’s native immune system. Ideally, in a BMT transplant the native immune system is removed to make way for the donor cells. There is always a chance that some native cells remain and that a battle for dominance can occur. For Sam, the BMT has gone as planned and all new blood is being generated by the donor cells.</p></li>
<li><p>All of the blood tests have shown Sam’s counts have come up and are stabilizing.</p></li>
<li><p>I have debated including this next thought … especially during Christmas. It is a challenging reality (skip it if you need to).</p>
<div class="tabset-margin-container"></div><div class="panel-tabset">
<ul class="nav nav-tabs"><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link active" id="tabset-1-1-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-1" aria-controls="tabset-1-1" aria-selected="true">Skip</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-2-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-2" aria-controls="tabset-1-2" aria-selected="false">Read</a></li></ul>
<div class="tab-content">
<div id="tabset-1-1" class="tab-pane active" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-1-tab">
<p><em>or click ‘Read’ above</em></p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-2" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-2-tab">
<p>Christmas at the Ronald McDonald House is amazing but strange – layered in hope and pain. There is so much generosity poured into this place you cannot help but feel cared for.<br>
<br>
During these last months, as we have weathered this cancer storm, we have also walked beside a number of other families in similar circumstances. Some are looking forward to completing treatment, while others are in the thick of the storm. Another family, is having an incredibly hard Christmas. They have reached the end of possible treatments and recently moved to hospice to spend what days remain with their child. Our hearts and prayers continue to go out to them.<br>
<br>
Here at the Ronald McDonald House joys and pains are especially visible. For me, this raises an inescapable question for life at home. If your Christmas is full of joy, and I truly hope it is, are there pains that may be close but remain unseen? Is there a way to demonstrate love and generosity into those situations?</p>
</div>
</div>
</div></li>
<li><p>Some good normal life has been happening.</p>
<ul>
<li>Sam has had energy to enjoy reading. He finished <em>The Hobbit</em> earlier this week and immediately got into another book.</li>
<li>Nana was able to visit and help us prepare for Christmas.</li>
<li>We were able to get off the hospital campus and visit the Frickers – with more family visits planned over the holidays. So great to play family games… this year games also includes some VR which actually has been an amazing physical rehabilitation tool.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>What a special Christmas this will be! We have seen Sam through a long and challenging journey and it seems we are on the other side!<br>
<br>
<em>What do I want for Christmas?</em> I already have it! My son is alive! And not just alive, he his beginning to thrive!</p></li>
<li><p>In the weeks ahead there will continue to be regular visits to the clinic as levels are check at medications are adjusted.</p></li>
<li><p>Numerous scans and tests will start in the new year to evaluate if there have been any internal impacts in Sam’s body. This will also include scans to determine if any disease remains.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam has completed his critical post-transplant period. He has now been discharged from the hospital! We will remain at the RMH for the next two months in order to monitor for potential GVHD complications.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam continues to regain strength. He is now able to walk from the RMH to the hospital.</p></li>
<li><p>New blood cells in Sam’s body are all from the donor! Sam’s bone marrow is pumping-out/generating new blood! The engraftment process is working! We have seen Sam’s numbers come up and now stabilize!</p></li>
<li><p>Sam will still be considered immune compromised for the months ahead and mostly susceptible to viral infection. It remains to be flu season and covid is still out there. We must continue to be vigilant to protect Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all of the messages of encouragement and solidarity that we have received from all of you.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
In case you missed it
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kATGCsIqALw?si=QwtKjKK690T1ljFy" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<div style="font-size:90%; margin-left: 15pt; margin-right: 15pt">
<p>On Dec.&nbsp;12<sup>th</sup> Santa paid a visit to the BC Children’s Hospital. Sam was able to welcome him onto the oncology ward. Tina and Nana Mary (1:03) were also able to meet him. Tina did an amazing job of sharing what this Christmas means to us (starting at 1:13). The original news article from the CBC is <a href="https://www.cbc.ca/player/play/2291723843615">linked here</a>.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>post-BMT</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-24_merry-christmas.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Christmas has come early! Freedom!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-13_christmas-came-early.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kATGCsIqALw?si=QwtKjKK690T1ljFy" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<div style="font-size:90%; margin-left: 15pt; margin-right: 15pt">
<p>On Dec.&nbsp;12<sup>th</sup> Santa paid a visit to the BC Children’s Hospital. Sam was able to welcome him onto the oncology ward. Tina and Nana Mary (1:03) were also able to meet him. Tina did an amazing job of sharing what this Christmas means to us (starting at 1:13). The original news article from the CBC is <a href="www.cbc.ca/i/phoenix/player/syndicate/?mediaId=2291723843615">linked here</a>.</p>
</div>
<p>Wow! It has been an amazing 48 hours!</p>
<p>Tuesday, two days ago, Santa visited a number of hospitals in the province and our family got to be a part of this celebration. Sam was able to be one of the first to welcome him to the ward and the staff loved his enthusiasm! I am still stunned by the opportunity Tina had to speak with the CBC, with how well she was able to capture what this Christmas means to us, and how it also let the medical team know how important they have been to us.</p>
<p>Yesterday, was a major Christmas present for our family: Sam was discharged from the ward and we are all back at the Ronald McDonald House!</p>
<p>Before leaving there was a short ceremony where all of the nurses gathered, a speech was given by one of the doctors to honor Sam for all of the work that he as undertaken – noting especially how he taken such responsibility in understanding the treatments and communicating so well with the team. After, Sam walked out the doors in stark contrast to his arrival by air ambulance eight months ago! He was done and ready to move on – though a part of him will miss the amazing people that have cared for him these last weeks (BMT) and months (Chemotherapy).</p>
<p>We will be based at the RMH for the next two months. In this time Sam will be at clinic 2-3 times per week to monitor for potential graft versus host disease (GVHD) which will likely mean lots of minor adjustments to his medications. He has a long list of medications but over time this will be reduced.</p>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam has completed his critical post-transplant period. He has now been discharged from the hospital! We will remain at the RMH for the next two months in order to monitor for potential GVHD complications.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam is returning to strength! Having received his discharge paper, he walked out of the hospital back towards the RMH. He made it most of the way back before powering out and transferring to the chair. With the way he has been eating his return to strength will continue to be rapid!</p></li>
<li><p>Sam’s bones are generating new blood! The engraftment process is working! We have seen Sam’s numbers come up and now stabilize!</p></li>
<li><p>Sam will still be considered immune compromised for the months ahead and mostly susceptible to viral infection. It remains to be flu season and covid is still out there. We must continue to be vigilant to protect Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery and engraftment of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all of the messages of encouragement and solidarity that we have received from all of you.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <category>hospital</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-13_christmas-came-early.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>From Step-down to Stepping-out</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-11_stepdown-to-steppingout.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It has now been 27 days since Sam received his BMT. The initial couple weeks had big challenges and Sam needed a lot of medical supports. His IV-tower was huge with a dozen lines running at once. In the last ten days that has all changed!</p>
<div class="center">
<p><em>I finally feel like myself again!</em> – Sam</p>
</div>
<p>Over the last ten days the team has been continuous reducing the number of medical supports. With one exception all his medications have been converted to pills. Sam has his appetite back and has been eating really well. The tube feed has been there as a back up for a few hours a day but I expect the we will try to stopping it’s use today. All this means Sam is IV-tower free for most of waking hours.</p>
<p>We are also seeing him return to energy. A couple weeks ago it was difficult to cross the room. Now, we are taking laps around the ward. One thing that we will miss is the Sam’s personal cheerleader-squad as the nurses literally cheer when he goes by the nurses station! On Saturday Sam had an afternoon pass – we left the hospital and wheeled over to the Ronald McDonald House. Sam loved the cool fresh air!</p>
<p>For Tina and I, it feels like a massive weight is being lifted. We knew that this time has been hard… but I don’t think we fully understood the pressure we were under. We are now beginning to be able to contemplate returning to home – though that is still a couple months away.</p>
<section id="next-steps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next steps</h2>
<p>Sam has done incredibly well and this engraftment process, so far, has gone smoothly and quickly. It is likely that Sam will be discharged from the hospital later this week – well ahead of schedule (previously we were hoping to get out a few days before Christmas).</p>
<p>Once out life should be simpler. We will be at the Ronald McDonald House (RMH) and visit the clinic 2-3 times per week to check on Sam’s progress and monitor for any Graft Versus Host Disease related issues. Practically speaking this means regular blood-work. Sometime in the weeks and months ahead Sam will receive a PET scan or two to confirm that the cancer has been defeated.</p>
<p>Once out the next major milestone will be <em>Day 100</em> (past the BMT). This will be the day we should have the green-light to go home!</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam is returning to strength! We expect to be out of the hospital and living back at the RMH later this week.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam’s bones are generating new blood! The engraftment process is working! We have seen Sam’s numbers come up and now stabilize!</p></li>
<li><p>What an incredible birthday present. Sam’s ANC blood metric went from non-detectable to 0.3. A strong indicator that the transplant is taking hold!</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that what Sam has experienced so far is within the normal for a BMT and that he has not had any complications. Although it is all in the ‘normal’, it is not all easy:</p>
<ul>
<li>Nausea is under control! We have seen the reduction of meds and will be testing removal of some anti-nausea meds. <del>Impacts from the pre-treatment, chemotherapy and radiation, remain strong. These cause deep bone and muscle pain, along with nausea. <em>These are starting to resolve!</em></del></li>
<li>Pain management is under control! Sam is on a regular dose of morphine which he will start reducing over the weeks ahead.</li>
<li>Nutrition mainly by mouth and I expect the NG tube will be removed in the next few days.</li>
<li>Energy levels are returning! – it is great to see Sam roam the halls!</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam will still be considered immune compromised for the months ahead and mostly susceptible to viral infection. It remains to be flu season and covid is still out there. We must continue to be vigilant to protect Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all of the messages of encouragement and solidarity that we have received from all of you.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <category>hospital</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-11_stepdown-to-steppingout.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Engraftment!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-01_engraftment.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Time here in the hospital feels so warped. It is hard to believe that we have been on the ward for three weeks now, having arrived a few days before the transplant. It is now <em>day 17</em>.</p>
<p>Although not without challenges, Sam has been making excellent process. It was beautiful to see the first numbers indicating success of the BMT come in on his birthday, and the numbers have been climbing everyday! On day fourteen Sams’s blood counts officially confirmed that engraftment is occurring! His bones are hard at work pushing out new blood and rebuilding a new immune system! Genetic testing to confirm that Sam’s new blood is from the donor will be done day ±30 (Dec.&nbsp;14).</p>
<section id="step-down" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="step-down">Step down</h2>
<p>Sam has now entered the <em>step-down</em> phase. It is in this period that all of the extra supports will be reduced, removed, or converted to oral; and we will be prepared to leave the hospital! Already:</p>
<ul>
<li>Anti-nausea medications have been reduced from continuous infusion to lower frequency does. We are going slow with these, as Sam is starts to get his appetite back we do not want to wreck that with a wave of nausea.</li>
<li>Nutrition is now dominantly provided via NG tube, and less so by IV/TPN which will likely be stopped today. As Sam gets his appetite, and his tastebuds back, all external supplements will eventually be removed.</li>
<li>Pain medications have been reduced and generally Sam is not needing to self administer as often.</li>
<li>Immune and transplant therapy drugs are ongoing and will eventually be converted to oral.</li>
</ul>
<p>As each day passes it is great to see less medications and fewer pumps needed. Sam is also more alert and with the help of the physio team here we expect to see him return to an energy and strength.</p>
</section>
<section id="current-challenges" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="current-challenges">Current challenges</h2>
<p>Sam has deep bone pain. This is not a new experience for him. With every round of chemotherapy his blood counts would drop and his bones, more specifically the marrow, would work hard to generate and replace the blood cells killed by the treatment. The BMT process was this again, but more intense. This time the marrow was entirely cleared out. The transplant cells have taken up home in the marrow and are cranking out new blood – but not without pain.</p>
<p>It is very exciting that Sam’s body is now generating new blood. The challenge is that this blood is still foreign to him. The medial team keeps a close eye on Sam looking for signs of Graft Versus Host Disease (GVHD) – where the new transplanted immune system could start attacking Sam. It is amazing, that cancer and immune therapy research has progressed so far that the team has a whole set of tools to address GVHD.</p>
<p>To date, and relatively speaking, Sam has not had much GVHD issues – though we will be watching for any complications in the weeks and months ahead. Sam has had painful, hot, and blotchy rashes show up – usually in the evening that may be attributed to GVHD. Although we throw everything we can at these flair-ups he often has to simply suffer through for an hour or two.</p>
<p>Sam continues to be courageous! He conveys gratefulness to everyone on the team and to Tina and I as we assist him through the days.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam’s bones are generating new blood! Engraftment is ongoing and everyday we see his numbers come up! We will be on the watch for Graft Versus Host Disease (GVHD) – which may be causing periodic rashes.</p></li>
<li><p>What an incredible birthday present. Sam’s ANC blood metric went from non-detectable to 0.3. A strong indicator that the transplant is taking hold!</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that what Sam has experienced so far is within the normal for a BMT and that he has not had any complications. Although it is all in the ‘normal’, it is not all easy:</p>
<ul>
<li>Impacts from the pre-treatment, chemotherapy and radiation, remain strong. These cause deep bone and muscle pain, along with nausea. <em>These are starting to resolve!</em></li>
<li>Pain management is constantly under revision. <em>Update: We seem to have the right mix. Pain and nausea are currently under control</em></li>
<li>Nutrition is received by ~~TPN (IV),~ NG tube, and minority by mouth.</li>
<li>Energy levels are low <em>but recovering</em>– it is great to see Sam have energy to sit up and play when he can.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>It had been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity. It is hard to see him have this strength pulled away from him.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>It is flu season and covid is still out there. If any of us get sick it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he is in a phase where he has no immune system for the next few weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all of the messages of encouragement and solidarity that we have received from all of you.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <category>hospital</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2312/2023-12-01_engraftment.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Best Birthday Present!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-25_happiest-b-day.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="yesterday-sams-birthday" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="yesterday-sams-birthday">Yesterday, Sam’s birthday</h2>
<section id="by-the-numbers" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="by-the-numbers">By the numbers</h3>
<p>While attempting to secretly decorate Sam’s room in the early morning hours Sam’s nurse provided me with the results of that night’s bloodwork – the numbers were exciting. Sam was hoping that on his birthday there would be some indication that the BMT was taking hold. Two days ago the bloodwork hinted that something was happening. For Sam’s birthday the bloodwork numbers were more than we hoped. Our hope was that his ANC, a metric of immune system strength, would hit 0.1. All week it had been &lt; 0.1 (essentially non-detectable) and for Sam’s birthday it jumped to 0.3!</p>
<p>This is exciting news! The numbers indicate that engraftment is happening, that the BMT is taking hold, though it will not be considered definitive until the ANC exceeds 0.5 for a three consecutive days and some additional tests are run.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-great-birthday" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-great-birthday">A great birthday</h3>
<p>Sam had a great day. The ANC of 0.3 had everyone excited, the three of us, the nurses, and the doctors, and this set a great tone for the day. Sam’s body is working overtime generating new blood so he rested a lot, pain and nausea have been under control for the last 48 hours.</p>
<p>Sam was able to have video-calls with his grandparents. Thoughout the afternoon, as a family, we loved reviewing messages, and video messages with birthday greetings. The nurses on shift all piled into the anteroom to sing Sam happy birthday and deliver a cake – he was even able to eat some of it! Of course there were presents which Sam took his time opening, reading the cards and enjoying every word written and gift sent. Thank you!</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="next-steps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next steps</h2>
<p>We will get more clarity on the next steps in the days ahead. Here is what I currently understand:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>We will be watching for the day the BMT is officially considered engrafted (3 consecutive days of ANC <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cgeq%200.5">).</p></li>
<li><p>Sam will begin a step-down process as his body heals from the intense chemotherapy and radiation therapy that was used to condition his body to receive the transplant. Currently, he receiving significant external supports: nutrition is being delivered via NG tube and TPN (IV delivery), and he is on a continuous schedule of numerous drugs. In the step down process these supports will slowly be removed, and drugs will be converted to oral delivery.</p></li>
<li><p>Over the next couple months Sam will be watched closely for signs of Graft versus Host Disease (GVHD)– essentially that the new immune system does not harm Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>We should be out of hospital and back the Ronald McDonald House before Christmas.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>What an incredible birthday present. Sam’s ANC blood metric went from non-detectable to 0.3. A strong indicator that the transplant is taking hold!</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that Sam has felt the love of his community around him – especially on his birthday.</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that what Sam has experienced so far is within the normal for a BMT and that he has not had any complications. Although it is all in the ‘normal’, it is not all easy:</p>
<ul>
<li>Impacts from the pre-treatment, chemotherapy and radiation, remain strong. These cause deep bone and muscle pain, along with nausea.</li>
<li>Pain management is constantly under revision. <em>Update: We seem to have the right mix. Pain and nausea are currently under control</em></li>
<li>Nutrition is received by TPN (IV), NG tube, and minority by mouth.</li>
<li>Energy levels are low – it is great to see Sam have energy to sit up and play when he can.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>There will be ongoing concern as many known and unknown pitfalls that may present themselves during the BMT process. Potential illness, establishment/engraftment of the donated bone-marrow/ stem cells. Numerous other potential complications.</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Update: Sam did have an infection earlier this week. Within about 45 minutes of detection he was on antibiotics and was cleared out quickly. The team here says that this happens to everyone going through a BMT.</em></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all of the messages of encouragement and solidarity that we have received from all of you.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that it seems Sam’s pain management is now mostly under control, including options to address any spikes in pain.</p></li>
<li><p>It had been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity. It is hard to see him have this strength pulled away from him.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>It is flu season and covid is still out there. If any of us get sick it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he is in a phase where he has no immune system for the next few weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that had to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Done! Thank you! <del>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</del></li>
<li>Continuing: We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>Done! <del>The medical team has a huge coordination task ahead of them. From our meetings with them it seems all of the pieces are coming together, but with so many moving parts it is easy for things go wrong.</del></li>
<li>Done! Although it was rough at points the BMT conditioning was successful! <del>These last days leading up to the BMT are very busy with lots of drugs running all day. Concerns during this time are that everything is able to be delivered as planned and that Sam does not have any overly negative reactions to any of this.</del></li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <category>hospital</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-25_happiest-b-day.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Wait Continues</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-19_the-wait.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I am writing from Sam’s room as my family sleeps. It was a good night last night as all of us slept the majority of it away.</p>
<p>We are now in the waiting period. Waiting for indications that the BMT is establishing in Sam’s body. In our instant world this is a long wait – 2-3 weeks of anticipation. This morning, knowing that many of you are wondering how we are doing – waiting in solidarity with us, I thought I would pass on a snapshot of what this waiting looks like.</p>
<p>Although in the big picture of Sam’s treatment we are waiting. In the day-to-day or hour-by-hour there can be a lot going on.</p>
<section id="regular-check-ins" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="regular-check-ins">Regular check-ins</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>BMT and Oncology Doctors come and check on Sam daily and often twice daily and adjust orders as needed. They are satisfied with how Sam is doing as everything seems to be progressing normally. Medical orders from this team tend to address issues with:</p>
<ul>
<li>blood – as blood counts will continually drop until the graft takes. Sam has received and will receive numerous transfusions in the weeks ahead.</li>
<li>bowels – mucositis has once again and as expected impacted Sam’s entire digestive track. However, where things were previously too slow now they are too fast.</li>
<li>They also keep a watchful eye with daily physical exams.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>The Acute Pain Services (APS) doctors visits 1-2 times per day. By the end of the previous six rounds of chemotherapy the suite of drugs was causing a lot of pain deep in Sam’s bones and muscles. In preparation, for the BMT Sam received higher doses of chemotherapy than he ever had previously. The APS ensures Sam is as comfortable as possible. Often his base pain management drugs are increased to match increasing pain levels.</p></li>
<li><p>A Nutritionist is here usually daily on weekdays. Sam receives his nutrition in a variety of ways. Eating is limited due to side effects of all the treatments but he still gets a little down. NG food delivery took a little while to get going but is going well now. Sam also receives TPN which is nutrition in a bag pumped directly into his bloodstream.</p></li>
<li><p>Physiotherapy regularly visits through the week. Providing exercises that are suited to how well Sam is feeling. Exercises range from squats and stretches outside the bed to simple muscle activations when he is too tired to leave the bed.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="incredible-nurses" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="incredible-nurses">Incredible Nurses</h2>
<p>It is the nurses that carry the weight of hour-by-hour activity. They ensure all of the orders from the various specialists are implemented. Sam now has over a dozen different pumps available to push drugs and nutrition into his body, and sometimes they are all running at the same time. On a regular basis alarms are going off (e.g.&nbsp;completion of a drug delivery, air-in-line). In addition, to ensuring everything is technically working, and that all the medical orders are being delivered, the nursing team is constantly available to trouble shoot with us and when needed advocate for changes to medical orders.</p>
</section>
<section id="mom-dad-and-sam" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mom-dad-and-sam">Mom, Dad, and Sam</h2>
<p>What are we doing during all of these different activities? Given that Sam is living this experience and Tina and I are the ones constantly observing, the three of us are very much a part of each visit and conversation with the specialists. Tina and I are also Sam’s first line of assistance – calling nurses when alarms sound, and assisting Sam in an out of bed. Sam’s big task for each day is to have complete his shower. This is a chore and he needs to bring his IV system with him and it can burn the majority of his available energy.</p>
<p>When there are no task to do and when Sam is awake we are simply there to be with him: sit beside him, watch a show together, talk, and Sam often asks for prayer. Yesterday, Sam was able to enjoy watching the Vancouver vs.&nbsp;Seattle hockey game.</p>
<p>How are we doing? I think… tired but hopeful. This journey is exhausting at many levels and for Sam most of all. But we are also encouraged with how everything is progressing. It is like when you are on a long journey and the last hours of that journey seem to always take the longest. Or if you are hiking through the mountains, when you cross the final ridge and you can see home but is is still a long way to get there. The big tasks have now been done. We look forward, knowing that we will get back, but there are many miles still ahead.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that what Sam has experienced so far is within the normal for a BMT and that he has not had any complications.</p></li>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all of the messages of encouragement and solidarity that we have received from all of you.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that it seems Sam’s pain management is now mostly under control, including options to address any spikes in pain.</p></li>
<li><p>There will be ongoing concern are many known and unknown pitfalls that may present themselves during the BMT process. Potential illness, establishment/engraftment of the donated bone-marrow/ stem cells. Numerous potential complications.</p></li>
<li><p>It had been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity. It is hard to see him have this strength pulled away from him.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>It is flu season and covid is still out there. If any of us get sick it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he will be entering a phase where he has no immune system for weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Done! Thank you! <del>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</del></li>
<li>Continuing: We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>Done! <del>The medical team has a huge coordination task ahead of them. From our meetings with them it seems all of the pieces are coming together, but with so many moving parts it is easy for things go wrong.</del></li>
<li>Done! Although it was rough at points the BMT conditioning was successful! <del>These last days leading up to the BMT are very busy with lots of drugs running all day. Concerns during this time are that everything is able to be delivered as planned and that Sam does not have any overly negative reactions to any of this.</del></li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <category>hospital</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-19_the-wait.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Wait Begins</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-15_bmt-received.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>As I begin writing it is 6:30am, Day +1 of Sam’s BMT. This morning I am sitting beside Sam’s bed, to protect him I am all gowned up and masked. Tina and I spent the night in the room and all things considered he is doing well.</p>
<p>At 5:06pm Nov.&nbsp;14, 2023 Sam started to received his new bone-marrow stem cells. Two hours later the IV drip was complete and the donated cells had been received. As hoped receiving the donor cells was very uneventful. Sam had been pre-medicated with numerous drugs to facilitate receiving these foreign cells. A good number of those drugs also cause drowsiness – so Sam slept through most of the procedure. Although there were many hands ready to jump into action should something go wrong, nothing did! Sam’s vitals were and continue to remain within stable limits. Now we wait.</p>
<p>So far things have gone as well as we could hope but it is still not easy on Sam. His body aches. He often has nausea. Although he is hungry very little appetites him. The pain and anti-nausea meds help but not entirely. Sam has gone through a lot and the most recent steps have literally taken a lot out of him. With organ-transplants surgeons cut out the existing organ and incredibly put in the donated one. With a BMT, it is a mind-trip, but we had to kill a part of Sam to make way for the transplant material. With the way made and the new cells received, we now wait.</p>
<p>In this period of waiting a silent battle wages inside Sam’s body. Vitals (e.g.&nbsp;blood pressure, heart and respiratory rates) are monitored. Chemical metrics are monitored through regular bodily fluids (blood and urine). Over the next weeks the transplant material should establish. The team here has been excellent at passing on information as it come in so we will learn more as we go. Metrics indicating the successful engraftment/establishment of the stem cells are not expected for 2-3 weeks.</p>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We very thankful for the successful delivery of the donated stems cells! To whoever made this donation <em>I cannot thank you enough</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to the medical team who have explained things incredibly well and who have worked professionally and confidently. Your clear communication, compassion, and care give us great confidence.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for all of the messages of encouragement and solidarity that we have received from all of you.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that it seems Sam’s pain management is now mostly under control, including options to address any spikes in pain.</p></li>
<li><p>There will be ongoing concern are many known and unknown pitfalls that may present themselves during the BMT process. Potential illness, establishment/engraftment of the donated bone-marrow/ stem cells. Numerous potential complications.</p></li>
<li><p>It had been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity. It is hard to see him have this strength pulled away from him.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>It is flu season and covid is still out there. If any of us get sick it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he will be entering a phase where he has no immune system for weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Done! Thank you! <del>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</del></li>
<li>Continuing: We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>Done! <del>The medical team has a huge coordination task ahead of them. From our meetings with them it seems all of the pieces are coming together, but with so many moving parts it is easy for things go wrong.</del></li>
<li>Done! Although it was rough at points the BMT conditioning was successful! <del>These last days leading up to the BMT are very busy with lots of drugs running all day. Concerns during this time are that everything is able to be delivered as planned and that Sam does not have any overly negative reactions to any of this.</del></li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <category>hospital</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-15_bmt-received.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ready for the BMT</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-14_bmt-ready.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Transplant ongoing
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Sam started receiving the donated bone-marrow/ stem cells at 5:06pm. It is 6:50pm as I write this. Everything is going well as Sam has not had any reactions to these currently foreign cells – cells that will become his own. He should have all finish reciving the material in the next twenty minutes. Sam is sleeping through it all.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-11-14_friends-this-week.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Friends and family visits from this past week. So good to see all of you!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Today is the day and Sam is ready!</p>
<p>Sam had a couple rough days leading up to today but he is now comfortable, settled into the the isolation room, and ready to take on the BMT. The actual transplant will happen later today and should be rather anti-climatic. The transplant is similar to receiving blood the difference being that the material in the bag will be bone marrow stem cells. These cells will take up residence in Sam’s bone marrow and start generating new blood – transplanted blood providing a new immune system.</p>
<p>Yesterday went well. The greatest challenge was moving Sam across the hall. It sounds simple but I was wiped out by the end of the day. In moving over everything had to be sterilized. Most items were thoroughly wiped, and placed in clean containers. Laundry had to be re-done as I had not washed the clothes to BMT clean standards. The medical team also had a big task taking all of the furniture out of the room, sterilized the room, and then they cleaned and sterilized each piece of furniture before returning it.</p>
<p>Sam’s isolation room is similar to the other rooms here on the ward. It has his medical bed, a recliner chair and a fold down couch/bed for Tina and I. The difference is that there is a small anteroom. This room has two sets of glass sliding doors. One door leads to the ward and the other to Sam’s room. Only one door is allowed to be open at one time to ensure that the air in Sam’s room is clean. In the anteroom we clean any items before they are passed into the room. It also in this room that we put on gowns to cover out ‘dirty’ outside world clothing. It is actually much simpler for Tina and I to leave and enter than I had expected.</p>
<p>Yesterday’s highlights was seeing friends. Sam was able to visit with Ben while Tina and I visited with David and Krista C. – following their visit Sam moved to the isolation room. In the evening Uncle Cal stopped was able to wave at Sam through the window. Senga and Tina were also able visit.</p>
<section id="upcoming-today" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming-today">Upcoming today</h2>
<p>Off course today is <em>the day.</em> Sam will receive his bone marrow transplant. This will be likely be sometime in the afternoon but it completely depends on when the donor material arrives. We have no idea if it is coming from within the city or from across the globe. In a couple years there may be an opportunity to meet the donor. Whoever you are <em>I can not thank you enough</em>!.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>There are many known and unknown concerns that will present themselves during the BMT process. Potential illness, establishment/engraftment of the donated bone-marrow/ stem cells. Numerous potential complications. We are thankful for a medical team that has a plan for all of it.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that it seems Sam’s pain management is now under control, including options to address any spikes in pain.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for friends that are able to visit.</p></li>
<li><p>It had been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity. It is hard to see him have this strength pulled away from him.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We have completed a major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy and targeted radiation. We now pivot to the bone marrow transplant – this current and upcoming treatments brings hope of removal of the disease but also anxiety about both the challenging process and the potential for long term side effects. We hope and pray that this treatment will be effective in beating the cancer for life.</p></li>
<li><p>It is flu season and covid is still out there. If any of us get sick it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he will be entering a phase where he has no immune system for weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>We are continually thankful for our medical teams here. They continue to provide incredible care. They are always open to conversation and answering questions. They have been incredibly pro-active and I am glad we are prepared for the next steps.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team has a huge coordination task ahead of them. From our meetings with them it seems all of the pieces are coming together, but with so many moving parts it is easy for things go wrong.</li>
<li>These last days leading up to the BMT are very busy with lots of drugs running all day. Concerns during this time are that everything is able to be delivered as planned and that Sam does not have any overly negative reactions to any of this.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <category>hospital</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-14_bmt-ready.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Last chemo</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-13_bmt-minus-1.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Monday morning, Sam is in a deep and restful sleep. Today is his last day before the BMT, and yesterday was his last dose of chemotherapy. It all goes as planned this will have been his last dose ever, and I look forward to a time when the memories of chemotherapy fade. Chemo sucks.</p>
<p>Yesterday was going really well for Sam. He woke up with a bright attitude and energy to take on the day. He really enjoyed his visit with his friends Chase and Caleb C. Ahh so good to see friends – what a bright highlight to our day! Following this visit Sam had a big nap.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, Sam woke up shortly after shift change in piecing pain – the side effects of chemo had set in while he had slept. When he woke mucositis had had left his mouth as an open wound, raw and full of sores. I am sure as many of you know from your own experiences it is hard to watch your child in pain. It took some time to get new orders but solutions were found. We had to wait an abnormal amount of time for the pain specialist team… we had to wait because they were helping some other poor child with their pain.</p>
<p>Between 10pm and 1am we had some needed victories:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Sam, knowing that the mucositis will only get worse in the days ahead, requested a NG<sup>1</sup> feeding tube. We all knew this would be needed and this was likely last best chance to install it without much difficulty. Our nursing team was successful at doing this.</p></li>
<li><p>The oncologist on-call was able to find a temporary pain solution.</p></li>
<li><p>The pain specialist team changed his main pain relieve medication and placed it on a constant infusion. Sam will also have a limited amount of addition pain relief available at the push of a button.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>A special thanks to our nursing team who advocated for Sam and took on all of the additional task needed to get Sam comfortable. Thank you especially to Ana and Molly.</p>
<section id="upcoming-today" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming-today">Upcoming today</h2>
<p>This morning we will prepare all of our stuff for the transition into the BMT isolation room. It all needs to be cleaned and stored following special protocols. The medical and cleaning teams here at the hospital will ensure that Sam’s room is spotless. We will need to make sure that anything we bring in does not contaminate it.</p>
<p>Sam should also be able to have one last outside visitor before the move into isolation.</p>
<p>We expect the actual move into isolation will be sometime in the mid-afternoon.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>There are many known and unknown concerns that will present themselves during the BMT process. Potential illness, establishment/engraftment of the donated bone-marrow/ stem cells. Numerous potential complications. We are thankful for a medical team that has a plan for all of it.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that it seems Sam’s pain management is now under control, including options to address any spikes in pain.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for friends that are able to visit.</p></li>
<li><p>It had been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity. It is hard to see him have this strength pulled away from him.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We have completed a major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy and targeted radiation. We now pivot to the bone marrow transplant – this current and upcoming treatments brings hope of removal of the disease but also anxiety about both the challenging process and the potential for long term side effects. We hope and pray that this treatment will be effective in beating the cancer for life.</p></li>
<li><p>It is flu season and covid is still out there. If any of us get sick it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he will be entering a phase where he has no immune system for weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>We are continually thankful for our medical teams here. They continue to provide incredible care. They are always open to conversation and answering questions. They have been incredibly pro-active and I am glad we are prepared for the next steps.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team has a huge coordination task ahead of them. From our meetings with them it seems all of the pieces are coming together, but with so many moving parts it is easy for things go wrong.</li>
<li>These last days leading up to the BMT are very busy with lots of drugs running all day. Concerns during this time are that everything is able to be delivered as planned and that Sam does not have any overly negative reactions to any of this.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Nasogastric tube to facilitate pumping liquid food (e.g.&nbsp;Boost) into Sam’s stomach.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <category>hospital</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-13_bmt-minus-1.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Immune and chemo therapies</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-12_bmt-minus-2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It is the middle of the night / early morning, Day minus 2 until Sam’s BMT. Sam is finally asleep. I don’t think he realized the level of pain he was in and it has taken about three hours to get a cap on it. Today will be another big day of immune therapy and chemotherapy drugs.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Update: Slept well!
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Sam woke up following a relatively short sleep but he slept really well. He was full of energy ready to take on the day!</p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="last-couple-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="last-couple-days">Last couple days</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Friday last day of radiation (day -4)</dt>
<dd>
<p>Sam completed his radiation therapy. This third day was much better then the days prior – no pain or nausea. Sam even had a burst of hyper energy in the evening and literally ran around the ward - excited to have completed the radiation phase.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Nana, Kevin, Shannon, and Kaden were able to come by for a visit. Nana is staying with Tina at the RMH for a few days – great to have her support!</p>
</dd>
<dt>Saturday fist day of immune and chemo therapies (day -3)</dt>
<dd>
<p>Sam’s immune suppression therapy began. It started with bringing in the big IV tower – it currently has 8 IV pumps with room to expand. Sam will have to push, pull, and drag this thing around for the next month or more. With the IV tower in place the immune therapy began. Numerous drugs were administered through the day. Later in the evening Sam received his chemotherapy drugs. So what’s all this mean for Sam?<br>
<br>
New therapies bring new and weird sensations. All of it causes fatigue. The return to chemotherapy is a hard reminder of how these drugs make his body ache and pain management becomes more challenging. I also recognize that while outside of the hospital we had incredible flexibility in pain management. The medical team at Canuck Place were able to consult with us at any time and had given us a lot of tools to manage pain. Here at the hospital it is more difficult as specific orders need to be written and the nurses are generally restricted to those orders. … changing them in the middle of the night on a long weekend can be done. It just not very easy.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>A couple of Sam’s friends are planning to pay a visit before he goes into isolation! It will be so good for Sam to see them. This whole process can be very isolating and it important for him to know that his friends are still there for him.</p>
<p>This Tuesday Sam should receive the transplant! The weeks following will focus on facilitating engraftment and managing his day to day health. None of this will be very easy especially given that he will have no immune defenses for a number of weeks.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam’s radiation sickness was brought under control. By the last day Sam was actually feeling great!</p></li>
<li><p>It has been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity. It is hard to see him have this strength pulled away from him.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We have completed a major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy and targeted radiation. We now pivot to the bone marrow transplant – this current and upcoming treatments brings hope of removal of the disease but also anxiety about both the challenging process and the potential for long term side effects. We hope and pray that this treatment will be effective in beating the cancer for life.</p></li>
<li><p>It is flu season and covid is still out there. If any of us get sick it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he will be entering a phase where he has no immune system for weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>We are continually thankful for our medical teams here. They continue to provide incredible care. They are always open to conversation and answering questions. They have been incredibly pro-active and I am glad we are prepared for the next steps.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the chemotherapy has been effective at initially reducing the cancer and keeping the cancer contained (as indicated by the PET scan). Thankful that these results allow us to move forward.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team has a huge coordination task ahead of them. From our meetings with them it seems all of the pieces are coming together, but with so many moving parts it is easy for things go wrong.</li>
<li>These last days leading up to the BMT are very busy with lots of drugs running all day. Concerns during this time are that everything is able to be delivered as planned and that Sam does not have any overly negative reactions to any of this.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <category>hospital</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-12_bmt-minus-2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Radiation sickness</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-09_radiation-sickness.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Update: Nov.&nbsp;10, 2023
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>By yesterday afternoon Sam was feeling himself again. Nausea and pain were under control and he has is appetite back! As a family we had a good time sharing the notes of encouragement that we have received from the recent post on Facebook.</p>
<p>Today Sam completes the TBI treatments.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>I am writing from BC Children’s Hospital, it is in the morning of Day -5 leading up to Sam’s bone marrow transplant (BMT; transplant day is Nov. 14). Yesterday Sam began his BMT conditioning treatments. This started with two rounds of total body irradiation (TBI) at 8:00am and 2:30pm. Following these treatments Sam was admitted, as planned, to the hospital.</p>
<p>The days leading up to the BMT will be full of various treatments to prepare Sam’s body to receive the donated bone marrow. We had expected this to be hard, but I had not expected it to be immediately hard. This new treatment has hit Sam with a new intensity. He has been nauseous and ill, has had distinct new pains, and slept most of the day and continues to sleep now. Talking with the doctors all of the new symptoms are common to the TBI.</p>
<p>Sam continues to be strong. Halfway through the afternoon treatment he was nauseated, he took a few minutes to puke, then with a let’s-do-this-determination positioned himself to complete the second half of that treatment.</p>
<section id="current-treatments" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="current-treatments">Current treatments</h2>
<p>The goal of these pre-transplant treatments are two-fold: 1) Make room for the donated material, and 2) Suppress Sam’s existing immune defenses to allow acceptance of the donated material.</p>
<section id="making-room" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="making-room">Making room</h3>
<p>Between today and tomorrow Sam will receive another four treatments of TBI. Over the weekend he will receive chemotherapy. The intent of these treatments will be permanently remove Sam’s native immune system. More specifically, the blood producing cells in his bone marrow will be destroyed to make room for the donated material. There will be no going back.</p>
</section>
<section id="immune-suppression" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="immune-suppression">Immune suppression</h3>
<p>Also on the weekend Sam will start receiving immune suppression treatments to prepare his body to receive the transplant material. Where the TBI and chemotherapy remove the body’s ability to generate <em>new blood</em> including immune system blood cells, the immune suppression therapy will manage the existing immune defenses. Sam’s existing mature immune defense cells will be suppressed so that they do no attack the donated material – facilitating the acceptance of the donated bone marrow.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Mid-day update
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>It has been half a day since I initially wrote this. This morning’s TBI therapy went much the same as yesterday’s. Since we have been back to the hospital the team here has made extra efforts to manage Sam’s symptoms. We should have a better visit to the BC Cancer clinic this afternoon.</p>
</div>
</div>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Immediate concerns for Sam: Sickness and pain from the total body irradiation (TBI).</p></li>
<li><p>It has been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity. It is hard to see him have this strength pulled away from him.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>We have completed a major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy and targeted radiation. We now pivot to the bone marrow transplant – this current and upcoming treatments brings hope of removal of the disease but also anxiety about both the challenging process and the potential for long term side effects. We hope and pray that this treatment will be effective in beating the cancer for life.</p></li>
<li><p>It is flu season and covid is still out there. If any of us get sick it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he will be entering a phase where he has no immune system for weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>We are continually thankful for our medical teams here. They continue to provide incredible care. They are always open to conversation and answering questions. They have been incredibly pro-active and I am glad we are prepared for the next steps.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the chemotherapy has been effective at initially reducing the cancer and keeping the cancer contained (as indicated by the PET scan). Thankful that these results allow us to move forward.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team has a huge coordination task ahead of them. From our meetings with them it seems all of the pieces are coming together, but with so many moving parts it is easy for things go wrong.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <category>hospital</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-09_radiation-sickness.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Sam is a Champion</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-05_champion.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/Chisholm2023-oliveandbeanphoto-9_sml.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The Chisholm family at the Ronald McDonald House. Fall 2023<sup>1</sup>.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Sam is a courageous champion! He has now endured and completed two types of cancer treatment, and is ready to take-on the upcoming bone marrow transplant (BMT). Over the past six months Sam’s treatments have focused on attacking the cancer cells within his body. He received six rounds of chemical chemotherapy between May and Oct.&nbsp;Over the last two weeks, following the completion of the initial chemotherapy treatment, tactics were changed to use radiation therapy against the largest detectable cancerous mass that remains in the center of his chest. The upcoming BMT will mark a significant change in strategy for removing the cancer. Instead of attacking the cancer directly the BMT will provide a long-term indirect assault on the cancer (long-term being life-long). This process will replace Sam’s immune system – removing his current native immune defenses and replacing them with a donated immune system. Where Sam’s immune system was not effective at detecting and attacking the cancer it is expected that the new immune system will. This process is not easy and Sam may face his greatest challenges to date. However, he is looking forward to completing these next phases.</p>
<p>There are currently 8 days until Sam receives the actual transplant. However, there are numerous steps/procedures to be completed to prepare his body for this process. This Wednesday he starts these steps.</p>
<section id="this-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="this-past-week">This past week</h2>
<section id="treatment" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="treatment">Treatment</h3>
<p>It is amazing to me how a short medical appointment can dominate an entire day. Monday through Friday this past week marked Sam’s second and final week of targeted radiation therapy to directly attack the main mass of cancer in his body. The actual procedure was usually not more than 15 minutes but it would dominate out entire day. Each day we would get ready, load up and head down to the BC Cancer clinic, a short drive away. Tina and Sam would check in while I attempted to find parking – there were a few days where Sam was done before I was able to park the van. Following treatment we would return to the RMH. Sam has generally felt well though with increasing fatigue. His medical team is happy with his current health: <em>He is an otherwise healthy young man, but with cancer.</em></p>
<p>We may never know the full impact that the radiation will have on the cancer. The radiation therapy can take weeks to show measurable impacts but by that point we will be well into the BMT process. I expect next scans to evaluate the various treatments and the state of the cancer will not be feasible until into the new year.</p>
</section>
<section id="visitors" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visitors">Visitors</h3>
<p>We were able to visit with and be encouraged by some family and friends this past week. Aunt Tricia put on an amazing meal. Uncle Cal paid a visit. Sam was able to have some time hanging out with cousin Kaden, while Tina and I visited with Kevin, Shannon, and Nana. Yesterday John, Jess, Kate, and John Jr.&nbsp;stopped by for a few hours. Tina was able to have and afternoon away visiting with her cousins in Abbotsford.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>This coming week will mark a point-of-no-return as Sam will have intense treatments to condition his body for the BMT – all the gains that have been made in returning Sam to feeling healthy will likely be ripped out from under him. These treatments include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Total body radiation</li>
<li>BMT Chemotherapy – intense chemo-drug therapy</li>
<li>Immune suppression drugs</li>
<li>The BMT transplant</li>
</ul>
<p>See the <a href="../../posts/2309/2023-09-19_courage-and-despair.html">previous post</a> or <a href="../../plan.html">The Plan</a> for the details.</p>
<p>Following the BMT medical efforts will focus on managing Sam’s day-to-day health and finding the balance of facilitating successful engraftment while suppressing graft-versus-host-disease impacts. To complicate matters symptoms of graft-versus-host-disease are easily confused or even synonymous with the flu, colds, or other infections which he will also be highly susceptible to – the medical team will have to be highly vigilant.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>It has been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity.</p></li>
<li><p>We have completed a major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy and targeted radiation. We now pivot to the bone marrow transplant – this next treatment brings hope of removal of the disease but also anxiety about both the challenging process and the potential for long term side effects. We hope and pray that this treatment will be effective in beating the cancer for life.</p></li>
<li><p>It is flu season and covid is still out there. In the weeks ahead, as a family, we will be more cautious to reduce our risk of getting ill.&nbsp;If any of us get sick in the weeks ahead it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he will be entering a phase where he has no immune system for weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>We are continually thankful for our medical teams here. They continue to provide incredible care. They are always open to conversation and answering questions. They have been incredibly pro-active and I am glad we are prepared for the next steps.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the chemotherapy has been effective at initially reducing the cancer and keeping the cancer contained (as indicated by the PET scan). Thankful that these results allow us to move forward.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team has a huge coordination task ahead of them. From our meetings with them it seems all of the pieces are coming together, but with so many moving parts it is easy for things go wrong.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Photography facilitated by the Ronald McDonald House taken by <a href="https://www.oliveandbeanphoto.com">Olive and Bean Photography</a>↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-05_champion.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Targeted Radiation</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-29_counting-down.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It is <em>Day -15</em> as we count down the days towards Sam’s bone marrow transplant (BMT).</p>
<section id="this-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="this-past-week">This past week</h2>
<section id="treatment" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="treatment">Treatment</h3>
<p>Sam is currently in his targeted radiation phase, which is intended to directly attack the main mass of cancer in his body. Each day this past week we went to the BC Cancer clinic at Vancouver General Hospital (VGH). During each visit the technician would use a mold of Sam to get him into position. The mold extends from below his shoulders up over his head and they use it to literally pin him to the treatment table ensuring that he is in the exact same position each time – thereby ensuring the radiation focuses on the intended area.</p>
<p>Sam is doing well with it all. Sam is now over thirty days away from the previous chemo-drug treatments and his strength is returning. He is a generally healthy young man, but with cancer. This is where we want him to be – as healthy and as strong as possible before starting the BMT.</p>
<p>So far the only side effect from the radiation therapy has been fatigue. It is different than chemo-fatigue which caused him to not have any energy, be nauseated, and caused brain fog. This radiation induced fatigue is the need to sleep, but once awake Sam usually has energy to go for walks and enjoy his life.</p>
</section>
<section id="visitors" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visitors">Visitors</h3>
<p>We had a good number of family and friends visiting with us this past week. Not everyone got to see Sam as he is being very cautious about seeing people – he is also training Tina and I to do the same as we all mask up more and more. Visitors included:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Gram and Papa spent some great time with Sam prior to heading home this past Monday</p></li>
<li><p>Nana, now living in the area, was able to come by for the Thursday afternoon.</p></li>
<li><p>Uncle Kevin and cousin Kaden were able to be here for a few hours. I love it when Sam and Kaden have a chance to hang out.</p></li>
<li><p>Friday morning I had a great visit with Aaron W.</p></li>
<li><p>Friday afternoon we spent some good time, Colin with Rob, and Tina with Leanne D. They also delivered some great messages of support from our church family in Prince George – thank you all!</p></li>
<li><p>Yesterday evening we were able to get away from the RMH and spend the evening with family out in Langley – celebrating our nieces birthdays. We are so fortunate to have family close by.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>Today Sam returns to his targeted radiation therapy. It highly likely that the impacts of this treatment will become more distinct with increasing levels of fatigue and potentially skin and esophagus irritation.</p>
<p>Next week after will be more difficult as Sam will have more intense treatments to condition his body for the BMT – all the gains that have been made in returning Sam to feeling healthy will likely be ripped out from under him. These treatments include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Total body radiation</li>
<li>BMT Chemotherapy – intense chemo-drug therapy</li>
<li>Immune suppression drugs</li>
<li>The BMT transplant</li>
</ul>
<p>See the <a href="../../posts/2309/2023-09-19_courage-and-despair.html">previous post</a> or <a href="../../plan.html">The Plan</a> for the details.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>It has been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity.</p></li>
<li><p>We have completed a major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy we now pivot to the bone marrow treatment plan – this next treatment brings hope of removal of the disease but also anxiety about both the challenging process and the potential for long term side effects.</p></li>
<li><p>It is the beginning of flu season and covid is still out there. In the weeks ahead, as a family, we will be more cautious to reduce our risk of getting ill.&nbsp;If any of us get sick in the weeks ahead it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he will be entering a phase where he has no immune system for weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>We are continually thankful for our medical teams here. They continue to provide incredible care. They are always open to conversation and answering questions. They have been incredibly pro-active and I am glad we are prepared for the next steps.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the chemotherapy has been effective at initially reducing the cancer and lately keeping the cancer contained (as indicated by the PET scan). Thankful that these results allow us to move forward.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team has a huge coordination task ahead of them. From out meetings with them it seems all of the pieces are coming together, but with so many moving parts it is easy for things go wrong.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-29_counting-down.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>On a knife’s edge</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-18_knife-edge-no-assurances.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-10-20_visitors.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A few of our visitors – so great to have you here!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
<p>In my last post I tried to keep things to a clinical picture. Here I will attempt to capture a little of what it is to live through this cancer journey and to provide more detail on what the upcoming process may look like.</p>
<p>From the latest results, <a href="../../posts/2309/2023-10-15_Results-round-6.html">last post</a>, It feels like we are walking along a knife’s edge separating life and hope on the one side, from doubt, fear, and death on the other. This is not simply a feeling. This is a reality as the results are not great, though they are good enough to keep going.</p>
<section id="good-results-good-enough-results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="good-results-good-enough-results"><del>Good results?</del> Good <em>enough</em> results</h2>
<p>Are the results good? Yes – in that we get to keep going, and that there is hope that the treatment will work. However, there are no assurances, and Sam is not in an ideal state for entering the next phases of treatment.</p>
<p>Sam’s cancer is unique, and our medical team is using their best judgment, but none of them have battled this cancer before. They have found a single reference to it, but that has only provided a little guidance.</p>
<p>The medical team is battling hard for Sam and their strategies to date have initially reduced, and more recently kept the cancer from growing. However, compared with known cancers this cancer has not responded as well as any of us have wanted.</p>
</section>
<section id="not-an-ideal-plan" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="not-an-ideal-plan">Not an ideal plan</h2>
<p>We are moving forward with a bone-marrow-transplant (BMT), but we are not in an ideal situation. Ideally, and for best results, when moving to BMT the medical team would like the cancer to be non-detectable. With Sam, starting from where he was back in April, the cancerous mass has been reduced in size, but a significant mass remains. It is not operable as it is in the lymphatic system; although it can be located, as I understand it, it is too amorphous and intertwined within his healthy tissues and bear vital organs (e.g.&nbsp;heart and lungs).</p>
<section id="challenges-ahead" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="challenges-ahead">Challenges ahead</h3>
<p>In the weeks ahead Sam will be facing a number of challenges (see <a href="../../plan.html">The Plan</a>).</p>
<dl>
<dt>Radiation therapy – phase 1: <em>Targeted radiation</em></dt>
<dd>
<p>The objective here is to directly attack the cancer and destroy as much as possible. There are both immediate and long term challenges. The radiation oncologist is trying to balance attacking the cancer while protecting the adjacent lungs which are very sensitive to radiation damage. In the short term there will be fatigue and pain – think of a time that you had a bad sun burn. Now take that sunburn and put it on the inside of your body. Sam may feel it most in his throat.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Radiation therapy – phase 2: <em>Total body irradiation (TBI)</em></dt>
<dd>
<p>Next, Sam will undergo three days of total body radiation (TBI). This radiation will not target his cancer, rather it is undertaken to condition his body for the upcoming bone marrow transplant. TBI has the objective of permanently destroying Sam’s native immune system so that his immune system will not compete with the transplant.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>There is a long list of potential side effects from the two radiation treatments. A few of these include: permanent scarring of the lungs, impacts on the thyroid, heart disease, changes to metabolism, secondary cancers, and others. Needless to say this can be scary.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>This step, in conjunction with the following BMT Chemotherapy, mark a point of no return. Once these steps are initiated a transplant must happen for Sam to ever have an immune system again.</p>
</dd>
<dt>BMT Chemotherapy</dt>
<dd>
<p>The previous chemotherapy that Sam has had focused on targeting and removing the disease. This upcoming chemotherapy has a different objective. In conjunction with TBI it will be used to remove Sam’s own immune system. Following this chemotherapy any cells that produce/create blood will have been killed, and Sam’s bone marrow will be ready to receive the transplant. As with most chemotherapy drugs this treatment will likely make Sam feel ill.</p>
</dd>
<dt>The transplant/graft</dt>
<dd>
<p>On Nov.&nbsp;14<sup>th</sup> Sam is scheduled to receive the donated bone marrow. The donated cells will need to establish or engraft to start providing Sam his new immune system. In the 2-3 weeks following receiving the transplant we will wait in anticipation for signs that the graft is taking hold. The whole transplant process will take place in an isolation room – Sam will not be allowed to leave until his new immune system takes hold. Tina and I will be able to gown-up and be with him.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>This will be a hard number of weeks. Given the prior steps Sam will likely feel horrible for numerous weeks. It is highly likely that he will need significant intravenous supports for management of pain, nausea, engraftment of the new immune system, hydration, nutrition, and then potentially additional medication should he become ill without an immune system to support him. To provide all of these supports Sam may need upward of 15 different intravenous lines to all be connected at once. His current central lines should support most of this.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Once the graft takes hold it will start generating Sam’s new immune system and start fighting for him, including battling the cancer. However, this is a foreign immune system and steps will need to be taken ensure that the graft does not attack Sam – potential graft versus host disease. The graft also must remain aggressive enough to continually attach the cancer.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
</section>
<section id="choosing-hope" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="choosing-hope">Choosing hope</h2>
<p>There are many reasons to be consumed by fear – to allow the beast of Despair to have a foothold in our lives. Sure we have our moments of anxiety – but we choose hope. Sam remains a champion. We have also laid out some great ideas for his time in isolation – I hope he will feel well enough to take part in the activities we have planned.</p>
<p>We invite you to choose hope with us. It does make this journey easier knowing that you are there with us in mind and spirit. Please continue in your commitment to care and prayer.</p>
</section>
<section id="highlights-from-this-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights-from-this-past-week">Highlights from this past week</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Visits</dt>
<dd>
<p>David and Beth H. came down. So good to see Sam be able to spend time with a friend in person!</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>We invited Nana over for a sleep-over. Although she now lives in the area it was great to have her here with us like before she moved.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Gram and Papa C. arrived yesterday evening. Great to have them here and have their in-person support.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Sam’s Energy</dt>
<dd>
<p>We have not seen Sam have this much energy since well before we left home. The cancer has been set back and he has had a week long break between treatments. It definitely shows how the chemotherapy has been relentless.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Sam has had renewed energy to take on some academics, to build Lego, to tease his parents (…I am happy about that? Right?…). So good to see him have more physical and mental capacity.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>It has been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity.</p></li>
<li><p>We have completed a major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy we now pivot to the bone marrow treatment plan – this next treatment brings hope of removal of the disease but also anxiety about both the challenging process and the potential for long term side effects.</p></li>
<li><p>It is the beginning of flu season and covid is still out there. In the weeks ahead, as a family, we will be very cautious to reduce our risk of getting ill.&nbsp;If any of us get sick in the weeks ahead it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he will be entering a phase where he has no immune system for weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>We are continually thankful for our medical teams here. They continue to provide incredible care. They are always open to conversation and answering questions. They have been incredibly pro-active and I am glad we are prepared for the next steps.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the chemotherapy has been effective at initially reducing the cancer and lately keeping the cancer contained (as indicated by the PET scan). Thankful that these results allow us to move forward.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. All the pieces need to fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-18_knife-edge-no-assurances.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Round 6 results and next steps</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-15_Results-round-6.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>This past Friday Sam had a number of appointments, starting with a PET scan first thing in the morning. A PET scan provides 3-dimensional imagery of where the cancer is in the body, and metrics of how metabolically active the cancer is. We have been anxious for the results of this scan as the data would provide direction for the next steps in Sam’s treatment. At clinic, in the afternoon, the results were back – and confirmed the direction that we are going.</p>
<section id="good-results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="good-results">Good results?</h2>
<p>For Tina and I, and likely many of you, we hoped for a miraculously good results – that following these latest two rounds of chemotherapy the cancerous mass would finally collapse and be non-detectable. We do not have that result.</p>
<p>At the end of August, following the completion of round four, the medical team communicated their plans to pivot towards a bone marrow transplant<sup>1</sup>. At that time it seemed evident that the cancer would not fully respond to the planned six rounds of chemotherapy. This is the result we have.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>The last two rounds of chemotherapy have held the cancer. The mass is stable – it has not grown and it has not spread anywhere new. … Although the cancer has not had any significant decrease in size, the chemotherapy regime that Sam has been under has been effective at holding the cancer back long enough to prepare the BMT process. We also know that the BMT process is the next best step as the now completed chemotherapy was no longer effective at reducing the disease.</p></li>
<li><p>The result are what the medical team hoped and planned for. Plans were initiated over seven weeks ago to prepare for this outcome. If the cancer had grown or spread our conversations with the medical team could have been very different.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>The results are good – as they support <a href="../../plan.html">the plan</a>.<br>
The results are also challenging as a hard road lays ahead.</p>
</section>
<section id="highlights-from-this-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights-from-this-past-week">Highlights from this past week</h2>
<section id="appointments" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="appointments">Appointments</h3>
<p>Lots of tests and appointments this past week.</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<table class="table table-striped table-sm small" data-quarto-postprocess="true">
<caption>Tests and appointments completed this past week. Most of these were to create baseline measurements of Sam before starting the BMT treatment protocols. </caption>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;" data-quarto-table-cell-role="th">Activity</th>
<th style="text-align: left;" data-quarto-table-cell-role="th">Complete</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Eye Exam</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Renal medical imaging</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Bone marrow biopsy and Lumbar Puncture</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Hearing assessment</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Pulmonary Function Test</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Partial</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">PET Scan</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Ultrasound of neck (state of blood-clots)</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Dental Assessment</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Dermatology</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="visits" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visits">Visits</h3>
<p>Sam has been able to connect with friends online.</p>
<p>Friday afternoon Sam and his Uncle Cal had a great connection remembering and celebrating Papa Gord together.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>For the most part Sam may have much of this coming week off. There will be clinic visits but the intent of the medical team is to give his body a break and get him as strong as we can before the BMT process starts.</p>
<p>We are looking forward to visits with friends and family.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We have finished the week strong – despite a long list of bookings we made it through and Sam is in good spirits.</p></li>
<li><p>We have completed a major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy we now pivot to the bone marrow treatment plan.</p></li>
<li><p>It is the beginning of flu season and covid is still out there. In the weeks ahead, as a family, we will be very cautious to reduce our risk of getting ill.&nbsp;If any of us get sick in the weeks ahead it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he will be entering a phase where he has no immune system for weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>I am continually thankful for our medical teams here. They continue to provide incredible care. They are always open to conversation and answering questions. They have been incredibly pro-active and I am glad we are prepared for the next steps.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the chemotherapy has been effective at initially reducing the cancer and lately keeping the cancer contained (as indicated by the PET scan). Thankful that these results allow us to move forward.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. All the pieces need to fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>See <a href="../../posts/2308/2023-08-26_results-and-recommendations.html">Aug.&nbsp;26 post</a> for the round 4 results↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-15_Results-round-6.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PET this morning</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-13_pending-PET-scan.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="pet-scan" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pet-scan">PET Scan</h2>
<p>Sam has a PET scan first thing this morning. This scan is the best tool for imaging the state of his cancer and how his chemotherapy has progressed. Decisions moving forward will be based on the results of this scan.</p>
<p>Needless to say, all of us, including the medical team, are anxious for the results. Preliminary findings may be available by the end of the day but the full report will not be available until next week.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Although we did not want to be in-hospital over this weekend we are glad that Sam’s health is so well guarded by the team here.</p></li>
<li><p>We are closing off this first major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy we will pivot to the bone marrow treatment plan.</p></li>
<li><p>That we would have enough strength/stamina, especially for Sam, as we are booked solid preparing for the BMT.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>We are thankful for a donor who is a match for Sam and that they are willing to undergo the full bone marrow extraction process!</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. All the pieces need to fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-13_pending-PET-scan.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Thankfulness in this journey</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-09_thanks-giving.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/supercars.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A Supercars event at the RMH. We got to explore and ride in some amazing cars</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="giving-thanks" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="giving-thanks">Giving thanks</h2>
<p>It is early morning here at BC Children’s hospital and my family is sleeping peacefully. In-hospital is not where we had hoped to be this Thanks Giving, as family in the area were hoping to host us. It would have been great to share a meal, visit with them, and catch up the additional nephews that had flown in. Despite our current situation we still have so much to be thankful for. Top of my mind:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>We are here and we have access to an incredible medical team and facility.</p></li>
<li><p>We are able to walk this journey as a family. Support from work, family and friends, church, and the local community allows us to be here without having to worry about life and responsibilities back home. Thank you!</p></li>
<li><p>The Ronald McDonald House provides us a home away from home.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has been able to connect with friends – especially in the last couple weeks. They talked or talked while playing online games.</p></li>
<li><p>Visitors: We have family in the area that come by on a regular basis to support us. We have friends that make extra efforts to some and see us.</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="highlights-from-this-past-week" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights-from-this-past-week">Highlights from this past week</h3>
<dl>
<dt>Baseline tests and clinic days</dt>
<dd>
<p>As we begin to wrap up round 6 and pivot to bone-marrow transplant there are many medical appointments. This week was full with regular clinic visits plus the addition of baseline tests.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Thursday Nana and Kevin visit</dt>
<dd>
<p>Kevin and I got away – we roamed around downtown and grabbed dinner. It was great to away from the hospital campus for a few hours.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Nana visited with Sam and Tina at the Ronald McDonald House. Following the loss of Gord, Mary has moved south where she is surrounded by family and can access Sam. She in a suite attached to Kevin and Shannon’s.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Friday’s fever</dt>
<dd>
<p>It was a normal clinic visit on Friday morning. We had gone in expecting to review blood levels and then return to the RMH. However, Sam spiked a fever. In a normal non-cancer scenario any of us would just sleep it off, but Sam’s immune system is compromised. Antibiotics were started, tests and bacterial cultures were ordered, and plans were made to admit Sam to the ward for this past weekend. We are hoping/expecting to be discharged later today to return to the RMH.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Dave and Louise SP, friends of ours working in SE Asia were able to stop by before catching their flight back. Great to catch up with and be encouraged by them.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Supercars Saturday</dt>
<dd>
<p>One of the other parents at the RMH was able to connect with a group of Supercar owners. We thought we might miss-out but the doctor here gave Sam an afternoon pass to take part. We were able to talk with the owners, look at, sit in, and got for some quick rides in these beautiful cars. Makes included Ferrari, Lamborghini, McLaren, and Mercedes. I think whenever I see one of these cars on the road I will always remember the joy on all the families faces and the hospitality of all the owners.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>This week is very full includes:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Clinic check-ins</p></li>
<li><p>Tuesday: Bone marrow biopsy and Lumbar puncture – to confirm that cancer continues to not be present in Sam’s bones or central nervous system</p></li>
<li><p>Wednesday will start with a consult with a radiation oncologist (doctor specializing in the use of radiation therapy to combat cancer). This will be followed by Resporatory function and hearing tests – to establish baseline metrics before the bone marrow transplant</p></li>
<li><p>Friday: PET Scan to determine the current state of Sam’s cancer – though the results will not be available until the following week. \</p>
<p>This will be followed by an ultrasound of Sam’s neck where heavy blood clotting was found associated with the cancer. It is expected that these clots have been reduced.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Although we did not want to be in-hospital over this weekend we are glad that Sam’s health is so well guarded by the team here.</p></li>
<li><p>We are closing off this first major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy we will pivot to the bone marrow treatment plan.</p></li>
<li><p>That we would have enough strength/stamina, especially for Sam, as we are booked solid preparing for the BMT.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>We are thankful for a donor who is a match for Sam and that they are willing to undergo the full bone marrow extraction process!</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. All the pieces need to fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-09_thanks-giving.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Remembrance of Papa Gord</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-02_remembrance.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="last-goodbyes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="last-goodbyes">Last goodbyes</h2>
<p>Last week was hard but beautiful.</p>
<p>On Friday Sept.&nbsp;29 at 11:00am Papa Gord (Tina’s Dad) passed on to eternity. He was surrounded by his family: Mary, Cal &amp; Tricia, Shannon &amp; Kevin, and Tina. Sam and I had to stay here at the RMH but we were also able to have final conversations, express our love, and say our goodbyes with Gord (via FaceTime). The other grandchildren were able to say goodbye via facetime as well.</p>
<p>Mary and Gord have given us an incredible legacy of love and commitment. It is and will be hard losing Gord though it was beautiful to share in the love of the family as they were able to spend a number of days with Gord before the end.</p>
<section id="the-week-in-review" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-week-in-review">The week in review</h3>
<dl>
<dt>Tuesday – a whirlwind of day.</dt>
<dd>
<p>It started with a big clinic day including lots of time with Dr. Jacob, the team lead of the BMT team, providing us a review of the process going forward. During this conversation Tina was fielding various communications regarding her dad, that he was in ER in Prince George.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Great news from this day was that there is a bone marrow donor for Sam, and the donor is willing to undergo the bone marrow extraction process. This is great news for Sam’s path of healing.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>By mid-afternoon flights were booked and in the evening Tina’s brother Cal and his wife Tricia picked Tina up to head for the airport where they met Tina’s sister Shannon and her husband Kevin – the five of them travelled to Prince George to see Gord. While they were en route Sam and I had a good FaceTime conversation with Papa Gord.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Wednesday – Thursday</dt>
<dd>
<p>Gord, though responsive, was not going to recover. By the end of day on Wed. he was transferred to Hospice. The siblings and Tina’s mom Mary, spent great quality time with Gord – sharing loving memories.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Back at the RMH Sam and I kept going with medications, pain control, and connected with the family in Prince George. Mucositis was really bad these days.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Friday</dt>
<dd>
<p>The family had a few more hours with Gord and at ~11:00am he entered eternity.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Here in Vancouver, Sam and I were in clinic, including meetings with different doctors and a blood transfusion, when we received word about Papa’s passing.</p>
<p>Sam is happy, though with tears, for Papa to be free of his declining body. Sam spoke words of hope to Papa, about seeing him again in heaven and sharing great experiences there (e.g.&nbsp;fishing and golfing together). Gord’s beautiful strong and gentle soul will be missed here.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Saturday – Sunday</dt>
<dd>
<p>The Prince George team made final arrangements for Gord and began their travels back to the lower mainland, bringing Mary with them to stay at Shannon’s home and be near family. Tina got back to us on Sunday afternoon.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Saturday night was a rough one for Sam and I. Sam hit the limit on what I was allowed to give him for pain control. Help was just a phone-call away. The on-call oncologist provided me additional pain control instructions and I was so glad to hear Sam gently snoring by early morning. Plans were also put in place to visit the hospital during the day – Sam got a blood transfusion.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>This week includes:</p>
<ul>
<li>regular clinic visits – and likely more blood products</li>
<li>more planning for the BMT</li>
<li>Some medical imaging as the medical teams create a baseline of Sam – essential for determining impacts of the radiation and BMT process.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that Tina and her siblings were able to make it back home and spend quality time with Papa Gord. Please keep the family in mind.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam has been able to connect with a number of friends from back home via online discussion tools and games.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that when things do get difficult (e.g.&nbsp;pain management and low blood levels) help is only a phone call away. The medical team here at BC Childrens continue to be amazing.</p></li>
<li><p>Chemotherapy continues to take its toll. His energy levels are lower with each round. As with previous rounds Sam’s blood counts are falling and mucositis has set in. We hope that that these side effects will be less intense and that they can be short lived – that Sam does not have to feel gross.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>We are thankful for a donor who is a match for Sam and that they are willing to undergo the full bone marrow extraction process!</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. All the pieces need to fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-02_remembrance.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
