<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Sam Chisholm</title>
<link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>News updating friends and family on our journey</description>
<generator>quarto-1.2.335</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>PICCs and other procedures</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-09_PICCs-procedures.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Sam and I are both up. Sam is in good spirits having had a sound sleep last night. It must have been a quality sleep because it certainly was not a long one … we should both take naps today. Last night we watched a very disappointing hockey game and then had a gaming session. I confess it got later than it should and Tina was not here to put a stop to it. She went to have a full night sleep at the <a href="https://rmhbc.ca">RMDH</a> and I hope that she is able to sleep well into the morning. As I write this Sam is reading a classic – if you know that the answer is <code>42</code> then you know the series he just started.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-8" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-8">Reflections on May 8</h2>
<p>To start the day we thought it would be rather simple and that the afternoon would be relaxed… It wasn’t all bad though there are some concerning elements, it just did not all go as planned. The bulk of the day</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>To start Sam did go under general anesthetic to adjust his <a href="http://www.cw.bc.ca/library/pdf/pamphlets/BCCH1552_PICC.pdf">PICC-line</a> and complete a lumbar puncture. The PICC procedure did not go the way the medical team had hoped. The plan was simply to adjust the position of the existing line, but they were not able to do this so they pulled that line and attempted a new line on the other arm. This new line also did not go as planned, as they were not able to centrally locate the outlet. This is where there is some concern, attempts to (re)position the previous or locate the current line failed due to blood clots in Sam’s system. No one is very clear as to why he has clots so frequently in his blood vessels (to be clear this is not because they are keeping anything from us … it is just they do not know). We know that some of the clots are an effect of the cancer – as the body tried to fight it; alternately, this clotting could be somehow related to the previous chemotherapy. The fact is there is clotting in Sam’s blood vessels, and there is more clotting than a couple weeks ago despite taking blood thinners twice a day.</p></li>
<li><p>The lumbar puncture went as planned.</p></li>
<li><p>The quiet afternoon turned into an additional procedure. The previous scans had focused on the upper chest and neck. This ultrasound was done to evaluate the potential of clotting in the abdomen and legs. Results are pending.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>We were finally back to the room by about 4pm. Time for dinner. I had left overs. A friend had brought poke bowls yesterday and the left over one as almost as good as the first. Sam had a hospital dinner supplemented with snacks from Safeway. Tina was off on her own adventure.</p>
<p>I am so happy for Tina as she was able to get away yesterday afternoon. Senga was here and she took her out to a local park and then out for a Tina-friendly meal.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam has a new PICC, despite not being placed idealy it should work.</p></li>
<li><p>Concerns around clotting in Sam’s blood vessels. He is on blood thinners but there appear be more clots than a couple weeks ago.</p></li>
<li><p>We are expecting to meet with the Dr.&nbsp;Cheng this afternoon to discuss recent results and plans for Sam’s next round of chemotherapy – which may start tomorrow.</p></li>
<li><p>Joyful for connections with friends – in person and through communication.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-09_PICCs-procedures.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ambassadors from Prince George</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-08_PG-ambassadors.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/20230506_sam-hunter-cedars.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Great visits with Hunter this past weekend. Hunter also brought gifts from friends in Prince George. Sam is looking forward to cashing in a gift card for some chicken nuggets.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This morning as I write, I am also chatting with my boy. He is in great spirits. He is also hungry: <em>This smile will be a lot bigger when I get food</em>. In a couple hours Sam will have a procedure to adjust the internal position of his PICC (so no food allowed until after the procedure). The medical team is also hoping while he is under general anesthetic he will also get a lumbar puncture to continue monitoring Sam’s health there.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-the-weekend" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-the-weekend">Reflections on the weekend</h2>
<p>This past weekend we had some great visits with friends from Prince George. Hunter and Sam have been great friends since grade 1. It was great to have him visit, and to see these friends reconnect, talk and laugh. Hunter, also acted as an ambassador delivering gifts to Sam from his class, and another bag of gifts for Tina and I – friends sent us some cozy clothes.</p>
<p>Yesterday our good friends Beth H. was also able to visit bringing gifts from her family. I also love how she was able to bring refreshment to Tina’s soul.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam goes under general anesthetic this am (~9:30) to adjust his PICC and possibly a lumbar puncture.</p></li>
<li><p>We are encouraged that the results from last Friday were so positive – with a 40% reduction in the size of the tumor. We also remain hopeful that the cancer will continue to be responsive to treatment.</p></li>
<li><p>We continue to feel loved an supported. Friends want to be here with us, and send there love when they cannot. Friends, family, and a broader community of support continue to send their love.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-08_PG-ambassadors.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/20230506_sam-hunter-cedars.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Response to the first round of chemotherapy</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-06_results-1st-chemotherapy.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Yesterday, Sam finished his first round of chemotherapy his final round of drugs. Mid-morning he had a CT scan. In the afternoon we had a visit with Dr.&nbsp;Cheng to discuss the results and the next steps. Being that Sam’s cancer is very rare we did not know if it would respond to the chemotherapy. I am so glad to say that it has.</p>
<ul>
<li>The size of the main tumor in Sam’s chest has seen an estimated 40% reduction in size.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is excellent news – though there is much work to be done. It has been amazing to see Sam’s body respond so well this past week and to know that the cancer was reduced in size. With these results in, the beginnings of a plan can be made, and we have an idea of what the next couple weeks will look like.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>This coming Monday Sam will have two procedures.</p>
<ul>
<li>Adjustments to his PICC line. Initial problems with the PICC resolved – how or why remain unclear, but the result was that regular blood tests (on average about every 8 hours) were taken easily via the PICC line. Going forward, the PICC need some re-positioning to allow for the safe delivery of the next round of chemotherapy.</li>
<li>A lumbar puncture to confirm that the caner continues to not be in the central nervous system (there is some concern that this form of cancer could migrate there). Dr.&nbsp;will also inject chemotherapy medications into the spinal fluid as a preventative measure.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Tuesday, Dr.&nbsp;Cheng will be presenting Sam’s case and consulting with other experts in the field. That afternoon, the we should know the plan for the next round of chemotherapy.</p></li>
<li><p>Wednesday, the next week of chemotherapy should begin.</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Excellent results from the first week of chemotherapy.</p></li>
<li><p>On the flip-side, there is much work to be done to further reduce and ultimately remove the cancer. There is always a possibility that the disease adapts and stops responding</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for an amazing community of people around us. We have been encouraged and gifted beyond what we could have ever expected.</p></li>
<li><p>Yesterday we spent time as a family simply listing things that we are thankful for. It was a beautiful time.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-06_results-1st-chemotherapy.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2023 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Anticipation of next steps</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-05_anticipation.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>This morning’s run of pills will mark the end of Sam’s first round of chemotherapy. At 9:30 Sam is scheduled for a CT scan and we will wait in anticipation for the results, as the scan will help inform our next steps including: 1) the need (or not) of a new central line for drug delivery, and 2) response of the cancer so far and a strategy moving forward.</p>
<section id="reflection-on-may-4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflection-on-may-4">Reflection on May 4</h2>
<p>Sam was full of energy and he was determined to show the physiotherapist all that he could do. We went for a couple of walks including getting off the floor and getting outside. Sam was also able to be disconnected from his IV and we are all loving the freedom that comes with that.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>CT scan today, the information will be used to determine next steps.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam is mobile and regaining strength. So great to have a break from IV line.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern that the cancer responds well to the treatment and wisdom for the next steps.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-05_anticipation.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Clarifying… from what I understand</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-04_current-understanding.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/img/230504_sunrise.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Sunrise from BC Children’s Hospital... Finally providing the ‘room with a view’ picture.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It looks like another beautiful sunny day here in Vancouver. The sun is just coming up over the mountains and is beaming into Sam’s room. These early morning hours are usually my as my family sleeps, and I take time to think, to pray, and to write. Not really no changes from yesterday we continue to slide into this pattern of routine. Nurses will be by to check-in, other members of the medical team will be what feels like randomly, as they move around the hospital checking on all their patients. Life as a patient definitely requires just that patience as you are either waiting for news, waiting for next steps, or generally having life interrupted. Don’t get me wrong, the care Sam is receiving is incredible. Being a patient is just a minor challenge in this process.</p>
<section id="clarifying-from-what-i-understand" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="clarifying-from-what-i-understand">Clarifying, from what I understand</h2>
<p>It really has been encouraging to see Sam come back, the return of his humor, his appetite, desires to do things. This morning, I want to explain my understanding of what has been happening with him. Before arriving, Sam was very sick, having extreme lethargy, and barely able to get out of bed. His body’s immune system was on overdrive in effort to battle what we now know is the cancer. The effect of this was that his whole body inflamed – think of a time that you had a small cut or burn and your skin was red and a little puffy around the injury… now take that idea and apply it to inside Sam’s body, and the majority of the lymphatic system. So why is he so much better now? Why does the treatment seem to be working so well? Is Sam healing?</p>
<p>Treatment started this past Friday, six days ago, and by the end of Saturday Sam was already feeling much better. This is actually an expected response. I am unclear if how dramatic the response is was expected, but the medical team did expect a fairly rapid response. One of the drugs that is part of Sam chemotherapy <em>prednisone</em>, which can be used to change the way the body ’s immune system reacts – effectively taking the immune system out of overdrive and reducing all that internal swelling.</p>
<p>So is Sam getting better? Sam is definitely feeling better and has a much improved quality of life, and I hope and pray that he is getting better in the long term. However, I need to be clear, when it comes to the cancer in his body, we just do not know.</p>
<p>Sam is now scheduled for a scan tomorrow morning. We will know more once those results are in.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are stunned, blessed, blown-away by the generosity of so many through the <a href="https://www.gofundme.com/f/help-the-chisholm-family-while-sam-battles-cancer">GoFundMe</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam’s has had the return of mobility and an appetite. Walking around a little yesterday was encouraging but I also recognize that Sam has lost alot of strength, which we will need to see him build back.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern that the cancer responds well to the treatment.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-04_current-understanding.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://samc-news.netlify.app/img/230504_sunrise.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Current plans</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-03_current-plans.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It is Wednesday morning, day 15, I just arrived at the hospital having had a full night sleep. My family is sleeping, and it appears that I was not missed overnight – so good.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-2" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-2">Reflections on May 2</h2>
<p>Breakfast this am was a beautiful surprise, as friends from Prince George ordered us an amazing breakfast from Juliet’s Cafe including a Tina friendly version. The remainder of the morning was a parade of various members of the medical team. This included a visit with Dr.&nbsp;Cheng, Sam’s oncologist – we reviewed the plan going forward with her (below).</p>
<p>The afternoon and evening was similar with various visits. I got out for a couple hours to do some shopping to gear us up to live here. A carry-on bag of cloths was just not enough and we all needed some new socks. Tomorrow I will get out to stock up on snacks – as our boy’s appetite continues to strengthen. In the evening, the three of us got out onto a deck and watched the sunset.</p>
</section>
<section id="plans" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="plans">Plans</h2>
<p>Sam’s treatment plan does not extend very far. Here is what I currently know… though plans change based on numerous factors.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Currently, Sam is mid-way through his first round of chemotherapy.</li>
<li>On Friday, he will go for a scan. The purpose of this will be two-fold
<ol type="a">
<li>To evaluate the response of the cancer to the current treatment</li>
<li>To evaluate if PICC to determine if it will work for delivering future treatment.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>On Monday, Sam may have to have place a new central line.</li>
</ol>
<p>That’s it! We have an idea of what the next five days may hold. The medical team does not know what the steps are beyond as they do not have the data. Although it would be nice to know what Sam is in for, what challenges he may have to face, I appreciate that decisions are being made based on the information available. When more is known, informed decisions can be made.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Umm, Wow! We are stunned, blessed, blown-away by the generosity of so many as evidenced by the <a href="https://www.gofundme.com/f/help-the-chisholm-family-while-sam-battles-cancer">GoFundMe</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Needles: Sam is doing really well with them. Though the potential of installing a new central line (PICC) is a challenging thought.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam’s has had the return of mobility and an appetite.</p></li>
<li><p>Concern that the cancer responds well to the treatment.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-03_current-plans.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Humbled by generosity</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-02_humbled-assistance.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="gofundme-insert" style="float: right; width: 50%; padding: 0 0pt 3pt 6pt; min-width: 320px;">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/img/family_2022.jpg" style="width: 100%; border: solid 1px #c8c8c8"></p>
<div class="gfm-embed" data-url="https://www.gofundme.com/f/help-the-chisholm-family-while-sam-battles-cancer/widget/medium">
<script defer="" src="https://www.gofundme.com/static/js/embed.js"></script>
</div>
</div>
<p>Today marks two weeks here at <a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca">BC Children’s hospital</a>. We continue to receive amazing care from the medical team, and we continue to be carried/surrounded by the love and prayers of all of you our friends and family, and we are humbled by your help!</p>
<p>Thank you all for your words of encouragement, gifts, and prayers. It seems you are unstoppable in finding ways to pour out your love and generosity. A number of days ago some friends convinced us that this <a href="https://www.gofundme.com/manage/help-the-chisholm-family-while-sam-battles-cancer">GoFundMe</a> page would be a good idea to support us in the expense of this current journey and to give people a means of providing tangible support. Please do not feel any obligation to give.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-may-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-may-1">Reflections on May 1</h2>
<p>Yesterday, was a great day! The issue of Sam’s feeding tube resolved by having to remove the tube. This turned out for the best as Sam got his appetite back. I can’t remember the last time Sam ate so well! Sam also noted that it is much easier to eat without the tube in. The medical team is also happy about this latest development.</p>
<p>Activity levels are also coming up. Sam is able to walk around some more. He was able to walk the hall here and he spent an hour sitting up and talking with his Uncle Cal.</p>
<p>These recent changes certainly give us hope for the future and definitely joy in the here-and-now. We are grateful for all of this. We have been cautioned that these improvements can be expected, but that the only way to evaluate if the cancer is responding is to complete new scans to see what has happened to the tumors. We will continue to choose hope and take joy in each victory.</p>
<p>Going forward, the next days ahead should be routine with medicines, bloodwork, checking vitals, and a new addition of prescribed physiotherapy. In about a week Sam will go for imaging and then the next steps will be determined.</p>
</section>
<section id="needs-concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="needs-concerns-and-victories">Needs, concerns, and victories</h2>
<p>Mostly victories today!</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Tina had a a full night sleep in our room at the [Ronald McDonald House] (night of April 30).</p></li>
<li><p>We all slept well last night (the family still is). Sam commented how cozy he felt after his nurse re-tucked him in following bloodwork and a bathroom break.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has his appetite back.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam’s activity level is improving.</p></li>
<li><p>I am thankful for messages and outpourings of love that we have received.</p></li>
<li><p>The cancer, and that it responds treatment, remains our largest concern.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-02_humbled-assistance.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A good day, but a rough night…</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-01_NG-tube-mishap.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It is currently just after 7:00am here. Sam is currently sleeping soundly, and I hope that Tina is having a good and lengthy sleep. Tina took a turn to sleep at our room at the Ronald McDonald House – her first night away from Sam since coming to Vancouver. Honestly it was a good night to miss… nothing major, just problems with the little things.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-april-30" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-april-30">Reflections on April 30</h2>
<p>Yesterday, was mostly quiet. Almost like we are entering into a routine. Sam was full of energy to start the day, feeling better than he had for months. We got out of the room, taking a tour of the ward, and checking out the youth room where we discovered options for art, music, a library of games (digital and board), movies, and video games. We made plans to start a Harry Potter movie marathon.</p>
<p>Sam was hungry again and I biked down to Broadway to grab a pizza (a great outing for me). It is weird, but life felt … normal. Our normal, now includes regular check-ins with nurses and doctors who are doing their routines of checking vitals, taking blood, loading Sam’s supplemental feeding, adjusting oxygen… <em>this is normal? this is routine?</em> Yes, it seems to be… and it was all going well until it wasn’t.</p>
<p>It is amazing how one tiny little thing can mess up your routine Something jammed up Sam’s NG-tube<sup>1</sup>. Attempts to clear it resulted in spillage and literally hours of frustration and extra work by the nurses. Sam has been patient through most all of it, and lost some significant time for sleeping… it is still not cleared.</p>
<!-- What I did not talk about was all of the extra alarms: obstructed lines, -->
<!-- sensors alarming regarding heart rates, or O~2~ -->
</section>
<section id="needs-concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="needs-concerns-and-victories">Needs, concerns, and victories</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>We are thankful to see Sam feeling so much better. We hope that this means he is getting better, but we will not know until Sam has his next scan which is not for about a week.</p></li>
<li><p>The little things matter in life – for all of us. Even though the little things may be issues in a larger storm they have a strong influence on life. I am thankful for the little-graces. I am learning to not take them for granted. I also hope for little graces in this journey ahead.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the medical team for all their hard work and care.</p></li>
<li><p>We also cannot forget the larger issue. We are in a major storm of life. Sam has cancer. His prognosis is unknown. We choose hope, but that does not mean waves of fear to not threaten to swamp us. We hope and pray for his healing. That the cancer would respond to treatment. That we would be able to go home together.</p></li>
</ol>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Nasogasteric feeding tube (i.e.&nbsp;through the nose to the gut)↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-05-01_NG-tube-mishap.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Joy in all the small victories</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-30_All-the-small-victories.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/img/tina-colin-BCCH-deck.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Sam is not a fan of getting his picture taken – so you get the two of us. Love to you all.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It is a beautiful Sunday morning, my family is sleeping. It is true the last days have been challenging, our lives have taken a huge turn. There have been tears, and fears. Today as I write, I have to reflect on the grace given us. There is no denying it. We have been blanketed in the love of friends and family. Thank you all for your notes of encouragement, your prayers, your solidarity in our circumstance. Today, I can share joys!</p>
<section id="reflections-on-april-29" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-april-29">Reflections on April 29</h2>
<section id="thankful-for-victories" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thankful-for-victories">Thankful for victories</h3>
<p>Yesterday was a day of grace, joy, and fun! As I reflect on the day, I am shocked at the contrast to the shock and challenges of the days prior. Yesterday was filled with many victories.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>We haven’t seen Sam have energy like this in over well over a month.</li>
<li>Times sitting up.<br>
</li>
<li>Concentrations levels to
<ul>
<li>Great visits and conversations with guests including: Shalom, a friend from PG; and his cousins Amanda, Chris and Mary-Joy.</li>
<li>Conquer Mario Kart tracks</li>
<li>Take in NHL playoffs</li>
<li>Read comic books</li>
</ul></li>
<li>He was hungry, and the cousins brought Wendy’s</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="health-and-healing-victories" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-and-healing-victories">Health and healing victories</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Sam’s PICC continues to function. This is a big deal. Blood chemistry is every four hours, and without the PICC it would mean needles for every sample. Today, needles to draw blood were not necessary.</p></li>
<li><p>On needles. Sam gets a small injection every 12 hours. Our nursing team might be in competition to see who can deliver with the least pain. Of the last three needles Sam felt one, a bit; didn’t feel one at all; and was tickled by a third. Wow, if we can keep this pattern going that would be amazing. Happy for what we have now.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam was able to complete the intake of his intense chemotherapy chemicals. If you have ever been in the health care system for more than a couple days you likely know the importance of … movements. Alex, Sam’s nurse, literally danced for joy as this health moment. The timing of this was critical to allow for the taking of the drugs. Also, if it had taken any longer Sam might have needed a yet another new IV.</p></li>
</ol>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-30_All-the-small-victories.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://samc-news.netlify.app/img/tina-colin-BCCH-deck.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Diagnosis and the initiation of treatment</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-29_diagnosis-and-treatment.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>My morning has started with an encouraging time with my boy. I managed to get some sleep over at the Ronald McDonald House and came back to Sam’s room for 5:00 (these days that is sleeping in for me). Shortly after I got here Sam woke up. Despite the intensity of the previous day, despite the pains in his body, he was full of faith and joy. He celebrated that his PICC worked for the latest blood-work (currently running at every four hours). We chatted for a bit, I rubbed his back, wrapped him in a warm blanket, and then tucked him back in. Currently he is sleeping soundly.</p>
<section id="reflections-on-april-28" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-april-28">Reflections on April 28</h2>
<p>This date will be significant to use for the rest of our lives – that day we received a diagnosis and the initiation of treatment.</p>
<section id="diagnosis-and-treatment" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="diagnosis-and-treatment">Diagnosis and Treatment</h3>
<p>In the morning the lead care team (Oncologist, Clinical Care Nurse, and Social Worker) met with us – the three of us to start, and then Tina and I for the details. Finally we have a diagnosis, Sam’s cancer has been identified. We have been looking forward to this as a diagnosis leads to a plan … if you know what it is, you can know how to treat it. We all wish it was that simple.</p>
<p>Sam has an extremely rare form of cancer. It is a blood-based cancer mostly located in the lymphatic system. The name of the disease is almost as long as the first two sentences in this paragraph. We know what to call it, we know where it is, the team will treat it. However, the treatment plan will be week-to-week, and as treatment phases are completed, additional steps will be taken to evaluate the response/impact on the disease.</p>
<p>Phase 1 of treatment has started, a round of chemotherapy, and we know the plan for this week.</p>
<p>I have to add that Sam is a champ! Today’s needle count tallied to 4 including the addition a new IV line.</p>
</section>
<section id="surrounded-by-love" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="surrounded-by-love">Surrounded by love</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>My Mom and Dad were here and were have to have a good time talking with Sam while Tina and I met with the medical team. I am glad they were here. It was good to share tears with them.</p></li>
<li><p>Rhoda and Dave, had a great conversation with Sam, and gifted him with comics and games</p></li>
<li><p>Tina had a great call with sister.</p></li>
<li><p>Many thanks to all of you for your notes of support, well-wishes, and prayers! Your words, stories, encouragement, and solidarity with us are amazing.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="needs-concerns-and-victories" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="needs-concerns-and-victories">Needs, concerns and victories</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>We are all walking in the dark. Our family and the Drs. Pray for wisdom to simply see the next step.</p></li>
<li><p>We need to see the cancer respond to the treatment. It is unknown, how this cancer will respond, or how it may adapt/ resist.</p></li>
<li><p>Chemotherapy, is intense, and some of the chemicals are literally poison. We have entered a world of trade-offs. The disease must die, but the treatment has dangers and significant potential side-effects.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>We will count the small victories and joys</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Sam took on numerous pokes/needles like a champ.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam’s PICC worked … most of the time.</p></li>
<li><p>Out of bed. Sam’ has been sick and mostly bed-ridden. He enjoyed some time out of bed sitting up in a chair.</p></li>
<li><p>It was a puppy therapy day today. If you know Sam you know he loves dogs.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="meditation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="meditation">Meditation</h3>
<p>There are two passages of scripture that are constantly in my mind. Two passages that reflect in-part where I am at.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>He guides me along the right paths for his name’s sake. Even though I walk through the darkest valley, I will fear no evil, for you are with me; <a href="https://www.bible.com/bible/111/PSA.23.NIV">Psalm 23</a></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>if you can do anything, take pity on us and help us.” “ ‘If you can’?”said Jesus. “Everything is possible for one who believes.” Immediately the boy’s father exclaimed, “I do believe; help me overcome my unbelief!” <a href="https://www.bible.com/bible/111/MRK.9.NIV">Mark 9:14f</a></p>
</blockquote>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-29_diagnosis-and-treatment.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pending decisions</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-28_confirming-cancer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Thank-you! We have received so many notes of solidarity, encouragement, and prayer. The community of support around us, all of you, is amazing!</p>
<section id="reflections-on-april-27th." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-april-27th.">Reflections on April 27<sup>th</sup>.</h2>
<p>I’m going to keep this one quick … we are in a state of hyper-vigilance for Sam, staying in the room with him. This is something that is essential for now, though not sustainable… we are stressed and exhausted.</p>
<ul>
<li>My parents, Earle and Dorothy, are here with us. Great to have their support. Thanks to the many who are also supporting them.</li>
<li>Recent scans confirm where the cancer is. No new surprises, though the impact of the cancer on Sam is stronger than previously known.</li>
<li>Cancer diagnosis is still pending. It is expected that BC Cancer Clinic will be able to identify the disease.</li>
<li>However, we may not be able to wait. Initial treatment steps may need to be taken before the diagnosis is in. From the medical perspective this is about managing risk. Starting treatment without diagnosis may impact longer term effectiveness of the treatments; not starting could allow the cancer to impact Sam in the now.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-28_confirming-cancer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Reality Check: Things are not good</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-27_reality-check.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It is early morning, the start of day 9, here at BC Children’s Hospital. This morning, I write so that you might better know what we are experiencing. In writing this, I am throwing caution out and exposing you to our pain… I do not expect you to read this … and perhaps you shouldn’t.</p>
<div class="panel-tabset">
<ul class="nav nav-tabs"><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link active" id="tabset-1-1-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-1" aria-controls="tabset-1-1" aria-selected="true">...</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-2-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-2" aria-controls="tabset-1-2" aria-selected="false">Pain</a></li></ul>
<div class="tab-content">
<div id="tabset-1-1" class="tab-pane active" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-1-tab">
<p>… <em>I leave it to you to choose to enter our pain (i.e.&nbsp;click the Pain tab).</em></p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-2" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-2-tab">
<p>Why share this? You are our friends and family. This is the truth of where we are at.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Tina and I have wept, we have wailed. It comes in waves – releases of love, pain, and grief from a depth of my being that I never before knew existed. The reality is, we might lose our boy.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam is sick, he has cancer, treatment has not begun and he continues to get sicker.</p></li>
<li><p>We do not know what kind of cancer this is. Cancer in children is rare, and Sam’s cancer, is extremely rare – the disease specialists have not been able to identify it.</p></li>
<li><p>We do not know if this cancer is treatable. It is so unknown; treatment might be simple… but it also may not be possible. We just do not know.</p></li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="recent-and-next-steps" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recent-and-next-steps">Recent and next steps</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>Sam had is PET scan yesterday – we do not know the results.</li>
<li>Sam received a feeding tube. His nausea had been debilitating, and he has eaten very little in the last weeks.</li>
<li>We continue to wait for a treatment plan.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="what-can-you-do" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-can-you-do">What can you do?</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>Pray.</li>
<li>Continue to send us your care. We are bolstered by your notes of encouragement, love, and support.</li>
<li>We have been blessed with visits from friends and family.<br>
If you would like to see us, please contact me first, and I will try to work something out. Please be aware that as we move forward, ideally into treatment, visits with Sam may be highly restricted.</li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-27_reality-check.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>There he is!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-26_waiting-and-visitors.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="reflecting-on-april-25" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflecting-on-april-25">Reflecting on April 25</h2>
<p>Given that the days have been hard lately. It is incredible to say that Sam had a great day yesterday. He was himself, he had energy to talk, even played a video game for almost an hour! Yes, I celebrate when Sam is able to play video games!</p>
<p>Sam’s afternoon and ours was filled with love as family arrived. My parents, Gram and Papa C, drove in from Prince George, and Kevin and Shannon, Tina’s sister, were here from Edmonton. My parents had a good visit with Sam and we look forward to seeing them over the next couple days. Uncle Kev and Auntie Shan had a good visit with Sam in the evening when, as always, Kevin attempted his jokes trying to get Sam to crack; this round went to Sam – though I definitely had some good laughs.</p>
</section>
<section id="needs-concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="needs-concerns-and-victories">Needs, concerns, and victories</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>PET scan this morning, scheduled for 8:15am. We will be transported to from BC Children’s to the BC Cancer Clinic – just a few miles away. This is a full body scan to provide a complete picture of where the cancer is in Sam’s body.</p></li>
<li><p>I am expecting that we will be sitting down with the medical team either later today or tomorrow to discuss Sam’s treatment plan.</p></li>
<li><p>PICC trouble. The team was not able to draw the routine blood sample from Sam this morning. I am not sure if they will try again … or draw blood with needles.</p></li>
<li><p>Thanks for an great day yesterday, as Sam was alert and interactive, and we felt the love of family. … It is awesome to receive love and notes from afar. It is next level to receive it as a hug!</p></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-26_waiting-and-visitors.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Waiting and watching…</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-25_waiting.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>One week ago today, Sam went in for the X-ray that started the chain of events that has led us here. Time is warped for us; I expect this is a common experience for all of us in times when life is intense; where experiential time does not seem to link up with chronological time. Needless to say, life has been intense.</p>
<p>It is amazing the range of emotion that can happen as your child sleeps. Over this last week I have watch with joy and contentment as Sam slept peacefully, to another extreme filled with waves of fear and anxiety that he hasn’t woken up (yesterday). In the later afternoon yesterday, we stepped away from Sam’s bedside, where he continued to sleep, to visit with Cal and Tricia. My day was made when we got back, he was not only awake, but he was up and out of bed, sitting in a chair. This was sweet joy, relief, and peace. He spent the next 1-2 hours chatting with his Aunt and Uncle!</p>
<section id="needs-concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="needs-concerns-and-victories">Needs, concerns and victories</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Still waiting for the cancer to be identified.</li>
<li>Sam has a PET Scan scheduled for 8:15am tomorrow morning (April 26) at the BC Cancer Clinic. The medical team would to have liked it a little sooner, but all of us are willing to take it! Many thanks to the Drs. who pushed hard to get him in, we know that you have worked hard!</li>
<li>Sam’s PICC, is working … enough. I can’t say that it is perfect, but it is all he needs for now – no additional needles have been needed.</li>
<li>Many thanks to Sam’s nurses. A special shout out to Pam – your efforts with Sam made my day yesterday!</li>
<li>Sam has had such a great attitude! Physically, he has not felt good, with fatigue and sometimes nausea. Mentally/emotionally he is doing really well. It is not uncommon to here him say <em>This is great</em> or <em>I’m so happy</em>. He knows he is where he needs to be; he is on a road to healing.</li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-25_waiting.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Clarity Needed</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-24_clarity-needed.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/img/sam-clean.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="reflections-of-april-23-2023" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-of-april-23-2023">Reflections of April 23, 2023</h2>
<p>Yesterday was a quiet day with challenges.</p>
<section id="cancer-but-what-type-are-we-dealing-with" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cancer-but-what-type-are-we-dealing-with">Cancer, but what type are we dealing with?</h3>
<p>Yesterday morning, Tina and I spoke with Dr.&nbsp;Chang who has been taking the lead in Sam’s case. I was really glad to have this conversation, to know what Dr.&nbsp;Chang was thinking, and strategies going forward … but this one also hurt. The major challenge for the medical team is that they still do not know exactly what they are dealing with. This is a cancer, but the specific type of cancer remains unknown.</p>
<p>Given that there are unknowns around the type of cancer, there are also unknowns about how it will behave and potentially where it is. Sam needs to have a full-body scan, if an opening in the schedule at the BC Cancer Clinic can be found, and timing on this is essential. The scan needs to happen before treatment starts and the team can only wait so long (i.e.&nbsp;treatment needs to start this week).</p>
</section>
<section id="on-needles" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="on-needles">On needles</h3>
<p>Over the last month, Sam has not had a good time with needles. Really, I think we can all relate – getting a shot, or having blood taken, is not something any of us enjoy. Sam has taken them on, with blood test after blood test. To make things worse, as Sam entered the hospital system he had to have IV medications, many of which failed. In the last nine IVs he experienced six failed attempts, and three were initially established successful; of those one was accidentally pulled during surgery, one blew, and a last one remains. All this to say needles cause a level of anxiety.</p>
<p>Sam has had a number of days of grace. The <a href="http://www.cw.bc.ca/library/pdf/pamphlets/BCCH1552_PICC.pdf">PICC line</a> provides easy access, but last night it stopped working, they could not draw blood. If it does not work, then drawing blood via needles will be needed. In a few texts last night, we asked for prayer for this.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-comforts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-comforts">Victories and comforts</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>The small things really do matter! Many thanks to our nurse Pam who made sure that Sam was able to get into the shower today. He came out clean, refreshed, and feeling human!</p></li>
<li><p>I didn’t finish the needle story:</p>
<ul>
<li>The doctor changes the order regarding taking blood. So no need for blood last night!</li>
<li>This morning I came into the room at 4:45 and both Sam and Tina were full of joy. Sam had just had his blood taken, and no needles were used. The PICC line was working again.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>So where was I coming in from at 5:00am? We now have a home away from home at the Ronald McDonald House, where I had a comfortable, and mostly full night’s sleep.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="needs-and-concerns" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="needs-and-concerns">Needs and concerns</h3>
<p>Currently:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Firm diagnosis of the type of cancer. This will significantly inform treatment.</li>
<li>PET scan to determine where this disease is and where it is not. Timing is essential on this – the sooner the better.</li>
<li>That Sam’s PICC line would continue to function. Ideally, that it could also be used for treatment … either adjustments are needed or another PICC will need to be established as the current one is not ‘centrally located’ (not exactly where they need it to be).</li>
</ol>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-24_clarity-needed.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://samc-news.netlify.app/img/sam-clean.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A room with a view</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-23_room-with-a-view.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="reflecting-on-april-22" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflecting-on-april-22">Reflecting on April 22</h2>
<p>As expected, we are in the waiting game. It is the weekend and things are quieter around the hospital, and lab results move in a little slower. So we continue to wait. Answers will come.</p>
<p>A day of waiting however is not without excitement!</p>
<p>Sam now has a room with a view. He was transferred from the ICU to the Oncology unit. Thank you to the ICU team and their vigilant care of our boy. Sam is now under the care of the Oncology team. Things are quieter here as medical policies do not require constant monitoring. The view is also nicer, the ICU window looked at the side of another building, now from the 8<sup>th</sup> floor the view is across Vancouver, out to Burnaby, SFU, and the mountains beyond.</p>
<p>… I was going to add a picture but as the rain comes down there are no views in Vancouver this morning.</p>
<p>We were encouraged by visits:</p>
<ul>
<li>The Smiths, dear friends who we originally bonded with while working in Guatemala with CMU’s Outtatown program, came over from Vancouver Island.</li>
<li>Sam’s sweetheart of a cousin Jayme (2.5 years) delivered her hand-made card supported by mom Amanda, Auntie Tricia, and Uncle Cal. Sam was touched!</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>We continue to look forward to Sam’s diagnosis … but we expect that these may still take a number of days</li>
<li>This afternoon Tina and I will check-in at the Ronald McDonald House. This will give us our own space a five minute walk from Sam. The other day I ate at McDonald’s and was offered to support the Ronald McDonald House. Of course I said yes. … I expect I will be saying yes for the rest of my life.</li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-23_room-with-a-view.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Waiting and Welcome Guests</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-22_waiting-and-guests.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="tldr" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tldr">TLDR</h3>
<p>We are in a waiting period, and as results from Sam’s biopsies trickle in, we have some knowledge of what the disease is not. Our hearts are peaceful and we have been filled with messages of love and prayer from around the world!</p>
</section>
<section id="reflections-on-april-21-2023" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-april-21-2023">Reflections on April 21, 2023</h3>
<p>How long have we been here? As I write this, it is only the beginning of day four and I am writing about day 3, so much has happened.</p>
<p>Yesterday, was … a beautiful day. Sam was far more comfortable, being another day away from his biopsy surgery. It was wonderful to watch him sleep and nap on and off through the day. This time of rest also powered him up to visit with family. It was also great to see Tina catch up on some much-needed sleep.</p>
<section id="physical-health" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="physical-health">Physical Health</h4>
<p>Medically, it was generally a quiet day. No new tests, just the routine of checking vitals, checking blood chemistry, and taking medicines (e.g.&nbsp;pain management from the previous surgery). We are in waiting phase. The lab has not finished processing the tissue samples taken April 20th. Despite not knowing much yet the medical team continues to communicate. The best news was that we now know that the disease is:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>not</em> in the central nervous system</li>
<li><em>not</em> in his bone marrow.</li>
</ul>
<p>It might be a quiet weekend as lab results may not come back until mid-next week. So we wait as a family, and the medical team waits with us. One might think this is frustrating, but it is not, rather it is a peaceful and strategic waiting. Once the tests come back the doctors will be very intentional on how to manage Sam’s health. So we wait, for the right understanding, and the subsequent right treatment plan.</p>
</section>
<section id="soul-health" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="soul-health">Soul Health</h4>
<p>Wow, what a good day! We have heard from so many friends, family, some of whom we have not connected with for years, but this challenging time is pulling our people together. Thank you for reaching out to us, conveying your care, telling us your stories, or simply what is happening in your world. We are supported by your words, your love, and your prayers.</p>
<p>People around the world are praying – it’s awesome. Friends, family, and their friends and families, bible study and prayer groups; from Prince George, across the province, across the continent, and as far away as Zambia!</p>
<p>We have also had some amazing face-to-face visits/care.</p>
<ul>
<li>A friend anticipated our needs and showed up with a bag of groceries and goodies picked especially for Tina and her dietary needs / requirements.</li>
<li>A providential visit with the Schellenbergs with whom we have shared so much life and adventure. What are the chances that they just happened to be in the area this weekend! For those who don’t know them, they live in Saskatchewan.</li>
<li>Sam had a great visit with his cousin Chris, Uncle Cal, and Auntie Tricia.</li>
</ul>
<p>To wrap up this post, please know that we feel cared for in soul and body. Although we do not know what treatment for Sam will look like, we are in a peaceful place. That might change, we may have challenges ahead, but we are bolstered by your love, we are carried.</p>
<p>Love to you all!</p>
<p>Colin</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-22_waiting-and-guests.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post Biopsies</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-21_Biopsy-Recovery.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="tldr-short-version" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tldr-short-version">TLDR (short version)</h3>
<p>Yesterday: surgery for tissue samples followed by pain management. In the weeks to come, Sam will be here at BC Children Hospital as he is treated for what is assumed to be lymphoma.</p>
<p>--</p>
</section>
<section id="full-version" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-version">Full version</h3>
<p>Hi all,</p>
<p>Yesterday was a big day for Sam. He had the surgery to complete a series of biopsies. These included the removal of a lymph node at the base of his neck, a lumbar puncture, a bone marrow sample from the top of his hip, and establishing a PICC (<a href="http://www.cw.bc.ca/library/pdf/pamphlets/BCCH1552_PICC.pdf">described here</a>) to facilitate ongoing blood work and upcoming intravenous drug delivery. All the procedures went well. Dr.&nbsp;Webber, completed the lymph node removal and said it went “Perfectly”. This was all done before noon. The biggest challenge of the day has been pain management, but Sam has been a trooper.</p>
<p>The staff here continue to be amazing, always taking the time to answer any of Sam’s questions, and making complex biology and bio-chemistry understandable. It is honestly amazing to hear Sam explain his disease to others – he gets it, understands it, and given the situation is very glad to be here.</p>
<p>Next steps are not totally clear. We are working with the understanding/assumption that Sam <del>has lymphoma (<a href="http://www.bcchildrens.ca/Oncology-Site/Documents/Non-Hodgkin%20Lymphoma.pdf">one possibility described here</a>)</del> <em>As of April 23, we still do not know what type of cancer this is</em>. The signs all point that way (e.g.&nbsp;X-ray and CT scan), but this will not be totally confirmed until the tissue samples are processed. Here is what we are currently expecting:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Sam will start a round of drug treatment, as soon as later today, and specific treatments will be refined following the analysis of his tissue samples</li>
<li>Sam is currently in the ICU, and we expect him to be here for the next number of days after which, he will be transferred to the oncology unit just a few floors above where he will remain a patient for three weeks or so (timing of stay will all depend on tests).</li>
<li>Tina and I will be able to check into the Ronald McDonald House here on hospital campus on Sunday. This will give us a home base, we will also be able to continue staying in the room with Sam.</li>
</ol>
<p>Many thanks to all of Sam’s friends and teachers, and all of our friends and family. We love to hear from you. We may not get back to you right away but know your messages are encouraging to us. If you have any questions, please feel free to ask, and I will try to answer them either directly or in a following update.</p>
</section>
<section id="qa" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="qa">Q&amp;A</h3>
<dl>
<dt>How is Tina doing?</dt>
<dd>
<p>She is actually great. She has been working so hard advocating for Sam’s health over the last months, trying to get the bottom of why he has been sick. Now, she can relax as Sam is where he needs to be, receiving the medical care that he needs. She also loves the medical world, she is in her element here. Our biggest challenge for Tina will be to ensure she is properly fed, especially given her dietary restrictions. We will need to find a new normal here.</p>
</dd>
<dt>How can we help / Let us know if we can help.</dt>
<dd>
<p>Hearing from you is currently the best. As noted, we might not be able to get back to you right away, but all of your notes are encouraging. Tina and I have literally had tears-of-joy reading them.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
<p>Thanks again for your prayers and support,</p>
<p>Colin and Tina</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-21_Biopsy-Recovery.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>An Alarming X-ray</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-20_an-alarming-xray.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Hi friends,</p>
<p>The last 48 hours have been a whirlwind, and we are where we need to be.</p>
<p>Sam is now at BC Children’s hospital, and Tina and I are able to stay in the room with him. Steps are being taken to manage what all indications suggest is lymphoma. Staff here have been amazing in: providing care, communicating what is happening and next steps, and conveying a sense that ‘this is serious’ mixed with a calming confidence.</p>
<p>The process: Yesterday, tests were run – the primary one being a CT scan of his chest. Today, Sam will start the day with a surgery to complete a series of biopsies, the primary one being one of his lymph nodes at the base of his neck. By the end of the day, we should have firmer answers as to what exactly is happening and a treatment plan.</p>
<p>Sam’s friends and classmates have been amazing. They have been in direct communication with him via Snapchat and hearing from them has been really encouraging to him, also to Tina and I – it is amazing to see friends rally behind him.</p>
<p>Thank you for your support and prayers,</p>
<p>Colin and Tina</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-04-20_an-alarming-xray.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
