<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Sam Chisholm</title>
<link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>News updating friends and family on our journey</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.361</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Sam is a Champion</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-05_champion.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/Chisholm2023-oliveandbeanphoto-9_sml.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The Chisholm family at the Ronald McDonald House. Fall 2023<sup>1</sup>.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Sam is a courageous champion! He has now endured and completed two types of cancer treatment, and is ready to take-on the upcoming bone marrow transplant (BMT). Over the past six months Sam’s treatments have focused on attacking the cancer cells within his body. He received six rounds of chemical chemotherapy between May and Oct.&nbsp;Over the last two weeks, following the completion of the initial chemotherapy treatment, tactics were changed to use radiation therapy against the largest detectable cancerous mass that remains in the center of his chest. The upcoming BMT will mark a significant change in strategy for removing the cancer. Instead of attacking the cancer directly the BMT will provide a long-term indirect assault on the cancer (long-term being life-long). This process will replace Sam’s immune system – removing his current native immune defenses and replacing them with a donated immune system. Where Sam’s immune system was not effective at detecting and attacking the cancer it is expected that the new immune system will. This process is not easy and Sam may face his greatest challenges to date. However, he is looking forward to completing these next phases.</p>
<p>There are currently 8 days until Sam receives the actual transplant. However, there are numerous steps/procedures to be completed to prepare his body for this process. This Wednesday he starts these steps.</p>
<section id="this-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="this-past-week">This past week</h2>
<section id="treatment" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="treatment">Treatment</h3>
<p>It is amazing to me how a short medical appointment can dominate an entire day. Monday through Friday this past week marked Sam’s second and final week of targeted radiation therapy to directly attack the main mass of cancer in his body. The actual procedure was usually not more than 15 minutes but it would dominate out entire day. Each day we would get ready, load up and head down to the BC Cancer clinic, a short drive away. Tina and Sam would check in while I attempted to find parking – there were a few days where Sam was done before I was able to park the van. Following treatment we would return to the RMH. Sam has generally felt well though with increasing fatigue. His medical team is happy with his current health: <em>He is an otherwise healthy young man, but with cancer.</em></p>
<p>We may never know the full impact that the radiation will have on the cancer. The radiation therapy can take weeks to show measurable impacts but by that point we will be well into the BMT process. I expect next scans to evaluate the various treatments and the state of the cancer will not be feasible until into the new year.</p>
</section>
<section id="visitors" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visitors">Visitors</h3>
<p>We were able to visit with and be encouraged by some family and friends this past week. Aunt Tricia put on an amazing meal. Uncle Cal paid a visit. Sam was able to have some time hanging out with cousin Kaden, while Tina and I visited with Kevin, Shannon, and Nana. Yesterday John, Jess, Kate, and John Jr.&nbsp;stopped by for a few hours. Tina was able to have and afternoon away visiting with her cousins in Abbotsford.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>This coming week will mark a point-of-no-return as Sam will have intense treatments to condition his body for the BMT – all the gains that have been made in returning Sam to feeling healthy will likely be ripped out from under him. These treatments include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Total body radiation</li>
<li>BMT Chemotherapy – intense chemo-drug therapy</li>
<li>Immune suppression drugs</li>
<li>The BMT transplant</li>
</ul>
<p>See the <a href="../../posts/2309/2023-09-19_courage-and-despair.html">previous post</a> or <a href="../../plan.html">The Plan</a> for the details.</p>
<p>Following the BMT medical efforts will focus on managing Sam’s day-to-day health and finding the balance of facilitating successful engraftment while suppressing graft-versus-host-disease impacts. To complicate matters symptoms of graft-versus-host-disease are easily confused or even synonymous with the flu, colds, or other infections which he will also be highly susceptible to – the medical team will have to be highly vigilant.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>It has been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity.</p></li>
<li><p>We have completed a major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy and targeted radiation. We now pivot to the bone marrow transplant – this next treatment brings hope of removal of the disease but also anxiety about both the challenging process and the potential for long term side effects. We hope and pray that this treatment will be effective in beating the cancer for life.</p></li>
<li><p>It is flu season and covid is still out there. In the weeks ahead, as a family, we will be more cautious to reduce our risk of getting ill.&nbsp;If any of us get sick in the weeks ahead it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he will be entering a phase where he has no immune system for weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>We are continually thankful for our medical teams here. They continue to provide incredible care. They are always open to conversation and answering questions. They have been incredibly pro-active and I am glad we are prepared for the next steps.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the chemotherapy has been effective at initially reducing the cancer and keeping the cancer contained (as indicated by the PET scan). Thankful that these results allow us to move forward.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team has a huge coordination task ahead of them. From our meetings with them it seems all of the pieces are coming together, but with so many moving parts it is easy for things go wrong.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Photography facilitated by the Ronald McDonald House taken by <a href="https://www.oliveandbeanphoto.com">Olive and Bean Photography</a>↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2311/2023-11-05_champion.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Targeted Radiation</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-29_counting-down.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It is <em>Day -15</em> as we count down the days towards Sam’s bone marrow transplant (BMT).</p>
<section id="this-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="this-past-week">This past week</h2>
<section id="treatment" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="treatment">Treatment</h3>
<p>Sam is currently in his targeted radiation phase, which is intended to directly attack the main mass of cancer in his body. Each day this past week we went to the BC Cancer clinic at Vancouver General Hospital (VGH). During each visit the technician would use a mold of Sam to get him into position. The mold extends from below his shoulders up over his head and they use it to literally pin him to the treatment table ensuring that he is in the exact same position each time – thereby ensuring the radiation focuses on the intended area.</p>
<p>Sam is doing well with it all. Sam is now over thirty days away from the previous chemo-drug treatments and his strength is returning. He is a generally healthy young man, but with cancer. This is where we want him to be – as healthy and as strong as possible before starting the BMT.</p>
<p>So far the only side effect from the radiation therapy has been fatigue. It is different than chemo-fatigue which caused him to not have any energy, be nauseated, and caused brain fog. This radiation induced fatigue is the need to sleep, but once awake Sam usually has energy to go for walks and enjoy his life.</p>
</section>
<section id="visitors" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visitors">Visitors</h3>
<p>We had a good number of family and friends visiting with us this past week. Not everyone got to see Sam as he is being very cautious about seeing people – he is also training Tina and I to do the same as we all mask up more and more. Visitors included:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Gram and Papa spent some great time with Sam prior to heading home this past Monday</p></li>
<li><p>Nana, now living in the area, was able to come by for the Thursday afternoon.</p></li>
<li><p>Uncle Kevin and cousin Kaden were able to be here for a few hours. I love it when Sam and Kaden have a chance to hang out.</p></li>
<li><p>Friday morning I had a great visit with Aaron W.</p></li>
<li><p>Friday afternoon we spent some good time, Colin with Rob, and Tina with Leanne D. They also delivered some great messages of support from our church family in Prince George – thank you all!</p></li>
<li><p>Yesterday evening we were able to get away from the RMH and spend the evening with family out in Langley – celebrating our nieces birthdays. We are so fortunate to have family close by.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>Today Sam returns to his targeted radiation therapy. It highly likely that the impacts of this treatment will become more distinct with increasing levels of fatigue and potentially skin and esophagus irritation.</p>
<p>Next week after will be more difficult as Sam will have more intense treatments to condition his body for the BMT – all the gains that have been made in returning Sam to feeling healthy will likely be ripped out from under him. These treatments include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Total body radiation</li>
<li>BMT Chemotherapy – intense chemo-drug therapy</li>
<li>Immune suppression drugs</li>
<li>The BMT transplant</li>
</ul>
<p>See the <a href="../../posts/2309/2023-09-19_courage-and-despair.html">previous post</a> or <a href="../../plan.html">The Plan</a> for the details.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for friends who have chosen to meet regularly to pray for Sam. If you would like to join them talk with Beth H., Krista C., or contact the <a href="https://westwoodchurch.bc.ca">Westwood Church</a> office.</p></li>
<li><p>It has been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity.</p></li>
<li><p>We have completed a major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy we now pivot to the bone marrow treatment plan – this next treatment brings hope of removal of the disease but also anxiety about both the challenging process and the potential for long term side effects.</p></li>
<li><p>It is the beginning of flu season and covid is still out there. In the weeks ahead, as a family, we will be more cautious to reduce our risk of getting ill.&nbsp;If any of us get sick in the weeks ahead it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he will be entering a phase where he has no immune system for weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>We are continually thankful for our medical teams here. They continue to provide incredible care. They are always open to conversation and answering questions. They have been incredibly pro-active and I am glad we are prepared for the next steps.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the chemotherapy has been effective at initially reducing the cancer and lately keeping the cancer contained (as indicated by the PET scan). Thankful that these results allow us to move forward.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team has a huge coordination task ahead of them. From out meetings with them it seems all of the pieces are coming together, but with so many moving parts it is easy for things go wrong.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-29_counting-down.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>On a knife’s edge</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-18_knife-edge-no-assurances.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/2023-10-20_visitors.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A few of our visitors – so great to have you here!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
<p>In my last post I tried to keep things to a clinical picture. Here I will attempt to capture a little of what it is to live through this cancer journey and to provide more detail on what the upcoming process may look like.</p>
<p>From the latest results, <a href="../../posts/2309/2023-10-15_Results-round-6.html">last post</a>, It feels like we are walking along a knife’s edge separating life and hope on the one side, from doubt, fear, and death on the other. This is not simply a feeling. This is a reality as the results are not great, though they are good enough to keep going.</p>
<section id="good-results-good-enough-results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="good-results-good-enough-results"><del>Good results?</del> Good <em>enough</em> results</h2>
<p>Are the results good? Yes – in that we get to keep going, and that there is hope that the treatment will work. However, there are no assurances, and Sam is not in an ideal state for entering the next phases of treatment.</p>
<p>Sam’s cancer is unique, and our medical team is using their best judgment, but none of them have battled this cancer before. They have found a single reference to it, but that has only provided a little guidance.</p>
<p>The medical team is battling hard for Sam and their strategies to date have initially reduced, and more recently kept the cancer from growing. However, compared with known cancers this cancer has not responded as well as any of us have wanted.</p>
</section>
<section id="not-an-ideal-plan" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="not-an-ideal-plan">Not an ideal plan</h2>
<p>We are moving forward with a bone-marrow-transplant (BMT), but we are not in an ideal situation. Ideally, and for best results, when moving to BMT the medical team would like the cancer to be non-detectable. With Sam, starting from where he was back in April, the cancerous mass has been reduced in size, but a significant mass remains. It is not operable as it is in the lymphatic system; although it can be located, as I understand it, it is too amorphous and intertwined within his healthy tissues and bear vital organs (e.g.&nbsp;heart and lungs).</p>
<section id="challenges-ahead" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="challenges-ahead">Challenges ahead</h3>
<p>In the weeks ahead Sam will be facing a number of challenges (see <a href="../../plan.html">The Plan</a>).</p>
<dl>
<dt>Radiation therapy – phase 1: <em>Targeted radiation</em></dt>
<dd>
<p>The objective here is to directly attack the cancer and destroy as much as possible. There are both immediate and long term challenges. The radiation oncologist is trying to balance attacking the cancer while protecting the adjacent lungs which are very sensitive to radiation damage. In the short term there will be fatigue and pain – think of a time that you had a bad sun burn. Now take that sunburn and put it on the inside of your body. Sam may feel it most in his throat.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Radiation therapy – phase 2: <em>Total body irradiation (TBI)</em></dt>
<dd>
<p>Next, Sam will undergo three days of total body radiation (TBI). This radiation will not target his cancer, rather it is undertaken to condition his body for the upcoming bone marrow transplant. TBI has the objective of permanently destroying Sam’s native immune system so that his immune system will not compete with the transplant.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>There is a long list of potential side effects from the two radiation treatments. A few of these include: permanent scarring of the lungs, impacts on the thyroid, heart disease, changes to metabolism, secondary cancers, and others. Needless to say this can be scary.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>This step, in conjunction with the following BMT Chemotherapy, mark a point of no return. Once these steps are initiated a transplant must happen for Sam to ever have an immune system again.</p>
</dd>
<dt>BMT Chemotherapy</dt>
<dd>
<p>The previous chemotherapy that Sam has had focused on targeting and removing the disease. This upcoming chemotherapy has a different objective. In conjunction with TBI it will be used to remove Sam’s own immune system. Following this chemotherapy any cells that produce/create blood will have been killed, and Sam’s bone marrow will be ready to receive the transplant. As with most chemotherapy drugs this treatment will likely make Sam feel ill.</p>
</dd>
<dt>The transplant/graft</dt>
<dd>
<p>On Nov.&nbsp;14<sup>th</sup> Sam is scheduled to receive the donated bone marrow. The donated cells will need to establish or engraft to start providing Sam his new immune system. In the 2-3 weeks following receiving the transplant we will wait in anticipation for signs that the graft is taking hold. The whole transplant process will take place in an isolation room – Sam will not be allowed to leave until his new immune system takes hold. Tina and I will be able to gown-up and be with him.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>This will be a hard number of weeks. Given the prior steps Sam will likely feel horrible for numerous weeks. It is highly likely that he will need significant intravenous supports for management of pain, nausea, engraftment of the new immune system, hydration, nutrition, and then potentially additional medication should he become ill without an immune system to support him. To provide all of these supports Sam may need upward of 15 different intravenous lines to all be connected at once. His current central lines should support most of this.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Once the graft takes hold it will start generating Sam’s new immune system and start fighting for him, including battling the cancer. However, this is a foreign immune system and steps will need to be taken ensure that the graft does not attack Sam – potential graft versus host disease. The graft also must remain aggressive enough to continually attach the cancer.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
</section>
<section id="choosing-hope" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="choosing-hope">Choosing hope</h2>
<p>There are many reasons to be consumed by fear – to allow the beast of Despair to have a foothold in our lives. Sure we have our moments of anxiety – but we choose hope. Sam remains a champion. We have also laid out some great ideas for his time in isolation – I hope he will feel well enough to take part in the activities we have planned.</p>
<p>We invite you to choose hope with us. It does make this journey easier knowing that you are there with us in mind and spirit. Please continue in your commitment to care and prayer.</p>
</section>
<section id="highlights-from-this-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights-from-this-past-week">Highlights from this past week</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Visits</dt>
<dd>
<p>David and Beth H. came down. So good to see Sam be able to spend time with a friend in person!</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>We invited Nana over for a sleep-over. Although she now lives in the area it was great to have her here with us like before she moved.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Gram and Papa C. arrived yesterday evening. Great to have them here and have their in-person support.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Sam’s Energy</dt>
<dd>
<p>We have not seen Sam have this much energy since well before we left home. The cancer has been set back and he has had a week long break between treatments. It definitely shows how the chemotherapy has been relentless.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Sam has had renewed energy to take on some academics, to build Lego, to tease his parents (…I am happy about that? Right?…). So good to see him have more physical and mental capacity.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>It has been amazing to see Sam out from under the influence of chemotherapy. To see him return to strength of mind and to have capacity for more activity.</p></li>
<li><p>We have completed a major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy we now pivot to the bone marrow treatment plan – this next treatment brings hope of removal of the disease but also anxiety about both the challenging process and the potential for long term side effects.</p></li>
<li><p>It is the beginning of flu season and covid is still out there. In the weeks ahead, as a family, we will be very cautious to reduce our risk of getting ill.&nbsp;If any of us get sick in the weeks ahead it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he will be entering a phase where he has no immune system for weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>We are continually thankful for our medical teams here. They continue to provide incredible care. They are always open to conversation and answering questions. They have been incredibly pro-active and I am glad we are prepared for the next steps.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the chemotherapy has been effective at initially reducing the cancer and lately keeping the cancer contained (as indicated by the PET scan). Thankful that these results allow us to move forward.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. All the pieces need to fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>BMT</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-18_knife-edge-no-assurances.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Round 6 results and next steps</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-15_Results-round-6.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>This past Friday Sam had a number of appointments, starting with a PET scan first thing in the morning. A PET scan provides 3-dimensional imagery of where the cancer is in the body, and metrics of how metabolically active the cancer is. We have been anxious for the results of this scan as the data would provide direction for the next steps in Sam’s treatment. At clinic, in the afternoon, the results were back – and confirmed the direction that we are going.</p>
<section id="good-results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="good-results">Good results?</h2>
<p>For Tina and I, and likely many of you, we hoped for a miraculously good results – that following these latest two rounds of chemotherapy the cancerous mass would finally collapse and be non-detectable. We do not have that result.</p>
<p>At the end of August, following the completion of round four, the medical team communicated their plans to pivot towards a bone marrow transplant<sup>1</sup>. At that time it seemed evident that the cancer would not fully respond to the planned six rounds of chemotherapy. This is the result we have.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>The last two rounds of chemotherapy have held the cancer. The mass is stable – it has not grown and it has not spread anywhere new. … Although the cancer has not had any significant decrease in size, the chemotherapy regime that Sam has been under has been effective at holding the cancer back long enough to prepare the BMT process. We also know that the BMT process is the next best step as the now completed chemotherapy was no longer effective at reducing the disease.</p></li>
<li><p>The result are what the medical team hoped and planned for. Plans were initiated over seven weeks ago to prepare for this outcome. If the cancer had grown or spread our conversations with the medical team could have been very different.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>The results are good – as they support <a href="../../plan.html">the plan</a>.<br>
The results are also challenging as a hard road lays ahead.</p>
</section>
<section id="highlights-from-this-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights-from-this-past-week">Highlights from this past week</h2>
<section id="appointments" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="appointments">Appointments</h3>
<p>Lots of tests and appointments this past week.</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<table class="table table-striped table-sm small" data-quarto-postprocess="true">
<caption>Tests and appointments completed this past week. Most of these were to create baseline measurements of Sam before starting the BMT treatment protocols. </caption>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;" data-quarto-table-cell-role="th">Activity</th>
<th style="text-align: left;" data-quarto-table-cell-role="th">Complete</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Eye Exam</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Renal medical imaging</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Bone marrow biopsy and Lumbar Puncture</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Hearing assessment</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Pulmonary Function Test</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Partial</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">PET Scan</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Ultrasound of neck (state of blood-clots)</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Dental Assessment</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Dermatology</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Complete</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="visits" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visits">Visits</h3>
<p>Sam has been able to connect with friends online.</p>
<p>Friday afternoon Sam and his Uncle Cal had a great connection remembering and celebrating Papa Gord together.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>For the most part Sam may have much of this coming week off. There will be clinic visits but the intent of the medical team is to give his body a break and get him as strong as we can before the BMT process starts.</p>
<p>We are looking forward to visits with friends and family.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We have finished the week strong – despite a long list of bookings we made it through and Sam is in good spirits.</p></li>
<li><p>We have completed a major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy we now pivot to the bone marrow treatment plan.</p></li>
<li><p>It is the beginning of flu season and covid is still out there. In the weeks ahead, as a family, we will be very cautious to reduce our risk of getting ill.&nbsp;If any of us get sick in the weeks ahead it will add challenges to Sam and the BMT process as he will be entering a phase where he has no immune system for weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>I am continually thankful for our medical teams here. They continue to provide incredible care. They are always open to conversation and answering questions. They have been incredibly pro-active and I am glad we are prepared for the next steps.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that the chemotherapy has been effective at initially reducing the cancer and lately keeping the cancer contained (as indicated by the PET scan). Thankful that these results allow us to move forward.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Due to some timing and logistics we have had to change donors. We are thankful for this current donor who will provide a peripheral blood sample and is a good match for Sam.</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. All the pieces need to fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>See <a href="../../posts/2308/2023-08-26_results-and-recommendations.html">Aug.&nbsp;26 post</a> for the round 4 results↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-15_Results-round-6.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PET this morning</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-13_pending-PET-scan.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="pet-scan" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pet-scan">PET Scan</h2>
<p>Sam has a PET scan first thing this morning. This scan is the best tool for imaging the state of his cancer and how his chemotherapy has progressed. Decisions moving forward will be based on the results of this scan.</p>
<p>Needless to say, all of us, including the medical team, are anxious for the results. Preliminary findings may be available by the end of the day but the full report will not be available until next week.</p>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Although we did not want to be in-hospital over this weekend we are glad that Sam’s health is so well guarded by the team here.</p></li>
<li><p>We are closing off this first major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy we will pivot to the bone marrow treatment plan.</p></li>
<li><p>That we would have enough strength/stamina, especially for Sam, as we are booked solid preparing for the BMT.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>We are thankful for a donor who is a match for Sam and that they are willing to undergo the full bone marrow extraction process!</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. All the pieces need to fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-13_pending-PET-scan.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Thankfulness in this journey</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-09_thanks-giving.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/supercars.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A Supercars event at the RMH. We got to explore and ride in some amazing cars</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="giving-thanks" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="giving-thanks">Giving thanks</h2>
<p>It is early morning here at BC Children’s hospital and my family is sleeping peacefully. In-hospital is not where we had hoped to be this Thanks Giving, as family in the area were hoping to host us. It would have been great to share a meal, visit with them, and catch up the additional nephews that had flown in. Despite our current situation we still have so much to be thankful for. Top of my mind:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>We are here and we have access to an incredible medical team and facility.</p></li>
<li><p>We are able to walk this journey as a family. Support from work, family and friends, church, and the local community allows us to be here without having to worry about life and responsibilities back home. Thank you!</p></li>
<li><p>The Ronald McDonald House provides us a home away from home.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has been able to connect with friends – especially in the last couple weeks. They talked or talked while playing online games.</p></li>
<li><p>Visitors: We have family in the area that come by on a regular basis to support us. We have friends that make extra efforts to some and see us.</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="highlights-from-this-past-week" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights-from-this-past-week">Highlights from this past week</h3>
<dl>
<dt>Baseline tests and clinic days</dt>
<dd>
<p>As we begin to wrap up round 6 and pivot to bone-marrow transplant there are many medical appointments. This week was full with regular clinic visits plus the addition of baseline tests.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Thursday Nana and Kevin visit</dt>
<dd>
<p>Kevin and I got away – we roamed around downtown and grabbed dinner. It was great to away from the hospital campus for a few hours.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Nana visited with Sam and Tina at the Ronald McDonald House. Following the loss of Gord, Mary has moved south where she is surrounded by family and can access Sam. She in a suite attached to Kevin and Shannon’s.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Friday’s fever</dt>
<dd>
<p>It was a normal clinic visit on Friday morning. We had gone in expecting to review blood levels and then return to the RMH. However, Sam spiked a fever. In a normal non-cancer scenario any of us would just sleep it off, but Sam’s immune system is compromised. Antibiotics were started, tests and bacterial cultures were ordered, and plans were made to admit Sam to the ward for this past weekend. We are hoping/expecting to be discharged later today to return to the RMH.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Dave and Louise SP, friends of ours working in SE Asia were able to stop by before catching their flight back. Great to catch up with and be encouraged by them.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Supercars Saturday</dt>
<dd>
<p>One of the other parents at the RMH was able to connect with a group of Supercar owners. We thought we might miss-out but the doctor here gave Sam an afternoon pass to take part. We were able to talk with the owners, look at, sit in, and got for some quick rides in these beautiful cars. Makes included Ferrari, Lamborghini, McLaren, and Mercedes. I think whenever I see one of these cars on the road I will always remember the joy on all the families faces and the hospitality of all the owners.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>This week is very full includes:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Clinic check-ins</p></li>
<li><p>Tuesday: Bone marrow biopsy and Lumbar puncture – to confirm that cancer continues to not be present in Sam’s bones or central nervous system</p></li>
<li><p>Wednesday will start with a consult with a radiation oncologist (doctor specializing in the use of radiation therapy to combat cancer). This will be followed by Resporatory function and hearing tests – to establish baseline metrics before the bone marrow transplant</p></li>
<li><p>Friday: PET Scan to determine the current state of Sam’s cancer – though the results will not be available until the following week. \</p>
<p>This will be followed by an ultrasound of Sam’s neck where heavy blood clotting was found associated with the cancer. It is expected that these clots have been reduced.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Although we did not want to be in-hospital over this weekend we are glad that Sam’s health is so well guarded by the team here.</p></li>
<li><p>We are closing off this first major chapter in Sam’s treatment. With the completion of this last/ sixth round of chemotherapy we will pivot to the bone marrow treatment plan.</p></li>
<li><p>That we would have enough strength/stamina, especially for Sam, as we are booked solid preparing for the BMT.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>We are thankful for a donor who is a match for Sam and that they are willing to undergo the full bone marrow extraction process!</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. All the pieces need to fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-09_thanks-giving.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Remembrance of Papa Gord</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-02_remembrance.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="last-goodbyes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="last-goodbyes">Last goodbyes</h2>
<p>Last week was hard but beautiful.</p>
<p>On Friday Sept.&nbsp;29 at 11:00am Papa Gord (Tina’s Dad) passed on to eternity. He was surrounded by his family: Mary, Cal &amp; Tricia, Shannon &amp; Kevin, and Tina. Sam and I had to stay here at the RMH but we were also able to have final conversations, express our love, and say our goodbyes with Gord (via FaceTime). The other grandchildren were able to say goodbye via facetime as well.</p>
<p>Mary and Gord have given us an incredible legacy of love and commitment. It is and will be hard losing Gord though it was beautiful to share in the love of the family as they were able to spend a number of days with Gord before the end.</p>
<section id="the-week-in-review" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-week-in-review">The week in review</h3>
<dl>
<dt>Tuesday – a whirlwind of day.</dt>
<dd>
<p>It started with a big clinic day including lots of time with Dr. Jacob, the team lead of the BMT team, providing us a review of the process going forward. During this conversation Tina was fielding various communications regarding her dad, that he was in ER in Prince George.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Great news from this day was that there is a bone marrow donor for Sam, and the donor is willing to undergo the bone marrow extraction process. This is great news for Sam’s path of healing.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>By mid-afternoon flights were booked and in the evening Tina’s brother Cal and his wife Tricia picked Tina up to head for the airport where they met Tina’s sister Shannon and her husband Kevin – the five of them travelled to Prince George to see Gord. While they were en route Sam and I had a good FaceTime conversation with Papa Gord.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Wednesday – Thursday</dt>
<dd>
<p>Gord, though responsive, was not going to recover. By the end of day on Wed. he was transferred to Hospice. The siblings and Tina’s mom Mary, spent great quality time with Gord – sharing loving memories.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Back at the RMH Sam and I kept going with medications, pain control, and connected with the family in Prince George. Mucositis was really bad these days.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Friday</dt>
<dd>
<p>The family had a few more hours with Gord and at ~11:00am he entered eternity.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Here in Vancouver, Sam and I were in clinic, including meetings with different doctors and a blood transfusion, when we received word about Papa’s passing.</p>
<p>Sam is happy, though with tears, for Papa to be free of his declining body. Sam spoke words of hope to Papa, about seeing him again in heaven and sharing great experiences there (e.g.&nbsp;fishing and golfing together). Gord’s beautiful strong and gentle soul will be missed here.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Saturday – Sunday</dt>
<dd>
<p>The Prince George team made final arrangements for Gord and began their travels back to the lower mainland, bringing Mary with them to stay at Shannon’s home and be near family. Tina got back to us on Sunday afternoon.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Saturday night was a rough one for Sam and I. Sam hit the limit on what I was allowed to give him for pain control. Help was just a phone-call away. The on-call oncologist provided me additional pain control instructions and I was so glad to hear Sam gently snoring by early morning. Plans were also put in place to visit the hospital during the day – Sam got a blood transfusion.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>This week includes:</p>
<ul>
<li>regular clinic visits – and likely more blood products</li>
<li>more planning for the BMT</li>
<li>Some medical imaging as the medical teams create a baseline of Sam – essential for determining impacts of the radiation and BMT process.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that Tina and her siblings were able to make it back home and spend quality time with Papa Gord. Please keep the family in mind.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam has been able to connect with a number of friends from back home via online discussion tools and games.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that when things do get difficult (e.g.&nbsp;pain management and low blood levels) help is only a phone call away. The medical team here at BC Childrens continue to be amazing.</p></li>
<li><p>Chemotherapy continues to take its toll. His energy levels are lower with each round. As with previous rounds Sam’s blood counts are falling and mucositis has set in. We hope that that these side effects will be less intense and that they can be short lived – that Sam does not have to feel gross.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>We are thankful for a donor who is a match for Sam and that they are willing to undergo the full bone marrow extraction process!</li>
<li>We are desiring that side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects long term</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. All the pieces need to fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-10-02_remembrance.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Completing round six’s treatment phase</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-23_r6-treatment.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It is early Saturday morning, day 5 of Sam’s chemotherapy, Sam and Tina are sleeping. Today is the last chemo-drug delivery day for this sixth round. Today is the last drug delivery day for this current treatment regime. Thanks to our medical team here, by adjusting chemo delivery times a little each day we will get out of the hospital and back to the RMH by mid-afternoon – much better than having to spend another night which is more the standard.</p>
<p>Sam continues to take on this challenge well. He is determined and has made the most of his time here. Specifically, this time, he made choices to simply get out of the hospital room. We spent hours sitting on the terrace/deck and in the family lounge reading and playing cards – I finally beat Sam at crib though I expect this victory will be short lived.</p>
<p>The realities of not going home after this treatment, and of not starting school with his friends, are setting in and it is hard. Sam misses home, his friends, and our life there. This is hard for him.</p>
<p>We also choose hope and courage. There is a plan and the next steps are laid out ahead of us. We can do this.</p>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Regular check-ins at clinic.</p></li>
<li><p>Tuesday we will also meet with the BMT team to review how their planning are going.<br>
</p></li>
<li><p>In the weeks ahead there will be numerous baseline tests before starting radiation and BMT therapies. I have these next steps outlined in <a href="../../plan.html"><em>The Plan</em></a>.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for the care and connections with other families here at the RMH. We are all walking our own journeys with our children in need. Although each story is unique we find solidarity and some levels of comfort and council in the sharing of similar experiences. Over time these families are becoming friends.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam remains in good spirits about the upcoming process (i.e.&nbsp;bone-marrow-transplant). He knows it will be tough but he also knows that there is hope in completing this plan. It is hard to see him carry all of this. He has lots of hard days where he feels gross and with low energy, but he remains determined and even encouraged.</p></li>
<li><p>Chemotherapy continues to take its toll. His energy levels are lower with each round. The next phase of this round of chemotherapy will see his blood counts fall, an mucositis will likely set in. We hope that that these impacts are not as strong as the last couple times and that Sam does not need to feel as gross.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam will need strength for the BMT journey ahead.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>We are thankful for donors who are good matches for Sam. We need one of them to agree to undergo the marrow extraction process. One option is to just receive blood but the better option is to receive marrow. The latter, receiving marrow, is far better for Sam but involves a intense procedure for the donor.</li>
<li>Side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. That all the pieces fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for Sam’s school who are looking forward to his return and who are willing to work with us once Sam is able. We are thankful for his classmates who wrote him and sent him gifts.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-23_r6-treatment.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 23 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Courage and Despair</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-19_courage-and-despair.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Definitions
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<div class="quarto-layout-panel">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<section id="courage" class="level3 courage quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="courage">cour·age</h3>
<dl>
<dt><em>/ˈkərij/</em></dt>
<dd>
<p>the ability to do something that frightens one.<br>
“she called on all her courage to face the ordeal”</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>strength in the face of pain or grief.<br>
“he fought his illness with great courage”</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="despair" class="level3 despair quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="despair">de·spair</h3>
<dl>
<dt><em>/dəˈsper/</em></dt>
<dd>
<p>the complete loss or absence of hope.<br>
“in despair, I hit the bottle”</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
</div>
</div>
<p><span style="font-size: 80%"><em>Google definitions powered by Oxford Languages</em></span></p>
</div>
</div>
<p>This morning I am writing from the RMH dining hall as my family sleeps upstairs. It is the morning of day 154, and day 1 of round 6 should start later today. This has been a hard and long journey. If all had gone as hoped this would be a day to celebrate as it would be the beginning of the last round of therapy. But things have not gone as planned, and this is just one more step in the effort to rid Sam’s body of cancer.</p>
<section id="courage-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="courage-1">Courage</h2>
<p>I have often told Sam that, though we may not get to choose our circumstances, we can always choose how we respond to them. Will we respond courageously and act rightly/ virtuously? Or do we react in frustration – and further fuel the storm<sup>1</sup>? Sam has been incredibly courageous. Facing this storm, this terrifying storm, and he has chosen courage. Not that he has never felt fear. Rather, courage is not the absence of fear, it is choosing to face it.</p>
</section>
<section id="facing-despair" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="facing-despair">Facing Despair</h2>
<p>This past week I was exhausted – mentally and emotionally exhausted, and it was starting to take a toll on me physically. I was not only wrestling with this cancer storm, I wrestled with my worldview at the core of my being; the foundations of how I interpret life have been shaken to the core. I wrestled with God – where is my God who saves. I have faced Despair and I had moments where I felt that beast would take me.</p>
<p>I am no longer there. I have faced the beast Despair. And I now walk with new energy and freedom. It is not by my own power that I have overcome. I am still processing all the layers that have come together to provide this victory<sup>2</sup>. Numerous pieces have come together including snippets of conversations, the example of another family, concepts from a good book, and some additional experiences.</p>
<p>A simplification of some lessons learned:</p>
<ol type="a">
<li>Cancer is evil.</li>
<li>God is good.</li>
<li>There is hope.</li>
<li>Despite this storm we are able to <em>live the good life</em>.<br>
I am intentionally leaving this undefined for now, and leave it for you to wrestle with.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="highlights-from-this-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights-from-this-past-week">Highlights from this past week</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Wed. and Thursday</dt>
<dd>
Quiet days at the RMH. Lots of rest as Sam’s numbers continued to return. Tina and I got out to Cambie Village for a coffee together.
</dd>
<dt>Friday</dt>
<dd>
Cal was able to visit. We are grateful for his care and compassion, and conversations with Cal always thought provoking.
</dd>
<dd>
Gram and Papa C. arrived and visited here at the RMH. Great to receive their love and the love of Buddy.
</dd>
<dt>Saturday through Monday</dt>
<dd>
We had a number of good visits with my parents. This included them visiting us here and us making a couple trips out to their trailer in Ft. Langley to enjoy the last of summer camping. One afternoon while Sam had time with his grandparents Tina and I had some time to roam Ft. Langley together. Another afternoon I took Buddy for a short hike to Tavistock View Point on McMillan Island.
</dd>
<dd>
Yesterday evening Tina was filled with joy having a chance to play with her nieces Jane, Amanda, and great-niece Jayme (Amanda’s daughter), at the campsite playground.
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="victories-and-concerns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="victories-and-concerns">Victories and concerns</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for the care and connections with other families here at the RMH. We are all walking our own journeys with our children in need. Although each story is unique we find solidarity and some levels of comfort and council in the sharing of similarities in the struggle. Over time these families are becoming friends.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam remains in good spirits about the upcoming process (i.e.&nbsp;bone-marrow-transplant). He knows it will be tough but he also knows that there is hope in completing this plan. It is hard to see him carry all of this. He has lots of hard days where he feels gross and with low energy, but he remains determined and even encouraged.</p></li>
<li><p>Chemotherapy continues to take its toll. His energy levels are lower with each round. As we enter round 6 Sam’s strength has been diminished. He needs strength for the journey ahead.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>We are thankful for donors who are good matches for Sam. We need one of them to agree to undergo the marrow extraction process. One option is to just receive blood but the better option is to receive marrow. The latter, receiving marrow, is far better for Sam but involves a intense procedure for the donor.</li>
<li>Side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. That all the pieces fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for Sam’s school who are looking forward to his return and who are willing to work with us once Sam is able. We are thankful for his classmates who wrote him and sent him gifts.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I think I have said this better here then I have every said it to him↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>I may write more on this in the weeks ahead↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-19_courage-and-despair.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Round 5: Thru the valley</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-12_thru-the-valley.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Yesterday, we were in clinic. Sam’s blood levels indicate that he is starting to climb out of the round 5 chemo-valley. He is through the worst of this round.</p>
<section id="this-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="this-past-week">This past week</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Most of a day at the BC Cancer clinic to begin planning for radiation treatments.</p></li>
<li><p>Clinic visits at BC Children’s including additional blood transfusions to bolster Sam through through the chemo-valley.</p></li>
<li><p>We snuck Tina home for a few days so that she could take care of some of her own medical needs. She came back to us with her heart-bucket filled having connected with family and a few friends.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has able to connect with friends online and with a new friends here at the RMH.</p></li>
<li><p>The Frickers visited on Sunday. I love seeing Sam’s face brighten as he spends time with his cousin Kaden.</p></li>
<li><p>Last night David and Krista C. were able to visit. So good to catch up with friends and have normal conversation. They also brought personal care-card from Sam’s classmates which he loved. Krista also gifted her with her cookies – dangerously good.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Clinic appointments including a fairly routine lumbar puncture this Friday.</p></li>
<li><p>We are looking forward to a weekend. Sam should be out of the chemo-valley. An opportunity to feel good for a few days before we do it all again.</p></li>
<li><p>Gram and Papa C. along with Buddy will be down for this weekend.</p></li>
<li><p>Round 6 will start next Tuesday.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are thankful to be through the valley of round five.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam is in good spirits about the upcoming process (i.e.&nbsp;bone-marrow-transplant). He knows it will be tough but he also knows that it has an end. It is hard to see him carry all of this. He has lots of hard days where he feels gross and with low energy, but he remains determined and even encouraged.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together. Top of mind:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>We are thankful for donors who are good matches for Sam. We need one of them to agree to undergo the marrow extraction process. One option is to just receive blood but the better option is to receive marrow. The latter, receiving marrow, is far better for Sam but involves a intense procedure for the donor.</li>
<li>Side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. That all the pieces fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement – they really do bolster us.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for Sam’s school who are looking forward to his return and who are willing to work with us once Sam is able. We are thankful for his classmates who wrote him and sent him gifts.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-12_thru-the-valley.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A day of relief</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-05_day-of-relief.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Yesterday morning we wheeled Sam over to one of his clinic visits. We often use a wheelchair to go back and forth to the hospital as Sam’s energy is so low. He still has the strength to walk but not the energy. During these visits Sam’s blood levels are checked as the chemotherapy drugs knock them back, and we need to be sure he does not get knocked back too hard. The results of the tests came back and his hemoglobin and platelet numbers were low enough that he would have to spend an addition three hours in clinic receiving transfusions… but this time was worth it.</p>
<p>It is amazing what some additional blood can do. Following the clinic Sam walked most of the way back to the RMH. He took the stairs. He enjoyed dinner. He wanted to wrestle and he spent lots of energy teasing us. … So good to see our Sam be himself!</p>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are all exhausted. Sam has to carry the greatest burden with undergoing this treatment. Tina and I are there to walk with him each step of the way and to provide all the parental care and also practical nursing care. I don’t think I look to see the end of this storm anymore … rather I just hold on.</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Yesterday provided some relief from our fatigue – So good to see Sam have some energy again.</em></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that there is a plan. However:<br>
The challenge with all of these plans is that we are in unknown territory. I stated early on that Sam’s cancer is very rare. The reality is that it is essentially unknown. In the world, there has been only one other documented case of this form of cancer. So, all of these plans are based in professional judgement/ best-guess. We are thankful for our medical team that is able provide guidance, but we recognize that there is no standard protocol for Sam’s cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>We have a long list of new concerns which I am yet to process. Top of mind:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Although it seems there are good matches for Sam, a donor needs to be willing to make a donation, and all the logistics of timing and delivery need to come together.</li>
<li>Side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. That all the pieces fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for willing donors who are good matches for Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Please keep your notes of encouragement coming – they can really bolster us.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for Sam’s school who are looking forward to his return and who are willing to work with us once Sam is able.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-05_day-of-relief.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The BMT plan</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-04_BMT-plan.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Day 139, we are at the Ronald McDonald House as the impacts of the latest chemo-drug deliveries take hold. Once again we are heading into the valley. Each round gets harder as Sam is continually beat down by this treatment regime. Truth be told at this point the treatment seems as bad as the disease, but we must push on. Mucositis is worse again with intense nausea. Sam has been experiencing pain deep in his bones as his body works so hard (based on his last PET scan his bone density is falling). We are doing ‘ok’ in the management of these symptoms by utilizing higher doses of morphine and nausea control medications.</p>
<section id="highlights-from-this-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights-from-this-past-week">Highlights from this past week</h2>
<p>Despite low energy levels, Sam has been able to rise and join in on life a number of times as family and friends have come to visit.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Little cousin Jayme delivered donuts</p></li>
<li><p>Sam had a good couple hours with the Fricker family and in particular with cousin Kaden.</p></li>
<li><p>Nana returned home. Mary, thank you for all of your love and support.</p></li>
<li><p>Rob D. was able to have a short visit with Tina and I. Thanks for coming to see us.</p></li>
<li><p>This past weekend Hunter and Brian L. made the trip from PG to be with Sam. Many thanks for your friendship.</p></li>
<li><p>In addition, Sam has been able to connect with friends online a few times.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="bmt-plan" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bmt-plan">BMT Plan</h2>
<p><em>BMT: Bone Marrow Transplant</em><br>
</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Disclaimer
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>I feel I need a quick disclaimer here as I am not sure I have all of this right. In addition, the following dates are rough estimates from the medical team. In broad strokes I think most of the items below are pretty much there … dates and details are likely to change.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>During last week’s clinic visits we gained some more clarity on the planned treatment for Sam.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Sam will complete the full six rounds of his initial chemotherapy.<br>
There had been some discussion about skipping the 6<sup>th</sup> round and going straight to bone-marrow-transplant (BMT) but there was just too many moving parts. The team needed more time to line everything up. This means we have about six weeks remaining in this treatment regime before pivoting to BMT.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for BMT Sam will see numerous specialists throughout BC Childrens and the BC Cancer Clinic. The goal will be to create a strong baseline of Sam’s health going into BMT.</p></li>
<li><p>Bone Marrow Transplant: Day zero is estimated to be <em>Nov.&nbsp;2</em> .<br>
Following the current chemotherapy we will transition to BMT. The medical team refers to the actual transplant day as day 0. Activities prior to this day are count-down days and then the days following start counting up.</p>
<ul>
<li><p><em>Days -12 to -8</em> (~Oct.&nbsp;16): Radiation targeting whatever cancerous masses remain. The goal is to set the cancer back as hard as they can.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Days -7 to -2</em>: Chemotherapy to suppress and remove Sam’s own immune system.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Day -1</em>: General full body radiation to ensure Sam’s own immune system is completely removed – in preparation for replacing with the transplant/ graft immune system.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Day zero</em>, currently planned for Nov.&nbsp;2, Sam should receive the transplant. This is actually quite simple – like receiving a blood transfusion. The team will hang the bag of bone marrow products and pump it into Sam’s body via his central line.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Days 0 to 30</em> Sam will be in an isolation room with strict protocols. Tina and I, along with the medical team will be allowed in.<br>
</p></li>
<li><p><em>Days 31 through 90</em>: If all goes well Sam will be allowed out of the hospital but is to remain close for regular check-ins.</p></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are all exhausted. Sam has to carry the greatest burden with undergoing this treatment. Tina and I are there to walk with him each step of the way and to provide all the parental care and also practical nursing care. I don’t think I look to see the end of this storm anymore … rather I just hold on.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that there is a plan. However:<br>
The challenge with all of these plans is that we are in unknown territory. I stated early on that Sam’s cancer is very rare. The reality is that it is essentially unknown. In the world, there has been only one other documented case of this form of cancer. So, all of these plans are based in professional judgement/ best-guess. We are thankful for our medical team that is able provide guidance, but we recognize that there is no standard protocol for Sam’s cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>We have a long list of new concerns which I am yet to process. Top of mind:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Although it seems there are good matches for Sam, a donor needs to be willing to make a donation, and all the logistics of timing and delivery need to come together.</li>
<li>Side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. That all the pieces fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for willing donors who are good matches for Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Please keep your notes of encouragement coming – they can really bolster us.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for Sam’s school who are looking forward to his return and who are willing to work with us once Sam is able.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>plans</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-04_BMT-plan.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Results and recommendations</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-26_results-and-recommendations.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Addition: August 30, 2023
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Yesterday, Sam completed his fifth round of chemo drug delivery and we were able to leave the hospital (11:pm). Currently, the family is sleeping (Sam, Tina, and Nana)and we don’t have to give any meds for almost two hours.</p>
<p>Very little new information yet. We have had a couple more conversations, and met another doctor. There are definitely a lot of moving parts happening in the background as the various teams need to coordinate schedules and activities.</p>
<p>Moving forward I expect the next couple weeks will become busier and busier. On top of the regular clinic check in days there will be lots of tests to complete, and medical teams to meet. The post below still covers the bulk of what we know.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>This morning, <em>August 26</em>, I am writing from Sam’s hospital room. He is here for the planned delivery of his fifth round of chemotherapy. Sam is sleeping well. I slept ‘ok’ but my mind has been busy as I process the results and recommendations from yesterday.</p>
<p>Yesterday we reviewed the results of the latest PET scan with Sam’s oncologist and clinical nurse. The good news is that the cancerous masses have been reduced further and that there is no new cancer. The challenge is that the rate of reduction in Sam’s cancer will not be enough to see it removed by the end of either this or the next round. We must consider further treatment options.</p>
<p>Following his current treatment Sam will most likely transition to a bone-marrow-transplant treatment protocol. This will involve:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Radiation</p></li>
<li><p>Further intense chemotherapy (drugs)</p></li>
<li><p>Isolation – though Tina and I will still be able to be with him, Sam will be sequestered in a special room during the transplant period of 4-6 weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>Significantly more time here at BC Childrens to accommodate all of this.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Amazingly, we already know that there a several good transplant matches for Sam!</p>
<p>There will be many meetings upcoming as new plans are made, and as we transfer his care to the bone-marrow transplant team. Although this is hard, I don’t think we would have been satisfied with anything less. This is the best option for Sam and it should provide life-long defense against this cancer.</p>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are thankful that the cancer is further reduced.</p></li>
<li><p>We have a long list of new concerns which I am yet to process. Top of mind:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Although it seems there are good matches for Sam. That a donor would be willing to make the donation, and all the logistics of timing and delivery would come together.</li>
<li>Side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. That all the pieces fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the care and support of the medical teams here.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for willing donors who are good matches for Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-26_results-and-recommendations.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pending results and preparing for round 5</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-25_round5-starting.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Round 4 is officially complete. It has been a rough one with little relief. The previous rounds Sam would usually have 2-4 days of feeling more normal… This past round hardly let up. As he was starting to feel a little better he was hit with another bought of nausea and mucositis.</p>
<p>Sam has a very significant clinic appointment today.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>We should receive the results of the lasted PET scan and lumbar-puncture</p></li>
<li><p>The medical team may be ready to present recommendations for treatment – will a bone marrow transplant be necessary?</p></li>
<li><p>Round 5 is likely to start today. This will begin with five days in hospital for chemo-drug delivery.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>All this to say, I am a little anxious this morning.</p>
<section id="looking-back-the-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-back-the-past-week">Looking back – the past week</h2>
<p>Despite Sam has not felt great we have had some great visits this week.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>On Monday, we had a last visit with my parents and Buddy before they made the return drive back to Prince George.</p></li>
<li><p>Tuesday, Tina’s mom arrived!</p></li>
<li><p>Wednesday, Korena and Samuel Z. were here for the afternoon. This was Sam’s strongest day and it was great to see him reconnect with a friend. Also great to see Korena and Tina reconnect!</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>So thankful for all our friends and family for your visits, care, and on-going communication.</p></li>
<li><p>I am amazed the medical tech. that is available to support the decision making here. Results of the PT scan are expected today.</p></li>
<li><p>This round has been a challenge with much stronger side-effects causing pain and nausea. We have adapted and learned how to manage much of it.</p></li>
<li><p>We expect that major decisions will be discussed regarding Sam’s future treatment – specifically determining if Sam will need a bone-marrow transplant.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-25_round5-starting.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pending…</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-21_pending.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/clinic_sam-tina.JPG" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A typical clinic day view. Waiting for bloodwork and discussions with the medical team.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It is Monday morning. Much of the province is covered in smoke and many are trying to find places to live. What a challenging time for so many.</p>
<p>Our own challenges continue.</p>
<section id="looking-back-the-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-back-the-past-week">Looking back – the past week</h2>
<p>As far as medical procedures, it was a mostly uneventful week… too uneventful. We had the usual clinic check-ins. Sam only needed one transfusion this round (platelets). Friday, Sam was scheduled to have a PET. This scan generates a 3-dimensional image of his body and where the cancer is in it. However, maintenance issues caused this scan to be postponed – hopefully Sam can get in this Wednesday.</p>
<p>The rest of the week was focused on the management of Sam’s side-effects. We have had to be very strict with the scheduling his medications this round. We have seen decent success in managing his nausea and some success in managing his pain. Sam’s energy levels have been low, and his bone ache as his marrow is in full production mode to restore the blood that was destroyed in this last round of chemo.</p>
</section>
<section id="looking-back-the-past-weekend" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-back-the-past-weekend">Looking back – the past weekend</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/ice-cream_c-t-gram-papa-buddy.JPG" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">We took my parents out for ice cream and brought some back for Sam</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Two great reports from the weekend!</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>My parents were down and though our visits were fairly short, given Sam’s energy levels, it was great to see them. Of course they brought Buddy and he was a joy to all including numerous other families that stopped to meet him near the Ronald McDonald House entrance.</p></li>
<li><p>The community driven <em>Fish for a Wish</em> event was held out at Aleza Lake. It sounds like it was a great day for everyone who attended! The numbers are still be finalized but there is a significant donation to support Sam in this cancer journey. We are amazed and humbled at the support of the community! Thank you!</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>PET scan should happen this week.</p></li>
<li><p>This weeks clinic appointments are significant. The medical team will be meeting to discuss Sam’s case either today or tomorrow morning. From that meeting we expect that recommendations will be made regarding next steps. Specifically, will there be a need for a bone-marrow transplant? If ‘no’ then we will finish the current plan, likely wrapping up the main treatment by the end of October. If ‘yes’, following this treatment plan (near the end of Oct.), Sam will likely start the bone-marrow transplant protocol.</p></li>
<li><p>Round 5 is planned to start this coming Friday.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>I am amazed at our community, their support, and their gifts.</p></li>
<li><p>I am amazed the medical tech. that is available to support the decision making here. Sure the PET was delayed but we have access to this and the delay is simply an inconvenience.</p></li>
<li><p>We are very appreciative of all the support, notes of encouragement, and other communications. Tina wishes that she had capacity to respond to these. Her on-going health concerns are the major cause of her inability to reply. Please know that your messages to her have been received and are held dear … despite any lack of response on her part.</p></li>
<li><p>This round has been a challenge with much stronger side-effects causing pain and nausea. We have adapted and learned how to manage much of it. The pain in particular has been most difficult.</p></li>
<li><p>This week, likely tomorrow, we expect that major decisions will be discussed regarding Sam’s future treatment – specifically determining if Sam will need a bone-marrow transplant.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-21_pending.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Reflections on round 4</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-14_round-4.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Sam has made it past the halfway mark of the fourth round of chemotherapy. We have been told from the beginning that we would need to remain flexible and adapt as each round would be different. There are so many changes each round, to the drug mix, to the cancer, to Sam’s body that it is not possible to know what the impacts will be each time. To date, it seemed that each round was getting easier and I had grown to expect that pattern to continue. However, this round turned our expectations up-side-down.</p>
<p>It has been a storm. Following our last clinic appointment Sam’s medications were adjusted, and this new medication plan have made things easier. By yesterday, it seems we have his nausea and pain mostly under control and options for when it is not. So what happened?</p>
<p>Our experience and discussion with the medical team point the majority of this points to a strong case of <a href="https://myhealth.alberta.ca/Health/aftercareinformation/pages/conditions.aspx?hwid=ack5321">mucositis</a> a common side-effect which results in the breakdown the mucus layer protecting the inside of the digestive track.</p>
<section id="the-last-few-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-last-few-days">The last few days</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>For the last few days Sam and I have enjoyed boy-time together. As Sam’s energy levels are low from a mix of the side-effects and medications we have probably had too much screen-time, and too much junk food – though I will let Sam eat anything these days in order to get calories into him.</p></li>
<li><p>Tina has been in Edmonton area as our representative at Kurt and Marielle’s wedding. From the video-feed, and Tina’s descriptions and photos it looked like an amazing day! Sam and I were able congratulate Kurtis via FaceTime.</p></li>
<li><p>Yesterday we had a great visit with our friend Wes S.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Clinic appointments and likely blood transfusions as the chemo brings Sam’s blood counts down dangerously low.</p></li>
<li><p>PET scan at the end of this week.</p></li>
<li><p>The <em>Fish for a Wish</em> event will be happening at Aleza Lake is happening this Saturday, August 19. There will be games, a bouncy castle, a silent auction, fishing, and the option to camp out. This year the community has chosen to support Sam!<br>
If you don’t know what I am talking about and you would like to attend send me a note and I will send you a Facebook invite.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are so excited that Tina was able to travel and attend wedding of Kurtis and Marielle F. A beautiful celebration, and great to share it with family and friends there.</p></li>
<li><p>This round has been a challenge with much stronger side-effects causing pain and nausea. In addition, Sam has reduced energy levels and appetite.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that recent changes to Sam’s daily medications have alleviated most of the pain and nausea. I hope that Sam get’s some level of appetite back.</p></li>
<li><p>There is concern that Sam will need further treatment (bone marrow transplant). There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-14_round-4.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Navigating the chemo-storm</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-09_navigating-the-storm.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Very little to update you on. This chemo-storm still rages on, but there have been moments of relief, and it seems we will be able to weather this latest challenge. We are making full use of all the tools available to us – that is the prescriptions, and they are taking the edge off.</p>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<p><em>repeated</em></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Tina had an amazing number of days away, attending Marielle’s bridal shower. It was good break. Sam and I did managed well on our own, but by the end of this short time away Tina was definitely missed.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to be past the drug delivery phase of round 4. Each round bring us closer to the end of this journey.</p></li>
<li><p>This time the side effects more intense, with nausea, pain, fatigue, and general feeling rotten.</p></li>
<li><p>Complicating Sam’s cancer journey are Tina’s on-going health issues. Being in Vancouver may present opportunities for us to continue to look for additional solutions. We are hoping that referrals and connections to medical providers specific to her situation come together.</p></li>
<li><p>We hope that there will not be a need for the contingency plan, a bone marrow transplant, yet we need to prepare ourselves for this possibility.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-09_navigating-the-storm.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>In the storm</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-06_past-the-midway.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It is the morning of day 111 and we have crossed mid-way of the treatment plan. Saturday was the fifth and final day of chemo-drug delivery for this round. That afternoon we left the hospital, returning to the Ronald McDonald House. It felt good to get away from the hospital and find the quiet of our room here, but it has been hard.</p>
<p>The truth of it is this journey is hard, long and hard. Sam has been amazing, a few days ago, day 2 and 3 of this treatment, he was the brightest and most active I have seen him in months: playing games, seeking social connections, including making a new friend.</p>
<p>In general, we were all expecting this round to be easier. From the past experience this set of drugs did not hit as hard. However, by day 4 Sam was lethargic and had intense brain-fog. Now that we are out of the hospital we are catching up on sleep, The fog seems to be lifting, but nausea and pain need to be managed constantly. Generally, Sam just feels gross.</p>
<p>Sam longs for normal days and our return to normal life – we all do. I fear I do not remember what normal is or how to find it. This cancer-storm is swirling around us – it is difficult to see beyond it.</p>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Tina had an amazing number of days away, attending Marielle’s bridal shower. It was good break. Sam and I did managed well on our own, but by the end of this short time away Tina was definitely missed.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to be past the drug delivery phase of round 4. Each round bring us closer to the end of this journey.</p></li>
<li><p>This time the side effects more intense, with nausea, pain, fatigue, and general feeling rotten.</p></li>
<li><p>Complicating Sam’s cancer journey are Tina’s on-going health issues. Being in Vancouver may present opportunities for us to continue to look for additional solutions. We are hoping that referrals and connections to medical providers specific to her situation come together.</p></li>
<li><p>We hope that there will not be a need for the contingency plan, a bone marrow transplant, yet we need to prepare ourselves for this possibility.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-06_past-the-midway.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Friends and the beginning of round 4</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-02_round4-begins-friends.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I think this has been the longest gap between posts. My silence is has simply been a break and waiting.</p>
<p>This morning I am writing from Sam’s hospital room, as yesterday Sam began round 4 of chemotherapy, and as per the plan he will be in the hospital for five days of drug delivery. We did have a delay over the last week as we needed to wait for his body to recover from round 3.</p>
<p>It had been a quiet week until this past weekend when we were encouraged by the love of friends and family. Unplanned, we had several visits almost back to back. So good to see you all!!</p>
<section id="recent-visits" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recent-visits">Recent visits</h2>
<p>We had many great talks, some special activities, games, an ice cream run, and a couple bike rides. Sam was encouraged to see his friends and family – though he did not get to engage with the activities as much as his energy was low.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Jess and Kate B. took Tina to Bard on the Beach and the Symphony of Fire (fireworks). Back at the RMH I visited with John Sr.&nbsp;and Sam with his classmate John (jr.).</p></li>
<li><p>A surprise visit with Auntie Shannon and Uncle Kevin. We knew Kevin was going to be here but they surprised us with a visit with Tina’s sister.</p></li>
<li><p>Brian, Beth, David, and Luke H. were here. The boys and Sam hung out while</p></li>
<li><p>I was able to have a quick quality visit with Mike J.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Many thanks to all of you! Your presence, your words, your friendship have encouraged us!</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>I am thrilled for Tina as she will be leaving us for a few days to attend Marielle’s bridal shower (engaged to Kurtis F.). How will Tina do away from us? How will we do with out her?</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for the support of friends and family.</p></li>
<li><p>Perhaps it was the quieter week that gave us space to realize how tired we are. Recent visits have lifted us but we are definitely feeling this marathon.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to keep going with the start of round 4. Each round bring us closer to the end of this journey.</p></li>
<li><p>The medical team here is great. Returning to the hospital is fairly easy. Many of the nurses know us and welcomed us back. Sam knows the routine and there is a comfort in the familiarity of it.</p></li>
<li><p>We hope that there will not be a need for the contingency plan (<a href="../../posts/2307/2023-07-17_contigency-plan.html">bone marrow transplant</a>), yet we need to prepare ourselves for it, and all the additional experiences and time that it may bring with it.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-02_round4-begins-friends.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Quiet waiting</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-27_quiet-delay.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Sam has completed round 3 of his chemotherapy. This marks half way through the current treatment plan. However, we are delayed in starting round 4. With each round of chemo Sam’s immune system is knocked back and metrics monitoring this drop to zero. Before he is able to start the next round his body needs to recover. This time the recovery is slow… so we wait. With low levels Sam is also low energy and life has been fairly quiet.</p>
<section id="highlights-from-the-last-few-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights-from-the-last-few-days">Highlights from the last few days</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Last Friday Sam had transfusions that lifted his energy for a couple days. We went out to Ft. Langley to visit with my parents and Buddy.</p></li>
<li><p>A surprise party to celebrated my 50<sup>th</sup> with family!</p></li>
<li><p>My parents came to us here at the RMH bringing Buddy with them.</p></li>
<li><p>Quiet days at the RMH allowing Sam to recover from chemo</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Today marks 100 days of this marathon. I am exhausted. I think we are all exhausted. Perhaps it is these quieter days that give us enough space to feel and not just do the work of managing it all.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the successful completion of round three. Recovery from this round is taking a little longer. Round 4 should start next week.</p></li>
<li><p>We hope that there will not be a need for the contingency plan (<a href="../../posts/2307/2023-07-17_contigency-plan.html">bone marrow transplant</a>), yet we need to prepare ourselves for it, and all the additional experiences and time that it may bring with it.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-27_quiet-delay.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
