<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Sam Chisholm</title>
<link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="http://samc-news.netlify.app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>News updating friends and family on our journey</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.361</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Round 5: Thru the valley</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-12_thru-the-valley.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Yesterday, we were in clinic. Sam’s blood levels indicate that he is starting to climb out of the round 5 chemo-valley. He is through the worst of this round.</p>
<section id="this-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="this-past-week">This past week</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Most of a day at the BC Cancer clinic to begin planning for radiation treatments.</p></li>
<li><p>Clinic visits at BC Children’s including additional blood transfusions to bolster Sam through through the chemo-valley.</p></li>
<li><p>We snuck Tina home for a few days so that she could take care of some of her own medical needs. She came back to us with her heart-bucket filled having connected with family and a few friends.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam has able to connect with friends online and with a new friends here at the RMH.</p></li>
<li><p>The Frickers visited on Sunday. I love seeing Sam’s face brighten as he spends time with his cousin Kaden.</p></li>
<li><p>Last night David and Krista C. were able to visit. So good to catch up with friends and have normal conversation. They also brought personal care-card from Sam’s classmates which he loved. Krista also gifted her with her cookies – dangerously good.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Clinic appointments including a fairly routine lumbar puncture this Friday.</p></li>
<li><p>We are looking forward to a weekend. Sam should be out of the chemo-valley. An opportunity to feel good for a few days before we do it all again.</p></li>
<li><p>Gram and Papa C. along with Buddy will be down for this weekend.</p></li>
<li><p>Round 6 will start next Tuesday.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are thankful to be through the valley of round five.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam is in good spirits about the upcoming process (i.e.&nbsp;bone-marrow-transplant). He knows it will be tough but he also knows that it has an end. It is hard to see him carry all of this. He has lots of hard days where he feels gross and with low energy, but he remains determined and even encouraged.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for the BMT there are numerous items that need to come together. Top of mind:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>We are thankful for donors who are good matches for Sam. We need one of them to agree to undergo the marrow extraction process. One option is to just receive blood but the better option is to receive marrow. The latter, receiving marrow, is far better for Sam but involves a intense procedure for the donor.</li>
<li>Side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. That all the pieces fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Thank you for your notes of encouragement – they really do bolster us.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for Sam’s school who are looking forward to his return and who are willing to work with us once Sam is able. We are thankful for his classmates who wrote him and sent him gifts.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern as the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-12_thru-the-valley.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A day of relief</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-05_day-of-relief.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Yesterday morning we wheeled Sam over to one of his clinic visits. We often use a wheelchair to go back and forth to the hospital as Sam’s energy is so low. He still has the strength to walk but not the energy. During these visits Sam’s blood levels are checked as the chemotherapy drugs knock them back, and we need to be sure he does not get knocked back too hard. The results of the tests came back and his hemoglobin and platelet numbers were low enough that he would have to spend an addition three hours in clinic receiving transfusions… but this time was worth it.</p>
<p>It is amazing what some additional blood can do. Following the clinic Sam walked most of the way back to the RMH. He took the stairs. He enjoyed dinner. He wanted to wrestle and he spent lots of energy teasing us. … So good to see our Sam be himself!</p>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are all exhausted. Sam has to carry the greatest burden with undergoing this treatment. Tina and I are there to walk with him each step of the way and to provide all the parental care and also practical nursing care. I don’t think I look to see the end of this storm anymore … rather I just hold on.</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Yesterday provided some relief from our fatigue – So good to see Sam have some energy again.</em></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that there is a plan. However:<br>
The challenge with all of these plans is that we are in unknown territory. I stated early on that Sam’s cancer is very rare. The reality is that it is essentially unknown. In the world, there has been only one other documented case of this form of cancer. So, all of these plans are based in professional judgement/ best-guess. We are thankful for our medical team that is able provide guidance, but we recognize that there is no standard protocol for Sam’s cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>We have a long list of new concerns which I am yet to process. Top of mind:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Although it seems there are good matches for Sam, a donor needs to be willing to make a donation, and all the logistics of timing and delivery need to come together.</li>
<li>Side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. That all the pieces fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for willing donors who are good matches for Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Please keep your notes of encouragement coming – they can really bolster us.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for Sam’s school who are looking forward to his return and who are willing to work with us once Sam is able.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-05_day-of-relief.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The BMT plan</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-04_BMT-plan.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Day 139, we are at the Ronald McDonald House as the impacts of the latest chemo-drug deliveries take hold. Once again we are heading into the valley. Each round gets harder as Sam is continually beat down by this treatment regime. Truth be told at this point the treatment seems as bad as the disease, but we must push on. Mucositis is worse again with intense nausea. Sam has been experiencing pain deep in his bones as his body works so hard (based on his last PET scan his bone density is falling). We are doing ‘ok’ in the management of these symptoms by utilizing higher doses of morphine and nausea control medications.</p>
<section id="highlights-from-this-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights-from-this-past-week">Highlights from this past week</h2>
<p>Despite low energy levels, Sam has been able to rise and join in on life a number of times as family and friends have come to visit.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Little cousin Jayme delivered donuts</p></li>
<li><p>Sam had a good couple hours with the Fricker family and in particular with cousin Kaden.</p></li>
<li><p>Nana returned home. Mary, thank you for all of your love and support.</p></li>
<li><p>Rob D. was able to have a short visit with Tina and I. Thanks for coming to see us.</p></li>
<li><p>This past weekend Hunter and Brian L. made the trip from PG to be with Sam. Many thanks for your friendship.</p></li>
<li><p>In addition, Sam has been able to connect with friends online a few times.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="bmt-plan" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bmt-plan">BMT Plan</h2>
<p><em>BMT: Bone Marrow Transplant</em><br>
</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Disclaimer
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>I feel I need a quick disclaimer here as I am not sure I have all of this right. In addition, the following dates are rough estimates from the medical team. In broad strokes I think most of the items below are pretty much there … dates and details are likely to change.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>During last week’s clinic visits we gained some more clarity on the planned treatment for Sam.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Sam will complete the full six rounds of his initial chemotherapy.<br>
There had been some discussion about skipping the 6<sup>th</sup> round and going straight to bone-marrow-transplant (BMT) but there was just too many moving parts. The team needed more time to line everything up. This means we have about six weeks remaining in this treatment regime before pivoting to BMT.</p></li>
<li><p>In preparation for BMT Sam will see numerous specialists throughout BC Childrens and the BC Cancer Clinic. The goal will be to create a strong baseline of Sam’s health going into BMT.</p></li>
<li><p>Bone Marrow Transplant: Day zero is estimated to be <em>Nov.&nbsp;2</em> .<br>
Following the current chemotherapy we will transition to BMT. The medical team refers to the actual transplant day as day 0. Activities prior to this day are count-down days and then the days following start counting up.</p>
<ul>
<li><p><em>Days -12 to -8</em> (~Oct.&nbsp;16): Radiation targeting whatever cancerous masses remain. The goal is to set the cancer back as hard as they can.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Days -7 to -2</em>: Chemotherapy to suppress and remove Sam’s own immune system.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Day -1</em>: General full body radiation to ensure Sam’s own immune system is completely removed – in preparation for replacing with the transplant/ graft immune system.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Day zero</em>, currently planned for Nov.&nbsp;2, Sam should receive the transplant. This is actually quite simple – like receiving a blood transfusion. The team will hang the bag of bone marrow products and pump it into Sam’s body via his central line.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Days 0 to 30</em> Sam will be in an isolation room with strict protocols. Tina and I, along with the medical team will be allowed in.<br>
</p></li>
<li><p><em>Days 31 through 90</em>: If all goes well Sam will be allowed out of the hospital but is to remain close for regular check-ins.</p></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are all exhausted. Sam has to carry the greatest burden with undergoing this treatment. Tina and I are there to walk with him each step of the way and to provide all the parental care and also practical nursing care. I don’t think I look to see the end of this storm anymore … rather I just hold on.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that there is a plan. However:<br>
The challenge with all of these plans is that we are in unknown territory. I stated early on that Sam’s cancer is very rare. The reality is that it is essentially unknown. In the world, there has been only one other documented case of this form of cancer. So, all of these plans are based in professional judgement/ best-guess. We are thankful for our medical team that is able provide guidance, but we recognize that there is no standard protocol for Sam’s cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>We have a long list of new concerns which I am yet to process. Top of mind:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Although it seems there are good matches for Sam, a donor needs to be willing to make a donation, and all the logistics of timing and delivery need to come together.</li>
<li>Side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. That all the pieces fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for willing donors who are good matches for Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the support of family and friends. Please keep your notes of encouragement coming – they can really bolster us.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for Sam’s school who are looking forward to his return and who are willing to work with us once Sam is able.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>plans</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2309/2023-09-04_BMT-plan.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Results and recommendations</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-26_results-and-recommendations.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Addition: August 30, 2023
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Yesterday, Sam completed his fifth round of chemo drug delivery and we were able to leave the hospital (11:pm). Currently, the family is sleeping (Sam, Tina, and Nana)and we don’t have to give any meds for almost two hours.</p>
<p>Very little new information yet. We have had a couple more conversations, and met another doctor. There are definitely a lot of moving parts happening in the background as the various teams need to coordinate schedules and activities.</p>
<p>Moving forward I expect the next couple weeks will become busier and busier. On top of the regular clinic check in days there will be lots of tests to complete, and medical teams to meet. The post below still covers the bulk of what we know.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>This morning, <em>August 26</em>, I am writing from Sam’s hospital room. He is here for the planned delivery of his fifth round of chemotherapy. Sam is sleeping well. I slept ‘ok’ but my mind has been busy as I process the results and recommendations from yesterday.</p>
<p>Yesterday we reviewed the results of the latest PET scan with Sam’s oncologist and clinical nurse. The good news is that the cancerous masses have been reduced further and that there is no new cancer. The challenge is that the rate of reduction in Sam’s cancer will not be enough to see it removed by the end of either this or the next round. We must consider further treatment options.</p>
<p>Following his current treatment Sam will most likely transition to a bone-marrow-transplant treatment protocol. This will involve:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Radiation</p></li>
<li><p>Further intense chemotherapy (drugs)</p></li>
<li><p>Isolation – though Tina and I will still be able to be with him, Sam will be sequestered in a special room during the transplant period of 4-6 weeks.</p></li>
<li><p>Significantly more time here at BC Childrens to accommodate all of this.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Amazingly, we already know that there a several good transplant matches for Sam!</p>
<p>There will be many meetings upcoming as new plans are made, and as we transfer his care to the bone-marrow transplant team. Although this is hard, I don’t think we would have been satisfied with anything less. This is the best option for Sam and it should provide life-long defense against this cancer.</p>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are thankful that the cancer is further reduced.</p></li>
<li><p>We have a long list of new concerns which I am yet to process. Top of mind:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Although it seems there are good matches for Sam. That a donor would be willing to make the donation, and all the logistics of timing and delivery would come together.</li>
<li>Side effects both immediate and long-term would be limited. <em>Ideally, that there would be no measurable side effects</em>.</li>
<li>The medical team have a huge coordination task ahead of them. That all the pieces fall into place for the best timing possible.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the care and support of the medical teams here.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for willing donors who are good matches for Sam.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <category>milestones</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-26_results-and-recommendations.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pending results and preparing for round 5</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-25_round5-starting.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Round 4 is officially complete. It has been a rough one with little relief. The previous rounds Sam would usually have 2-4 days of feeling more normal… This past round hardly let up. As he was starting to feel a little better he was hit with another bought of nausea and mucositis.</p>
<p>Sam has a very significant clinic appointment today.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>We should receive the results of the lasted PET scan and lumbar-puncture</p></li>
<li><p>The medical team may be ready to present recommendations for treatment – will a bone marrow transplant be necessary?</p></li>
<li><p>Round 5 is likely to start today. This will begin with five days in hospital for chemo-drug delivery.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>All this to say, I am a little anxious this morning.</p>
<section id="looking-back-the-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-back-the-past-week">Looking back – the past week</h2>
<p>Despite Sam has not felt great we have had some great visits this week.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>On Monday, we had a last visit with my parents and Buddy before they made the return drive back to Prince George.</p></li>
<li><p>Tuesday, Tina’s mom arrived!</p></li>
<li><p>Wednesday, Korena and Samuel Z. were here for the afternoon. This was Sam’s strongest day and it was great to see him reconnect with a friend. Also great to see Korena and Tina reconnect!</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>So thankful for all our friends and family for your visits, care, and on-going communication.</p></li>
<li><p>I am amazed the medical tech. that is available to support the decision making here. Results of the PT scan are expected today.</p></li>
<li><p>This round has been a challenge with much stronger side-effects causing pain and nausea. We have adapted and learned how to manage much of it.</p></li>
<li><p>We expect that major decisions will be discussed regarding Sam’s future treatment – specifically determining if Sam will need a bone-marrow transplant.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-25_round5-starting.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pending…</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-21_pending.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/clinic_sam-tina.JPG" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A typical clinic day view. Waiting for bloodwork and discussions with the medical team.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It is Monday morning. Much of the province is covered in smoke and many are trying to find places to live. What a challenging time for so many.</p>
<p>Our own challenges continue.</p>
<section id="looking-back-the-past-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-back-the-past-week">Looking back – the past week</h2>
<p>As far as medical procedures, it was a mostly uneventful week… too uneventful. We had the usual clinic check-ins. Sam only needed one transfusion this round (platelets). Friday, Sam was scheduled to have a PET. This scan generates a 3-dimensional image of his body and where the cancer is in it. However, maintenance issues caused this scan to be postponed – hopefully Sam can get in this Wednesday.</p>
<p>The rest of the week was focused on the management of Sam’s side-effects. We have had to be very strict with the scheduling his medications this round. We have seen decent success in managing his nausea and some success in managing his pain. Sam’s energy levels have been low, and his bone ache as his marrow is in full production mode to restore the blood that was destroyed in this last round of chemo.</p>
</section>
<section id="looking-back-the-past-weekend" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-back-the-past-weekend">Looking back – the past weekend</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/ice-cream_c-t-gram-papa-buddy.JPG" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">We took my parents out for ice cream and brought some back for Sam</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Two great reports from the weekend!</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>My parents were down and though our visits were fairly short, given Sam’s energy levels, it was great to see them. Of course they brought Buddy and he was a joy to all including numerous other families that stopped to meet him near the Ronald McDonald House entrance.</p></li>
<li><p>The community driven <em>Fish for a Wish</em> event was held out at Aleza Lake. It sounds like it was a great day for everyone who attended! The numbers are still be finalized but there is a significant donation to support Sam in this cancer journey. We are amazed and humbled at the support of the community! Thank you!</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>PET scan should happen this week.</p></li>
<li><p>This weeks clinic appointments are significant. The medical team will be meeting to discuss Sam’s case either today or tomorrow morning. From that meeting we expect that recommendations will be made regarding next steps. Specifically, will there be a need for a bone-marrow transplant? If ‘no’ then we will finish the current plan, likely wrapping up the main treatment by the end of October. If ‘yes’, following this treatment plan (near the end of Oct.), Sam will likely start the bone-marrow transplant protocol.</p></li>
<li><p>Round 5 is planned to start this coming Friday.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>I am amazed at our community, their support, and their gifts.</p></li>
<li><p>I am amazed the medical tech. that is available to support the decision making here. Sure the PET was delayed but we have access to this and the delay is simply an inconvenience.</p></li>
<li><p>We are very appreciative of all the support, notes of encouragement, and other communications. Tina wishes that she had capacity to respond to these. Her on-going health concerns are the major cause of her inability to reply. Please know that your messages to her have been received and are held dear … despite any lack of response on her part.</p></li>
<li><p>This round has been a challenge with much stronger side-effects causing pain and nausea. We have adapted and learned how to manage much of it. The pain in particular has been most difficult.</p></li>
<li><p>This week, likely tomorrow, we expect that major decisions will be discussed regarding Sam’s future treatment – specifically determining if Sam will need a bone-marrow transplant.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-21_pending.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Reflections on round 4</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-14_round-4.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Sam has made it past the halfway mark of the fourth round of chemotherapy. We have been told from the beginning that we would need to remain flexible and adapt as each round would be different. There are so many changes each round, to the drug mix, to the cancer, to Sam’s body that it is not possible to know what the impacts will be each time. To date, it seemed that each round was getting easier and I had grown to expect that pattern to continue. However, this round turned our expectations up-side-down.</p>
<p>It has been a storm. Following our last clinic appointment Sam’s medications were adjusted, and this new medication plan have made things easier. By yesterday, it seems we have his nausea and pain mostly under control and options for when it is not. So what happened?</p>
<p>Our experience and discussion with the medical team point the majority of this points to a strong case of <a href="https://myhealth.alberta.ca/Health/aftercareinformation/pages/conditions.aspx?hwid=ack5321">mucositis</a> a common side-effect which results in the breakdown the mucus layer protecting the inside of the digestive track.</p>
<section id="the-last-few-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-last-few-days">The last few days</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>For the last few days Sam and I have enjoyed boy-time together. As Sam’s energy levels are low from a mix of the side-effects and medications we have probably had too much screen-time, and too much junk food – though I will let Sam eat anything these days in order to get calories into him.</p></li>
<li><p>Tina has been in Edmonton area as our representative at Kurt and Marielle’s wedding. From the video-feed, and Tina’s descriptions and photos it looked like an amazing day! Sam and I were able congratulate Kurtis via FaceTime.</p></li>
<li><p>Yesterday we had a great visit with our friend Wes S.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Clinic appointments and likely blood transfusions as the chemo brings Sam’s blood counts down dangerously low.</p></li>
<li><p>PET scan at the end of this week.</p></li>
<li><p>The <em>Fish for a Wish</em> event will be happening at Aleza Lake is happening this Saturday, August 19. There will be games, a bouncy castle, a silent auction, fishing, and the option to camp out. This year the community has chosen to support Sam!<br>
If you don’t know what I am talking about and you would like to attend send me a note and I will send you a Facebook invite.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are so excited that Tina was able to travel and attend wedding of Kurtis and Marielle F. A beautiful celebration, and great to share it with family and friends there.</p></li>
<li><p>This round has been a challenge with much stronger side-effects causing pain and nausea. In addition, Sam has reduced energy levels and appetite.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that recent changes to Sam’s daily medications have alleviated most of the pain and nausea. I hope that Sam get’s some level of appetite back.</p></li>
<li><p>There is concern that Sam will need further treatment (bone marrow transplant). There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-14_round-4.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Navigating the chemo-storm</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-09_navigating-the-storm.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Very little to update you on. This chemo-storm still rages on, but there have been moments of relief, and it seems we will be able to weather this latest challenge. We are making full use of all the tools available to us – that is the prescriptions, and they are taking the edge off.</p>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<p><em>repeated</em></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Tina had an amazing number of days away, attending Marielle’s bridal shower. It was good break. Sam and I did managed well on our own, but by the end of this short time away Tina was definitely missed.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to be past the drug delivery phase of round 4. Each round bring us closer to the end of this journey.</p></li>
<li><p>This time the side effects more intense, with nausea, pain, fatigue, and general feeling rotten.</p></li>
<li><p>Complicating Sam’s cancer journey are Tina’s on-going health issues. Being in Vancouver may present opportunities for us to continue to look for additional solutions. We are hoping that referrals and connections to medical providers specific to her situation come together.</p></li>
<li><p>We hope that there will not be a need for the contingency plan, a bone marrow transplant, yet we need to prepare ourselves for this possibility.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-09_navigating-the-storm.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>In the storm</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-06_past-the-midway.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It is the morning of day 111 and we have crossed mid-way of the treatment plan. Saturday was the fifth and final day of chemo-drug delivery for this round. That afternoon we left the hospital, returning to the Ronald McDonald House. It felt good to get away from the hospital and find the quiet of our room here, but it has been hard.</p>
<p>The truth of it is this journey is hard, long and hard. Sam has been amazing, a few days ago, day 2 and 3 of this treatment, he was the brightest and most active I have seen him in months: playing games, seeking social connections, including making a new friend.</p>
<p>In general, we were all expecting this round to be easier. From the past experience this set of drugs did not hit as hard. However, by day 4 Sam was lethargic and had intense brain-fog. Now that we are out of the hospital we are catching up on sleep, The fog seems to be lifting, but nausea and pain need to be managed constantly. Generally, Sam just feels gross.</p>
<p>Sam longs for normal days and our return to normal life – we all do. I fear I do not remember what normal is or how to find it. This cancer-storm is swirling around us – it is difficult to see beyond it.</p>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Tina had an amazing number of days away, attending Marielle’s bridal shower. It was good break. Sam and I did managed well on our own, but by the end of this short time away Tina was definitely missed.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to be past the drug delivery phase of round 4. Each round bring us closer to the end of this journey.</p></li>
<li><p>This time the side effects more intense, with nausea, pain, fatigue, and general feeling rotten.</p></li>
<li><p>Complicating Sam’s cancer journey are Tina’s on-going health issues. Being in Vancouver may present opportunities for us to continue to look for additional solutions. We are hoping that referrals and connections to medical providers specific to her situation come together.</p></li>
<li><p>We hope that there will not be a need for the contingency plan, a bone marrow transplant, yet we need to prepare ourselves for this possibility.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-06_past-the-midway.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Friends and the beginning of round 4</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-02_round4-begins-friends.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I think this has been the longest gap between posts. My silence is has simply been a break and waiting.</p>
<p>This morning I am writing from Sam’s hospital room, as yesterday Sam began round 4 of chemotherapy, and as per the plan he will be in the hospital for five days of drug delivery. We did have a delay over the last week as we needed to wait for his body to recover from round 3.</p>
<p>It had been a quiet week until this past weekend when we were encouraged by the love of friends and family. Unplanned, we had several visits almost back to back. So good to see you all!!</p>
<section id="recent-visits" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recent-visits">Recent visits</h2>
<p>We had many great talks, some special activities, games, an ice cream run, and a couple bike rides. Sam was encouraged to see his friends and family – though he did not get to engage with the activities as much as his energy was low.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Jess and Kate B. took Tina to Bard on the Beach and the Symphony of Fire (fireworks). Back at the RMH I visited with John Sr.&nbsp;and Sam with his classmate John (jr.).</p></li>
<li><p>A surprise visit with Auntie Shannon and Uncle Kevin. We knew Kevin was going to be here but they surprised us with a visit with Tina’s sister.</p></li>
<li><p>Brian, Beth, David, and Luke H. were here. The boys and Sam hung out while</p></li>
<li><p>I was able to have a quick quality visit with Mike J.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Many thanks to all of you! Your presence, your words, your friendship have encouraged us!</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>I am thrilled for Tina as she will be leaving us for a few days to attend Marielle’s bridal shower (engaged to Kurtis F.). How will Tina do away from us? How will we do with out her?</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for the support of friends and family.</p></li>
<li><p>Perhaps it was the quieter week that gave us space to realize how tired we are. Recent visits have lifted us but we are definitely feeling this marathon.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful to keep going with the start of round 4. Each round bring us closer to the end of this journey.</p></li>
<li><p>The medical team here is great. Returning to the hospital is fairly easy. Many of the nurses know us and welcomed us back. Sam knows the routine and there is a comfort in the familiarity of it.</p></li>
<li><p>We hope that there will not be a need for the contingency plan (<a href="../../posts/2307/2023-07-17_contigency-plan.html">bone marrow transplant</a>), yet we need to prepare ourselves for it, and all the additional experiences and time that it may bring with it.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2308/2023-08-02_round4-begins-friends.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Quiet waiting</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-27_quiet-delay.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Sam has completed round 3 of his chemotherapy. This marks half way through the current treatment plan. However, we are delayed in starting round 4. With each round of chemo Sam’s immune system is knocked back and metrics monitoring this drop to zero. Before he is able to start the next round his body needs to recover. This time the recovery is slow… so we wait. With low levels Sam is also low energy and life has been fairly quiet.</p>
<section id="highlights-from-the-last-few-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights-from-the-last-few-days">Highlights from the last few days</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Last Friday Sam had transfusions that lifted his energy for a couple days. We went out to Ft. Langley to visit with my parents and Buddy.</p></li>
<li><p>A surprise party to celebrated my 50<sup>th</sup> with family!</p></li>
<li><p>My parents came to us here at the RMH bringing Buddy with them.</p></li>
<li><p>Quiet days at the RMH allowing Sam to recover from chemo</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Today marks 100 days of this marathon. I am exhausted. I think we are all exhausted. Perhaps it is these quieter days that give us enough space to feel and not just do the work of managing it all.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the successful completion of round three. Recovery from this round is taking a little longer. Round 4 should start next week.</p></li>
<li><p>We hope that there will not be a need for the contingency plan (<a href="../../posts/2307/2023-07-17_contigency-plan.html">bone marrow transplant</a>), yet we need to prepare ourselves for it, and all the additional experiences and time that it may bring with it.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-27_quiet-delay.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Monitoring, supplements, and Buddy!</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-23_monitoring-buddy.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/buddy-visit_20230721.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The highlight this week is the arrival of Gram, Papa C., and Buddy!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Sam is nearing the end of round 3 which will mark the half-way through this treatment regime. Generally, it has been slow and quiet week with trips back and forth to the clinic but there has been much anticipation in our minds for the arrival of my parents and Sam’s dog Buddy this past Friday.</p>
<p>For each of the clinic visits Sam’s energy was low, walking down the hall took significant effort, so we transported back and forth him by wheel chair. Thursday afternoon we were in to check levels to prepare for Friday’s LP<sup>1</sup>. Friday was a long day in the clinic: Platelets first, then the LP, and Hemoglobin provided in the afternoon.</p>
<p>With the completion of clinic procedures and a couple units of new blood Sam was ready to go. We packed up and made our way to Ft. Langley for a great reunion! Sam has been having great visits with my parents and Buddy these last couple days. So good for him, for all of us, to experience some normal life!</p>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that we can easily access to care here and the amazing medical team.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the successful completion of round three’s drug delivery phase! So far the side effects have been minimal. Sam is nearing the end of round 3.</p></li>
<li><p>We hope that there will not be a need for the contingency plan (<a href="../../posts/2307/2023-07-17_contigency-plan.html">bone marrow transplant</a>), yet we need to prepare ourselves for it, and all the additional time may bring with it.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>LP: Lumbar puncture, to monitor if cancer has crossed into the central nervous system and to provide chemo drugs into the spinal column as a preventative.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-23_monitoring-buddy.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Contingency planning</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-17_contigency-plan.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Sam had a clinic appointment this past Friday and honestly I had to let that conversation sit for a number of days before presenting it here. It was a really important conversation, one that I very much appreciated as the team is being proactive in Sam’s treatment. Despite this, I received it like a gut-punch.</p>
<p>What it came down to is making a contingency plan. Sam’s cancer is unknown and as such it is impossible to know if the current treatment will be fully effective. If it is not, then what next? We discussed the possibility of following the current treatment up with a bone marrow transplant. There is quite a lot of planning needed to move forward with a such a procedure as a donor needs to be found. So we are starting now.</p>
<p>The bone marrow transplant treatment, if needed, would start following the current treatment (~early Oct), and would add some significant time to our stay down here.</p>
<p>If it is needed, of course we will do it. We just hope that it is not needed.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Become a bone marrow donor
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://makeallthedifference.blood.ca/stem-cells-1/"><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/https:/www.blood.ca/themes/custom/cbs_bootstrap_sass/CBS_Logo_descriptors_RGB-WhiteBG.svg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="&quot;max-width:80%"></a></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It is easy to become a donor – no needles, just a cheek swab that you can do yourself.</p>
<p>Register via Canada Blood Services’ stem cell donor website:</p>
<p><a href="https://makeallthedifference.blood.ca/stem-cells-1/">https://makeallthedifference.blood.ca/stem-cells-1/</a></p>
<p>Perhaps you will be a match for Sam or someone else in need.</p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="the-past-few-days-including-a-hospital-visit" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-past-few-days-including-a-hospital-visit">The past few days – including a hospital visit</h2>
<p>This past weekend has been very quiet. As a family we managed one outing on Friday night to visit Uncle Kev. The remainder of our days have at RMH and for the most part in our room here. Sam is mid-way through this cycle of chemotherapy and as expected his blood counts are falling. This means that his energy levels are low, and that his immune system is compromised. The best thing we can do is keep him from getting sick – hide away until his system starts recovering.</p>
<section id="hospital-er-visit" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hospital-er-visit">Hospital ER visit</h3>
<p>Last night we paid a visit to the ER. Sam was having chest pain and headaches that would come in waves. The medical team pursued the potential for a blood embolus (throwing a clot) ordering ECGs, bloodwork, and a CT. After a few hours these pains subsided, and the tests were all clear. So a bit of a mystery but good that there was nothing serious.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that we can easily access to care here and the amazing medical team.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the successful completion of round three’s drug delivery phase! So far the side effects have been minimal. Sam is currently in the valley trying to avoid any secondary infections / flu, etc.</p></li>
<li><p>We hope that there will not be a need for the contingency plan, yet we need to prepare ourselves for it, and all the additional time may bring with it.</p></li>
<li><p>Last’s nights visit made us remember the blood clots associated with this cancer. Sam’s current medicines should keep them from being an issue but they remain a background concern.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <category>plans</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-17_contigency-plan.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Round 3 out-patient life</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-14_outpatient-life.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>There have been too many new-normals over the last number of years. Covid and post-covid transitions being the most obvious in our collective consciousness. It seems that we are finding another new-normal here as patterns of life are established. At the 3-4 week scale we have the pattern of hospital in-patient period of ~5 days (drug-delivery) followed by out-patient life.</p>
<p>Out patient life is where life begins to feel most normal, with meals, and activities. I am still amazed that activities are possible and that we have seen such a good return of Sam’s health. This week we had some unexpected encounters that brought some home-normality to life.</p>
<section id="the-last-few-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-last-few-days">The last few days</h2>
<dl>
<dt>July 10 - 13</dt>
<dd>
<p>Tuesday was the first clinic day following this round of chemo’s drug delivery. We also had a chance to review the results of the latest PET scan in more detail with Dr.&nbsp;C. Great to see the imagery of how the cancer is being reduced, and how Sam’s heart and lungs are now clear.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>We bumped into a classmate of Sam’s on our way out of the hospital. Tyler was here to have a check-up. Sam had a great visit him. Lisa and Tina had a great connection.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Shoshanna is here with her family. Great to catch up with them and plays some family games.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Ronald McDonald House provided a trip to Science World – we spent a couple hours there yesterday.</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Another regular life item: our van is in the shop … usual stuff: brakes and fluid leak repairs.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>Clinic appointments to monitor Sam’s ongoing health and blood levels.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are thankful for the successful completion of round three’s drug delivery phase! So far the side effects have been minimal with intermittent nausea and general fatigue.</p></li>
<li><p>Great to have some visits with our Prince George people.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for BC Children’s and the medical team here. Amazing that Sam is returning to health!</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that the cancer remains. We long for the day when Sam is clear of this disease.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-14_outpatient-life.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Round 3 hospital time and release</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-10_round3-hospital-time.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>We are now all back at the RMH. These last few days Sam was in hospital to receive the chemical delivery of ths current round of chemotherapy. All-in-all this round seems to be going well. Sam has such a great understanding of the process and because of that he asked to get his drugs pushed a little earlier each day. He had a goal in mind and with the assistance of the medical team he was able to achieve it. It was a simple goal – <em>Get out on Saturday</em>. And that is exactly what we did… it was a little late but it was worth it. We left the hospital a little before midnight and had a good sleep – without interruptions.</p>
<section id="the-last-few-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-last-few-days">The last few days</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Tuesday, July 4</dt>
<dd>
<p>Clinic day and start of round 3 of chemo.</p>
</dd>
<dt>July 5 - 8</dt>
<dd>
<p>Days in hospital for chemo drug delivery. Sam received a variety of different drugs. Generally, he had anywhere from two to four lines of medication including additional hydration running the whole time we were in hospital. The additional hydration was to ensure that his body not only received the chemicals but was able to process them without damaging his liver or kidneys. The inconvenience of hydration is that Sam was up every ~2.5 hours (day and night; I was up with him).</p>
</dd>
<dd>
<p>Nana was here and had great visits. Tina and her mom spent the much of their time at the RMH with visits to Sam. On the Friday Cal, Tricia, and Jane visited as well. Nana returned home on Saturday.</p>
</dd>
<dt>Sunday, July 9</dt>
<dd>
<p>Our first full day out. So far the only side effect that Sam has felt is fatigue but even this fatigue is better then his best days from a couple months ago. Kevin was able to come by and we hosted him with a BBQ here.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>Clinic appointments to monitor Sam’s ongoing health and blood levels. With each treatment his immune system is expected to crash. If the pattern from the previous rounds hold Sam should have a 3-4 more days of grace before he is left without immune defenses. He will have around a week where we will have to be careful and keep him away from any potential disease.</p>
<p>In a week-and-a-half my parents will be back down and they have arranged to bring Buddy with them.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that family for such a supportive family.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the successful completion of round three’s drug delivery phase!</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam has not had significant side effects from this round … though concern that they may yet arise.</p></li>
<li><p>We miss home: our friends and family there, our house, the neighborhood…<br>
I miss my work, my team, the forest, and the work itself.</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that it remains effective to fully remove the cancer.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>regular</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-10_round3-hospital-time.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Treatment progress and the start of round 3</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-05_round3-and-results.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Sam’s clinic appointment went as expected yesterday: bloodwork confirmed that his body was ready to start round 3. We were also able to discuss results of last week’s PET scan and lumbar puncture.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Last Thursday Sam had a lumbar puncture. A small amount of spinal fluid was removed and an equal amount of chemo-drugs was inserted. Analysis of the spinal fluid confirmed that there is no cancer in the central nervous system!</p></li>
<li><p>PET scan results – the treatment is working! Sam has two main cancerous masses one in his chest, and a smaller one in his neck. Results from the PET scan indicate that:</p>
<ul>
<li>Both masses are smaller then in the previous scan</li>
<li>The activity level of the cancer in the body is reduced</li>
<li>No new locations of cancer have been detected (i.e.&nbsp;it has not moved to other locations in the body)</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p><em>Note: Sam is receiving additional monitoring (i.e.&nbsp;more scans) then normal because his case is … not a normal cancer case. Since so little is known about this form of cancer additional monitoring is taking place. I expect this is for two purposes. First to confirm that the treatment is working. Second, to document that the treatment is working – adding to the pool of knowledge on cancer.</em></p>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>The next number of days will be here at the hospital while Sam receives his treatment. I will be with him through the nights. Tina and her mom will join us through the day. Tina and I may even get away for some additional time together while Nana visits.</p>
<p>This round of chemo includes some nastier drugs, though Sam is in a much stronger place then the last time he experienced them. Potential side effects are likely to include pain, nausea, GI sores, and further hair loss.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>We are thankful for positive results – that the treatment is working!</p></li>
<li><p>There is always concern that it remains effective to fully remove the cancer.</p></li>
<li><p>Specific more immediate concerns are the side effects from this current round of chemotherapy.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <category>results</category>
  <category>treatment</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-05_round3-and-results.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Happy anniversary and Canada Day</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-03_anniversay-canada-day.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/canada-day-delta.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Canada Day in Delta</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="highlights-from-the-past-few-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights-from-the-past-few-days">Highlights from the past few days</h2>
<p>This past weekend was spent like many of yours – celebrating Canada Day.</p>
<p>Sam’s day-to-day health is much improved. To look at him, other than the thin short hair, your might no know there was anything wrong. Since my last post:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Tina and I celebrated our 27<sup>th</sup> anniversary! We celebrated as a family out for a great meal and then ice cream.</p></li>
<li><p>Sam had his lumbar puncture and PET scan – results are pending.</p></li>
<li><p>Nana (Tina’s mom) arrived – she will be here for the week.</p></li>
<li><p>Celebrated Canada Day in North Delta where Kevin and Kelsey F. were the MCs for the activities there.</p></li>
<li><p>Townsend reunion with Tina, her mom, her siblings and most of their families – four generations.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>Tomorrow Sam returns to the hospital. We will check in at the day-clinic where:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>We will hear the results of this past weeks scans.</p></li>
<li><p>Check blood levels.</p></li>
<li><p>Start round 3 (i.e.&nbsp;begin delivery of chemotherapy drugs) – assuming blood levels are where they need to be.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Assuming all goes as planned Sam will be admitted tomorrow evening for a total of five days of chemo-drug delivery.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for my wife! We have had an amazing journey together though this latest chapter is the hardest we have faced. I am grateful to be able journey this storm with her.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that we are able to take part in normal activities! Happy Canada Day! Great to be with family.</p></li>
<li><p>Round 3 starts tomorrow. It has a different drug delivery regime then the last round and impacts will likely it will feel stronger.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that the treatment is working. There is also concern that it is effective to remove the cancer fully.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2307/2023-07-03_anniversay-canada-day.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Round 2 complete and some family fun</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-28_round-2-complete.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Chemo round 2 officially ended on the weekend and it has felt like a great success. Aside from 4 nights during the initial chemical delivery days and several clinic days, Sam spent the remainder of the time out of hospital. The majority of the days have been within the hospital campus, and over the last week we were able to spread our wings a little further as Sam’s immune system strengthened.</p>
<p>Though the lived experience of this round felt better, tests this week will determine what the unseen impacts were on the cancer. Sam will have a lumbar puncture and a PET scan over the next few days.</p>
<p>Next week Sam will return for some hospital days to begin round 3 of chemotherapy which, given it’s chemical makeup, may be harder on him then this last round.</p>
<section id="highlights-from-the-past-few-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights-from-the-past-few-days">Highlights from the past few days</h2>
<p>This past weekend we have had good time as a family and with the extended family.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>We were able to celebrate little Jayme’s birthday. Though Auntie Tricia and Uncle Cal also took the chance to spoil our boy – providing him a huge steak, which he enjoyed immensely.</p></li>
<li><p>Uncle Kevin started his new position in Delta and so we have been able to connect with them more. We spent an afternoon with Kevin and Kaden at Granville Island. Over the last few years Sam, Tina and I have made it there a number of times and have our favourite spots for snacks.</p></li>
<li><p>What do you do if your immune system is low and you want to go to the movies. The drive-in is a great option. The three of us had a great night taking in a double header … though we paid for it the following day.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that Sam has completed his second round of chemo as an out-patient.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful that we have family in the area.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that we are getting to know some families here.</p></li>
<li><p>Round 3 starts next week. It has a different drug delivery regime then the last round and impacts will likely it will feel stronger.K</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that the treatment is working. There is also concern that it is effective to remove the cancer fully.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-28_round-2-complete.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Out-patient life</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-24_out-patient.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/https:/samsstory.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/bike_kerrisdale.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Tina and I got out on bikes to the neighborhood of Kerrisdale.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Over a month ago one of our nurses told us that Sam would become an out-patient. At the time it seemed impossible. We were in the middle of round one, Sam was weak and sick, but it seems we have arrived at out-patient status. This morning marks day 19 of this round of chemotherapy – Sam has made it through the chemo-valley without the need of hospital time (his numbers are starting to recover). What a difference!</p>
<p>It is really weird as it seems we stumbled our way into this out-patient status. With the exception of four nights, when Sam received the chemo-chemicals, he has been out of the hospital for this round. Sam has had clinic appointments twice a week, and at each one we half-expected that he may need to be admitted. We know now that, even with dropping blood levels, if Sam keeps feeling good there was no need to return to the hospital. Living on the hospital campus makes out-patient life feasible as in the event Sam got sick (e.g.&nbsp;due to his chemo-compromised immune) we would simply visit the ER here and follow the oncology patient protocols.</p>
<section id="looking-back" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-back">Looking back</h2>
<p>The week as been a quiet one. Sam was in the valley where his blood levels were lowest. Yet his time there was dramatically better then last time. His energy levels were low and given that his immune system was at its weakest point he hid out for much of the week. A few highlights from this past week:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Playing cards with Minecraft with Sam</p></li>
<li><p>Slurpee-run therapy walks – the local corner store is about six blocks away. Sam is getting closer to walking all of the way there.</p></li>
<li><p>A couple outings for Tina and I. Including a bike ride to Kerrisdale.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="looking-ahead" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-ahead">Looking ahead</h2>
<p>The week ahead will include:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Continued recovery from this last round of chemo</p></li>
<li><p>Tests to monitor the state of the cancer in Sam’s body – to confirm it is still being reduced and that we can continue without having to adjust the treatment regime.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful that it Sam has made it through the second round of chemo as an out-patient.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful for the Ronald McDonald House, all the generosity supporting it, and all the volunteers serving here. This place makes living through this journey … almost feel like normal life.</p></li>
<li><p>Currently, one of our greatest challenges is that we have been away for over two months and it hard to stay connected with home. We miss you. We are thankful that Sam has been able to connect with friends on-line. We are thankful for visits and notes. However, despite these interactions, the nature of this cancer journey can feel isolating – for all of us.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that we are getting to know some families here.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that Sam has made it through round two!</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that the treatment is working. There is also concern that it is effective to remove the cancer fully.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-24_out-patient.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A second weekend at the RMH</title>
  <dc:creator>Colin C.</dc:creator>
  <link>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-19_rmh-weekend-2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I am not writing as often as, simply, there is not as much to say. Our days are normal<em>ish</em> – a good thing! Currently, we are not trying to understand what is happening, or what is next. It is good to have the stress level come down and have some time for mental recovery.</p>
<section id="the-last-couple-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-last-couple-days">The last couple days</h2>
<p>This weekend has been at the Ronald McDonald House (RMH) – our home away from home. On Saturday my parents got into town. It has been great to share meals and visit with them. A few quick highlights:</p>
<ul>
<li>Card games. Including Sam’s ongoing winning streak in crib. … I will attempt to humble him, if I can, in the week ahead.</li>
<li>A walk and ice cream. We continue to be encouraged with how Sam’s strength is returning.<br>
</li>
<li>A coffee date with Tina while Sam visited with his grandparents.</li>
<li>Father’s Day BBQ hosted by the RMH.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming">Upcoming</h2>
<p>Tomorrow, June 20, we will have a fourth clinic appointment to evaluate how Sam’s blood-levels are doing and if his immune system is holding.</p>
</section>
<section id="concerns-and-victories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concerns-and-victories">Concerns and victories</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Thankful for normal<em>ish</em> days.</p></li>
<li><p>Thankful for time with my parents.</p></li>
<li><p>Again, we are thankful that Sam is not feeling the effects of this chemotherapy round. The pending valley-of-gross appears to be getting smaller and smaller. Of course there is some concern as Sam’s blood levels continue to drop. Some days in hospital are still expected.</p></li>
<li><p>We are thankful that the treatment is working. There is also concern that it is effective to remove the cancer fully.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>daily</category>
  <guid>http://samc-news.netlify.app/posts/2023-06-19_rmh-weekend-2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
